<?xml version='1.0' encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "bg.dtd" [

<!ENTITY homepage "http://beej.us/guide/bgc/">

<!ENTITY copydates "2007">
<!ENTITY beejmail "beej@beej.us">

<!ENTITY esrsmartqs "http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">
<!ENTITY cclicenseurl "http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
<!ENTITY iocccurl "http://www.ioccc.org/">
<!ENTITY gccurl "http://www.gnu.org/software/gcc/gcc.html">
<!ENTITY dmarsurl "http://www.digitalmars.com/">
<!ENTITY vcurl "http://msdn.microsoft.com/visualc/">
<!ENTITY tcurl "http://community.borland.com/article/0,1410,20841,00.html">
]>

<guide id="index">

<guideinfo>
	<title>Beej's Guide to C Programming</title>

	<author>
		<name>Brian "Beej" Hall</name>
		<email>&beejmail;</email>
	</author>

	<version>Revision alpha-25</version>
	<date>May 17, 2007</date>

	<copyright>Copyright <copysym/> &copydates;  Brian "Beej" Hall</copyright>

	<dedication><p>I dedicate this guide to some of my biggest heroes and inpirators in
the world of computers: Donald Knuth, Bruce Schneier, W. Richard
Stevens, and The Woz, my Readership, and the entire Free and Open Source
Software Community.</p></dedication>

	<legal><p>Unless otherwise mutually agreed by the parties in
writing, the author offers the work as-is and makes no representations or
warranties of any kind concerning the work, express, implied, statutory
or otherwise, including, without limitation, warranties of title,
merchantibility, fitness for a particular purpose, noninfringement, or
the absence of latent or other defects, accuracy, or the presence of
absence of errors, whether or not discoverable.</p>

	<p>Except to the extent required by applicable law, in no event will
the author be liable to you on any legal theory for any special,
incidental, consequential, punitive or exemplary damages arising out of
the use of the work, even if the author has been advised
of the possibility of such damages.</p>

	<p>This document is freely distributable under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0
License. See the Copyright and Distribution section for
details.</p></legal>

	<comment><p>This book is written in XML using the vim editor on a
Slackware Linux box loaded with GNU tools.  The cover "art" and diagrams
are produced with Inkscape.  The XML is converted into HTML and XSL-FO
by custom Python scripts. The XSL-FO output is then munged by Apache FOP
to produce PDF documents, using Liberation fonts.  The toolchain is
composed of 100% Free and Open Source Software.</p></comment>

</guideinfo>

<!-- ======================================================= -->
<!-- Introduction -->
<!-- ======================================================= -->
<sect1 id="intro">
<title>Foreward</title>

<p>No point in wasting words here, folks, let's jump straight into the
C code:</p>

<code>E((ck?main((z?(stat(M,&amp;t)?P+=a+'{'?0:3:
execv(M,k),a=G,i=P,y=G&amp;255,
sprintf(Q,y/'@'-3?A(*L(V(%d+%d)+%d,0)</code>

<p>And they lived happily ever after.  The End.</p>

<p>What's this?  You say something's still not clear about this whole C
programming language thing?</p>

<p>Well, to be quite honest, I'm not even sure what the above code does.
It's a snippet from one of the entires in the 2001 <ulink
url="&iocccurl;">International Obfuscated C Code Contest</ulink>, a
wonderful competition wherein the entrants attempt to write the most
unreadable C code possible, with often surprising results.</p>

<p>The bad news is that if you're a beginner in this whole thing, all
C code you see looks obfuscated!  The good news is, it's not going to be
that way for long.</p>

<p>What we'll try to do over the course of this guide is lead you from
complete and utter sheer lost confusion on to the sort of enlightened
bliss that can only be obtained though pure C programming.  Right on.</p>

<!-- Audience -->
<sect2 id="audience">
<title>Audience</title>

<p>As with most Beej's Guides, this one tries to cater to people who are
just starting on the topic.  That's you!  If that's not you for whatever
reason the best I can hope to provide is some pastey entertainment for
your reading pleasure.  The only thing I can reasonably promise is that
this guide won't end on a cliffhanger...or <emp>will</emp> it?</p>

</sect2>

<!-- Platform -->
<sect2 id="platform">
<title>Platform and Compiler</title>

<p>I'll try to stick to Good Ol'-Fashioned ANSI C, just like Mom used to
bake.  Well, for the most part.  Here and there I talk about things that
are in subsequent C standards, just to try to keep up to date.</p>

<p>My compiler of choice is GNU <com>gcc</com> since that's
available on most systems, including the Linux systems on which I
work.</p>

<p>Since the code is basically standard, it should build with virtually
any C compiler on virtually any platform.  If you're using Windows, run
the result in a DOS window.  All sample code will be using the console
(that's "text window" for you kids out there), except for the sample
code that doesn't.</p>

<p>There are a lot of compilers out there, and virtually all of them
will work for this book.  And for those not in the know, a C++ compiler
will compile C most code, so it'll work for the purposes of this guide.
Some of the compilers I am familiar with are the following:</p>

<list>
<li><b><ulink url="&gccurl;">GCC</ulink></b>: GNU's C compiler,
available for almost every platform, and popularly installed on Unix
machines.</li>

<li><b><ulink url="&dmarsurl;">Digital Mars C/C++</ulink></b>: The
hackers at Digital Mars have a pretty rippin' C/C++ compiler for Windows
that you can download and use for free, and that will work wonderfully
for all the code presented in this guide.  I highly recommend it.</li>

<li><b><ulink url="&vcurl;">VC++</ulink></b>: Microsoft's Visual C++ for
Windows.  This is the standard that most Microsoft programmers use, and
I freaking hate it.  Nothing personal, but I'm one of those crazy people
that still uses <com>vi</com>.</li>

<li><b><ulink url="&tcurl;">Turbo C</ulink></b>: This is a classic
compiler for MSDOS.  It's downloadable for free, and I has a special
place in my heart.  (It can't handle the "<tt>//</tt>"-style comments,
so they should all be converted to "<tt>/**/</tt>"-style.)</li>

<li><b><tt>cc</tt></b>: Virtually every Unix system has a C compiler
installed, and they're typically and merely named <tt>cc</tt> (C
Compiler, see?)  Just try it from the command line and see what
happens!</li>

</list>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="unixbuild">
<title>Building under Unix</title>

<p>If you have a source file called <file>foo.c</file>, it can be built
with the following command from the shell:</p>

<screen>gcc -o foo foo.c</screen>

<p>This tells the compiler to build <file>foo.c</file>, and output an
executable called <file>foo</file>.  If <com>gcc</com> doesn't work,
try using just <com>cc</com> instead.</p>

</sect2>

<!-- Homepage -->
<sect2 id="homepage">
<title>Official Homepage</title>

<p>This official location of this document is
<ulink url="&homepage;" footnote="y">&homepage;</ulink>.  Maybe
this'll change in the future, but it's more likely that all the other
guides are migrated off Chico State computers.</p>

</sect2>

<!-- Email policy -->
<sect2 id="emailpolicy">
<title>Email Policy</title>

<p>I'm generally available to help out with email questions so feel free
to write in, but I can't guarantee a response.  I lead a pretty busy
life and there are times when I just can't answer a question you have.
When that's the case, I usually just delete the message.  It's nothing
personal; I just won't ever have the time to give the detailed answer
you require.</p>

<p>As a rule, the more complex the question, the less likely I am to
respond.  If you can narrow down your question before mailing it and be
sure to include any pertinent information (like platform, compiler,
error messages you're getting, and anything else you think might help me
troubleshoot), you're much more likely to get a response.  For more
pointers, read ESR's document, <ulink url="&esrsmartqs;">How To Ask
Questions The Smart Way</ulink>.</p>

<p>If you don't get a response, hack on it some more, try to find the
answer, and if it's still elusive, then write me again with the
information you've found and hopefully it will be enough for me to help
out.</p>

<p>Now that I've badgered you about how to write and not write me, I'd
just like to let you know that I <emp>fully</emp> appreciate all the
praise the guide has received over the years.  It's a real morale boost,
and it gladdens me to hear that it is being used for good! <smiley/>
Thank you!</p>

</sect2>

<!-- Mirroring -->
<sect2 id="mirroring">
<title>Mirroring</title>

<p>You are more than welcome to mirror this site, whether publically or
privately.  If you publically mirror the site and want me to link to it
from the main page, drop me a line at <email>&beejmail;</email>.</p>

</sect2>

<!-- Translators -->
<sect2 id="xlations">
<title>Note for Translators</title>

<p><!--<ii key="translations"/>-->If you want to translate the guide into
another language, write me at <email>&beejmail;</email> and I'll link to
your translation from the main page. Feel free to add your name and
contact info to the translation.</p>

<p>Please note the license restrictions in the Copyright and
Distribution section, below.</p>

<p>Sorry, but due to space constraints, I cannot host the
translations myself.</p>

</sect2>

<!-- Copyright -->
<sect2 id="copylic">
<title>Copyright and Distribution</title>

<p>Beej's Guide to Network Programming is Copyright <copysym/> &copydates;
Brian "Beej Jorgensen" Hall.</p>

<p>With specific exceptions for source code and translations, below,
this work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-
Noncommercial- No Derivative Works 3.0 License. To view a copy of this
license, visit <tt><ulink url="&cclicenseurl;"
footnote="n">&cclicenseurl;</ulink></tt> or send a letter to Creative
Commons, 171 Second Street, Suite 300, San Francisco, California, 94105,
USA.</p>

<p>One specific exception to the "No Derivative Works" portion of the
license is as follows: this guide may be freely translated into any
language, provided the translation is accurate, and the guide is
reprinted in its entirety.  The same license restrictions apply to the
translation as to the original guide.  The translation may also include
the name and contact information for the translator.</p>

<p>The C source code presented in this document is hereby granted to the
public domain, and is completely free of any license restriction.</p>

<p>Educators are freely encouraged to recommend or supply copies of this
guide to their students.</p>

<p>Contact <email>&beejmail;</email> for more information.</p>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- /Introduction -->


<!-- ======================================================= -->
<!-- Programming Building Blocks -->
<!-- ======================================================= -->
<sect1 id="bblox">
<title>Programming Building Blocks</title>

<quote><p><emp>"Where do these stairs go?"</emp><br/>
<emp>"They go up."</emp><br/>
--Ray Stantz and Peter Venkman, Ghostbusters</p></quote>

<p>What is programming, anyway?  I mean, you're learning how to do it,
but what is it?  Well, it's, umm, kind of like, well, say you have this
multilayered chocolate and vanilla cake sitting on top of an internal
combustion engine and the gearbox is connected to the coil with a
banana.  Now, if you're eating the cake a la mode, that means... Wait.
Scratch that analogy.  I'll start again.</p>

<p>What is programming, anyway?  It's telling the computer how to
perform a task.  So you need two things (besides your own self and a
computer) to get going.  One thing you need is the task the computer is
to perform.  This is easy to get as a student because the teacher will
hand you a sheet of paper with an assignment on it that describes
exactly what the computer is to do for you to get a good grade.</p>

<p>If you don't want a good grade, the computer can do that without your
intervention.  But I digress.</p>

<p>The second thing you need to get started is the knowledge of how to
tell the computer to do these things.  It turns out there are lots of
ways to get the computer to do a particular task...just like there are
lots of ways to ask someone to please obtain for me my fluffy foot
covering devices in order to prevent chilliness.  Many of these ways are
right, and a few of them are best.</p>

<p>What you can do as a programmer, though, is get through the
assignments doing something that works, and then look back at it and see
how you could have made it better or faster or more concise. This is one
thing that seriously differentiates programmers from excellent
programmers.</p>

<p>Eventually what you'll find is that the stuff you wrote back in
college (e.g. The Internet Pizza Server, or, say, my entire Masters
project) is a horridly embarrassing steaming pile of code that was quite
possibly the worst thing you've ever written.</p>

<p>The only way to go is up.</p>

<!-- "The Specification" -->
<sect2 id="specification">
<title>The Specification</title>

<quote><p><emp>In the beginning was the plan</emp><br/>
<emp>And then came the assumptions</emp><br/>
<emp>And the assumptions were without form</emp><br/>
<emp>And the plan was completely without substance</emp><br/>
<emp>And the darkness was upon the face of workers</emp><br/>
--Excerpt from The Plan, early Internet folklore</p></quote>

<p>Ooooo!  Prostrate yourself, mortal, in the face of The
Specification!</p>

<p>Ok, maybe I'm being a little too overdramatic here.  But I wanted to
stress just mildly and subtly, if you might indulge me, that <b><emp>The
Specification</emp></b> BWHAHAHA <emp>*THUNDERCLAP*</emp> (Sorry!  Sorry!) is
something you should spend time absorbing before your fingers touch the
keyboard.  Except for checking your mail and reading Slashdot,
obviously.  That goes without saying.</p>

<p>So what do you do with this specification?  It's a description of
what the program is going to do, right?  But where to begin?  What you
need to do is this: break down the design into handy bite-sized pieces
that you can implement using techniques you know work in those
situations.</p>

<p>As you learn C, those bite-sized pieces will correspond to function
calls or statements that you will have learned.  As you learn to program
in general, those bite-sized pieces will start corresponding to larger
algorithms that you know (or can easily look up.)</p>

<p>Right now, you might not know any of the pieces that you have at your
disposal.  That's ok.  The fastest way to learn them is to, right now,
press the mouse to your forehead and say the password, "K&amp;R2".</p>

<p>That didn't work?  Hmmm.  There must be a problem with the system
somewhere.  Ok, we'll do it the old-school way: learning stuff by
hand.</p>

<p>Let's have an example:</p>

<offsettext><p><b>Assignment:</b> Implement a program that will
calculate the sum of all numbers between 1 and the number the user
enters.  The program shall output the result.</p></offsettext>

<p>Ok, well, that summary is pretty high level and doesn't lend itself
to bite-sized pieces, so it's up to us to split it up.</p>

<p>There are several places that are good to break up pieces to be more
bite-sized.  Input is one thing to break out, output is another.  If you
need to input something, or output something, each of those is a handy
bite-sized piece.  If you need to calculate something, that can be
another bite-sized piece (though the more difficult calculations can be
made up of many pieces themselves!)</p>

<p>So, moving forward through a sample run of the program:</p>

<numlist>
<li>We need the program to read a number from the keyboard.</li>
<li>We need the program to compute a result using that number.</li>
<li>We need the program to output the result.</li>
</numlist>

<p>This is good!  We've identified the parts of the assignment that need
to be worked on.</p>

<p>"Wait!  Stop!"  I hear you.  You're wondering how we knew it was
broken down into enough bite-sized pieces, and, in fact, how we even
know those are bite-sized pieces, anyhow!  For all you know, reading a
number from the keyboard could be a hugely involved task!</p>

<p>The short of it is, well, you caught me trying to pull a fast one on
you.  <emp>I</emp> know these are bite-sized because in my head I can
correspond them to simple C function calls or statements.  Outputting
the result, for instance, is one line of code (very bite-sized).  But
that's me and we're talking about you.  In your case, I have a little
bit of a chicken-and-egg problem: you need to know what the bite-sized
pieces of the program are so you can use the right functions and
statements, and you need to know what the functions and statements are
in order to know how to split the project up into bite-sized pieces!
Hell's bells!</p>

<p>So we're compromising a bit.  I agree to tell you what the statements
and functions are if <emp>you</emp> agree to keep this stuff about
bite-sized pieces in the back of your head while we progress.  Ok?</p>

<p>...I said, "Ok?"  And you answer... "Ok, I promise to keep this
bite-sized pieces stuff in mind."  Excellent!</p>

</sect2>

<!-- "The Implementation" -->
<sect2 id="implementation">
<title>The Implementation</title>

<p>Right!  Let's take that example from the previous section and see how
we're going to actually implement it.  Remember that once you have the
specification (or assignment, or whatever you're going to call it)
broken up into handy bite-sized pieces, then you can start writing the
instuctions to make that happen.  Some bite-sized pieces might only have
one statement; others might be pages of code.</p>

<p>Now here we're going to cheat a little bit again, and I'm going to
tell you what you'll need to call to implement our sample program.  I
know this because I've done it all before and looked it all up.  You,
too, will soon know it for the same reasons.  It just takes time and a
lot of reading what's in the reference section of your C books.</p>

<p>So, let's take our steps, except this time, we'll write them with a
little more information.  Just bear with me through the syntax here and
try to make the correlation between this and the bite-sized pieces
mentioned earlier.  All the weird parentheses and squirrely braces will
make sense in later sections of the guide.  Right now what's important
is the steps and the translation of those steps to computer code.</p>

<p>The steps, partially translated:</p>

<numlist>
<li>Read the number from the keyboard using <func>scanf()</func>.</li>
<li>Compute the sum of the numbers between one and the entered number
using a <func>for</func>-loop and the addition operator.</li>
<li>Print the result using <func>printf()</func>.</li>
</numlist>

<p>Normally, this partial translation would just take place in your
head.  You need to output to the console?  You know that the
<func>printf()</func> function is one way to do it.</p>

<p>And as the partial translation takes place in your head, what better
time than that to actually code it up using your favorite editor:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	int num, result = 0, i;

	scanf("%d", &amp;num); // read the number from the keyboard

	for(i = 1; i &lt;= num; i++) { // compute the result
		result += i;
	}

	printf("%d\n", result); // output the result

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Remember how I said there were multiple ways to do things?  Well, I
didn't have to use <func>scanf()</func>, I didn't have to use a
<func>for</func>-loop, and I didn't have to use <func>printf()</func>.
But they were the best for this example.  <smiley/></p>

</sect2>

<!-- "So Much To Do, So Little Time" -->
<sect2 id="somuchtodo">
<title>So Much To Do, So Little Time</title>

<p>Another name for this section might have been, "Why can't I write
a Photoshop clone in half an hour?"</p>

<p>Lots of people when they first start programming become disheartened
because they've just spent all this effort to learn this whole
programming business and what do they have to show for it: a little
text-based program that prints a string that looks like it's some
prehistoric throwback to 1979.</p>

<p>Well, I wish I could sugarcoat this a little bit more, but that is
unfortunately the way it tends to go when you're starting out.  Your
first assignment is unlikely to be DOOM III, and is more likely to
be something similar to:</p>

<screen>Hello, I am the computer and I know that 2+2 =   4!</screen>

<p>You elite coder, you.</p>

<p>Remember, though, how I said that eventually you'll learn to
recognize larger and larger bite-sized pieces?  What you'll eventually
built up is a set of <emp>libraries</emp> (collections of reusable code)
that you can use as building blocks for other programs.</p>

<p>For example, when I want to draw a bitmap on the screen, do I write a
system to read the bytes of the file, decode the JPEG image format,
detect video hardware, determine video memory layout, and copy the
results onto the display?  Well do I, punk?  No.  I call
<func>loadJPEG()</func>.  I call <func>displayImage()</func>.  These
are examples of functions that have already been written for my use.
That makes it easy!</p>

<p>So you can plan ahead and figure out which components can be built up
and reused, or you can use components that other people have built for
you.</p>

<p>Examples pre-built components are: the standard C library
(<func>printf()</func>, which we'll be using a lot of in this guide),
the GTK+ library (a GUI library used with GNOME), the Qt toolkit (a GUI
library used with the K Desktop), libSDL (a library for doing graphics),
OpenGL (a library for doing 3D graphics), and so on, and so on.  You can
use all these to your own devious ends and you don't have to write them
again!</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="helloworld">
<title>Hello, World!</title>

<p>This is the canonical example of a C program.  Everyone uses it:</p>

<code>/* helloworld program */

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	printf("Hello, World!\n");

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>We're going to don our long-sleeved heavy-duty rubber gloves, grab a
scapel, and rip into this thing to see what makes it tick.  So, scrub
up, because here we go.  Cutting very gently...</p>

<p>Let's get the easy thing out of the way: anything between the
digraphs <tt>/*</tt> and <tt>*/</tt> is a comment and will be completely
ignored by the compiler.  This allows you to leave messages to yourself
and others, so that when you come back and read your code in the distant
future, you'll know what the heck it was you were trying to do.  Believe
me, you will forget; it happens.</p>

<p>(Modern C compilers also treat anything after a <tt>//</tt> as a
comment.  GCC will obey it, as will VC++.  However, if you are using an
old compiler like Turbo C, well, the <tt>//</tt> construct was a little
bit before its time.  So I'll try to keep it happy and use the old-style
<tt>/*comments*/</tt> in my code.  But everyone uses <tt>//</tt> these days
when adding a comment to the end of a line, and you should feel free
to, as well.)</p>

<p>Now, what is this <tt>#include</tt>?  GROSS!  Well, it tells the C
Preprocessor to pull the contents of another file and insert it into the
code right <emp>there</emp>.</p>

<p>Wait&emdash;what's a C Preprocessor?  Good question.  There are two
stages (well, technically there are more than two, but hey, let's
pretend there are two and have a good laugh) to compilation: the
preprocessor and the compiler.  Anything that starts with pound sign, or
"octothorpe", (<tt>#</tt>) is something the preprocessor operates on
before the compiler even gets started.  Common <emp>preprocessor
directives</emp>, as they're called, are <tt>#include</tt> and
<tt>#define</tt>.  More on that later.</p>

<p>Before we go on, why would I even begin to bother pointing out that a
pound sign is called an octothorpe?  The answer is simple: I think the
word octothorpe is so excellently funny, I have to gratuitiously spread
its name around whenever I get the opportunity.  Octothorpe.
Octothorpe, octothorpe, octothorpe.</p>

<p>So <emp>anyway</emp>.  After the C preprocessor has finished
preprocessing everything, the results are ready for the compiler to take
them and produce assembly code, machine code, or whatever it's about to
do.  Don't worry about the technical details of compilation for now;
just know that your source runs through the preprocessor, then the
output of that runs through the compiler, then that produces an
executable for you to run.  Octothorp.</p>

<p>What about the rest of the line?  What's <tt>&lt;stdio.h&gt;</tt>?
That is what is known as a <emp>header file</emp>.  It's the dot-h at the
end that gives it away.  In fact it's the "Standard IO" (stdio) header
file that you will grow to know and love.  It contains preprocessor
directives and function prototypes (more on that later) for common input
and output needs.  For our demo program, we're outputting the string
"Hello, World!", so we in particular need the function prototype for the
<func>printf()</func> function from this header file.</p>

<p>How did I know I needed to <tt>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;</tt> for
<func>printf()</func>?  Answer: it's in the documentation.  If you're on
a Unix system, <com>man printf</com> and it'll tell you right at the top
of the man page what header files are required.  Or see the reference
section in this book. <smiley/></p>

<p>Holy moly.  That was all to cover the first line!  But, let's face
it, it has been completely dissected.  No mystery shall remain!</p>

<p>So take a breather...look back over the sample code.  Only a couple
easy lines to go.</p>

<p>Welcome back from your break!  I know you didn't really take a break;
I was just humoring you.</p>

<p>The next line is <func>main()</func>.  This is the definition
of the function <func>main()</func>; everything between the squirrely
braces (<tt>{</tt> and <tt>}</tt>) is part of the function
definition.</p>

<p>A <emp>function</emp>.  "Great!  More terminology I don't know!"  I
feel your pain, but can only offer you the cold heartless comfort of
more words: a function is a collection of code that is to be executed as
a group when the function is called.  You can think of it as, "When I
call <func>main()</func>, all the stuff in the squirrley braces will be
executed, and not a moment before."</p>

<p>How do you call a function, anyway?  The answer lies in the
<func>printf()</func> line, but we'll get to that in a minute.</p>

<p>Now, the main function is a special one in many ways, but one way
stands above the rest: it is the function that will be called
automatically when your program starts executing.  Nothing of yours gets
called before <func>main()</func>.  In the case of our example, this
works fine since all we want to do is print a line and exit.</p>

<p>Oh, that's another thing: once the program executes past the end of
<func>main()</func>, down there at the closing squirrley brace, the
program will exit, and you'll be back at your command prompt.</p>

<p>So now we know that that program has brought in a header file,
<tt>stdio.h</tt>, and declared a <func>main()</func> function that will
execute when the program is started.  What are the goodies in
<tt>main()</tt>?</p>

<p>I am so happy you asked.  Really.  We only have the one goodie: a
call to the function <func>printf()</func>.  You can tell this is a
function call and not a function definition in a number of ways, but one
indicator is the lack of squirrely braces after it.  And you end the
function call with a semicolon so the compiler knows it's the end of the
expression.  You'll be putting semicolons after most everything, as
you'll see.</p>

<p>You're passing one parameter to the function <func>printf()</func>: a
string to be printed when you call it.  Oh, yeah&emdash;we're calling a
function!  We rock!  Wait, wait&emdash;don't get cocky.  What's that
crazy <tt>\n</tt> at the end of the string?  Well, most characters in
the string look just like they are stored.  But there are certain
characters that you can't print on screen well that are embedded as
two-character backslash codes.  One of the most popular is <tt>\n</tt>
(read "backslash-N") that corresponds to the <emp>newline</emp>
character.  This is the character that causing further printing to
continue on the next line instead of the current.  It's like hitting
return at the end of the line.</p>

<p>So copy that code into a file, build it, and run it&emdash;see what
happens:</p>

<screen>Hello, World! </screen>

<p>It's done and tested!  Ship it!</p>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="sve">
<title>Variables, Expressions, and Statements (Oh My)</title>

<quote><p><emp>"It takes all kinds to make a world, does it not,
Padre?"</emp><br/>
<emp>"So it does, my son, so it does."</emp><br/>
Pirate Captain Thomas Bartholomew Red to the Padre, Pirates</p></quote>

<p>There sure can be lotsa stuff in a C program.</p>

<p>Yup.</p>

<p>And for various reasons, it'll be easier for all of us if we classify
some of the types of things you can find in a program, so we can be
clear what we're talking about.</p>

<sect2 id="variables">
<title>Variables</title>

<p>A variable is simply a name for a number.  The number associated with
that variable is said to be it's <emp>value</emp>.  You can change the
value later, too.  One minute a variable named <var>foo</var> might have
the value 2, the next you might change it to 3.  It's
<emp>variable</emp>, see?</p>

<p>Variables can have different <emp>types</emp>, as well.  In C,
because it's such a picky language about types (I'm saying that
emphatically to make strongly-typed language fanatics roll in their
future graves) you have to know in advance what type of numbers you'll
be storing in the variable.</p>

<p>Before you can use a variable in your code, you have to
<emp>declare</emp> it.  This way the compiler knows in advance as it
runs down your program how to treat any variables.  Here is an example
that shows a number of different types, and their corresponding sets of
numbers they represent:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int i;	  /* holds signed integers, e.g. -3, -2, 0, 1, 10 */
	float f;  /* holds signed floating point numbers, e.g. -3.1416 */

	printf("Hello, World!\n"); /* ah, blessed familiarity */

	return 0;
}</code>
	
<p>In the above example, we've declared a couple of variables.  We
haven't used them yet, and they're both uninitialized.  One holds an
integer number (random, to start, since we never initialized it), and
the other holds a floating point number (a real number, basically.)</p>

<p>What's this?  You want to store some numbers in those variables?
Well, ask your mother; if it's all right with her, it's all right with
me.</p>

<p>So, how to do that...you use the <emp>assignment</emp> operator.  An
operator is generally a piece of punctuation that operates on two
expressions to produce a result.  There are a number of them, like the
addition operator (<tt>+</tt>) and the subtraction operator
(<tt>-</tt>), but I'm getting ahead of myself.  We'll talk about those
more in the expressions section, below.  In this case, we're going to
use the assignment operator, which is <tt>=</tt>, to assign a value into
a variable:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int i;

	i = 2; /* assign the value 2 into the variable i */

	printf("Hello, World!\n");

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Killer.  We've stored a value.  But don't run off and implement a
clone of Quake III just yet; let's try to do something with that
variable, just so we can say we did.  Let's print it out using
<func>printf()</func>, for instance.</p>

<p>We're going to do that by passing <emp>two</emp> parameters to the
<func>printf()</func> function.  The first argument is a string that
describes what to print and how to print it (called the <emp>format
string</emp>), and the second is the value to print, namely whatever is
in the variable <var>i</var>.</p>

<p><func>printf()</func> hunts through the format strings for a variety of
special sequences which start with a percent sign (<tt>%</tt>) that tell
it what to print.  For example, if it finds a <tt>%d</tt>, it looks to
the next parameter that was passed, and prints it out as an integer.  If
it finds a <tt>%f</tt>, it prints the value out as a float.</p>

<p>As such, we can print out the value of <var>i</var> like so:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int i;

	i = 2; /* assign the value 2 into the variable i */

	printf("Hello, World!  The value of i is %d, okay?\n", i);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>And the output will be:</p>

<screen>Hello, World!  The value of i is 2, okay?</screen>

<p>And now, on to expressions!  We'll do all kinds of fancy stuff with
these variables.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="operators">
<title>Operators</title>

<p>I've snuck a few quick ones past you already when it comes to
expressions.  You've already seen things like:</p>

<code>result += i;
i = 2;</code>

<p>Those are both expressions.  In fact, you'll come to find that most
everything in C is an expression of one form or another.  But here for
the start I'll just tell you about a few common types of operators that
you probably want to know about.</p>

<code>i = i + 3;  /* addition (+) and assignment (=) operators */
i = i - 8;  /* subtraction, subtract 8 from i */
i = i / 2;  /* division */
i = i * 9;  /* multiplication */
i++;		/* add one to i ("post-increment"; more later) */
++i;		/* add one to i ("pre-increment") */
i--;		/* subtract one from i ("post-decrement") */</code>

<p>Looks pretty weird, that <tt>i = i + 3</tt> expression, huh.  I mean,
it makes no sense algebraically, right?  That's true, but it's because
it's not really algebra.  That's not an equivalency
statement&emdash;it's an assignment.  Basically it's saying whatever
variable is on the left hand side of the assignment (=) is going to be
assigned the value of the expression on the right.  So it's all ok.</p>

<p>An expression?  What's that?  Sorry, but I'm far to lazy to cover it
here, so I'll cover it in the next section.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="expressions">
<title>Expressions</title>

<p>This is actually one of the most important sections in the guide
about C.  So pay attention and be seated, you naughty children!</p>

<p>Now that everything's in order, we'll...actually, let's do the
important part a little later.  But since you're already seated, let's
get started.</p>

<p>An expression in C consists of other expressions optionally put
together with operators.  I know that's a self-referential definition,
but those are always good for a laugh, aren't they?  (Pick up any old C
book and look up <emp>recursion</emp> in the index and see what pages it
leads you to.)</p>

<p>The basic building block expressions that you put together with
operators are variables, constant numbers (like <const>10</const> or
<const>12.34</const>), and functions.  (We'll talk about functions
later, although if you recall we've already had a run-in with the
<func>printf()</func> function.)</p>

<p>And so when you chain these together with operators, the result is an
expression, as well.  All of the following are valid C expressions:</p>

<code>i = 3
i++
i = i + 12
i + 12
2 
f += 3.14</code>

<p>Now where can you use these expressions?  Well, you can use them in a
function call (I know, I know&emdash;I'll get to function real soon
now), or as the right hand side of an assignment.  You have to be more
careful with the left side of an assignment; you can only use certain
things there, but for now suffice it to say it must be a single variable
on the left side of the assignment, and not a complicated
expression:</p>

<code>radius = circumference / (2.0 * 3.14159);		/* valid */
diameter / 2 = circumference / (2.0 * 3.14159);  /* INVALID */</code>

<p>(I also slipped more operator stuff in there&emdash;the parentheses.
These cause part of an expression (yes, any old expression) to be
evaluated first by the compiler, before more of the expression is
computed.  This is just like parentheses work in algebra.)</p>

<p>Well, I was going to talk about that important thing in this section,
but now it looks like we're running behind a bit, so let's postpone it
until later.  I promise to catch up, don't you fear!</p>
	
</sect2>

<!--
<sect2 id="datatypes">
<title>Data Types</title>

<p>Ok, here we are.  The reason I'm so gung-ho about this chapter is
that my C instructor once told me "know your data types!"  That didn't
really mean anything to me at the time, but subsequent hours spent
answering questions in the lab showed me the Truth of the Assertion.</p>

<p>"Know your data types!"</p>  This'll be even more important when we
talk about pointers later on, but let's start with some easy ones that
require no mind bending

</sect2>
-->

<sect2 id="statements">
<title>Statements</title>

<p>For the most part, you're free to make up variable names to your
heart's content, calling them whatever you'd like.  There are no
exceptions, except for statements and other <emp>reserved words</emp>
which you may not use unless you use them in the officially (by the
compiler) prescribed manner.</p>

<p>That definition was rather glib.  I should rewrite it.  Or maybe
we'll just sojourn bravely on!  Yes!</p>

<p>What are these pesky statements?  Let's say, completely
hypothetically, you want to do something more than the already amazingly
grand example program of assigning a value to a variable and printing
it.  What if you only want to print it if the number is less than 10?
What if you want to print all numbers between it and 10?  What if you
want to only print the number on a Thursday?  All these incredible
things and more are available to you through the magic of various
statements.</p>

<sect3 id="ifstat">
<title>The <statement>if</statement> statement</title>

<p>The easiest one to wrap your head around is the conditional
statement, <statement>if</statement>.  It can be used to do (or not do)
something based on a condition.</p>

<p>Like what kind of condition?  Well, like is a number greater than
10?</p>

<code>int i = 10;

if (i > 10) {
	printf("Yes, i is greater than 10.\n");
	printf("And this will also print if i is greater than 10.\n");
}

if (i &lt;= 10) printf("i is less than or equal to 10.\n");</code>

<p>In the example code, the message will print if <var>i</var> is
greater than 10, otherwise execution continues to the next line.  Notice
the squirrley braces after the <statement>if</statement> statement; if
the condition is true, either the first statement or expression right
after the if will be executed, or else the collection of code in the
squirlley braces after the <statement>if</statement> will be executed.
This sort of <emp>code block</emp> behavior is common to all
statements.</p>

<p>What are the conditions?</p>

<code> i == 10;       /* true if i is equal to 10 */
i != 10;       /* true if i is not equal to 10 */
i &gt; 10;        /* true if i greater than 10 */
i &lt; 10;        /* true if i less than 10 */
i &gt;= 10;       /* true if i greater than  or equal to 10 */
i &lt;= 10;       /* true if i less than or equal to 10 */</code>

<p>Guess what these all are?  No really, guess.  They're expressions!
Just like before!  So statements take an expression (some statements
take multiple expressions) and evaluate them.  The
<statement>if</statement> statement evaluates to see if the expression
is true, and then executes the following code if it is.</p>

<p>What is "true" anyway?  C doesn't have a "true" keyword like C++
does.  In C, any non-zero value is true, and a zero value is false.  For
instance:</p>

<code>
if (1)      printf("This will always print.\n");
if (-3490)  printf("This will always print.\n");
if (0)      printf("This will never print.  Ever.\n");</code>

<p>And the following will print <tt>1</tt> followed by <tt>0</tt>:</p>

<code>int i = 10;

printf("%d\n", i == 10); /* i == 10 is true, so it's 1 */
printf("%d\n", i > 20);  /* i is not > 20, so this is false, 0 */</code>

<p>(Hey, look!  We just passed those expressions as arguments to the
function <func>printf()</func>!  Just like we said we were going to do
before!)</p>

<p>Now, one common pitfall here with conditionals is that you end up
confusing the assignment operator (<operator>=</operator>) with the
comparison operator (<operator>==</operator>).  Note that the results of
both operators is an expression, so both are valid to put inside the
<statement>if</statement> statement.  Except one assigns and the other
compares!  You most likely want to compare.  If weird stuff is
happening, make sure you have the two equal signs in your comparison
operator.</p>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="whilestat">
<title>The <statement>while</statement> statement</title>

<p>
Let's have another statement.  Let's say you want to repeatly perform a
task until a condition is true.  This sounds like a job for the
<statement>while</statement> loop.  This works just like the
<statement>if</statement> statement, except that it will repeately
execute the following block of code until the statement is false, much
like an insane android bent on killing its innocent masters.</p>

<p>Or something.</p>

<p>Here's an example of a while loop that should clarify this up a bit
and help cleanse your mind of the killing android image:</p>

<code>// print the following output:
//
//   i is now 0!
//   i is now 1!
//   [ more of the same between 2 and 7 ]
//   i is now 8!
//   i is now 9!

i = 0;

while (i &lt; 10) {
	printf("i is now %d!\n", i);
	i++;
}

printf("All done!\n");</code>

<p>The easiest way to see what happens here is to mentally step through
the code a line at a time.</p>

<numlist>
<li>First, <var>i</var> is set to zero.  It's good to have these things
initialized.</li>

<li>Secondly, we hit the <statement>while</statement> statement.  It
checks to see if the <emp>continuation condition</emp> is true, and
continues to run the following block if it is.  (Remember, true is
<tt>1</tt>, and so when <var>i</var> is zero, the expression <tt>i &lt;
10</tt> is <const>1</const> (true).</li>

<li>Since the continuation condition was true, we get into the block of
code.  The <func>printf()</func> function executes and outputs "<tt>i is
now 0!</tt>".</li>

<li>Next, we get that post-increment operator!  Remember what it does?
It adds one to <var>i</var> in this case.  (I'm going to tell you a
little secret about post-increment: the increment happens <emp>AFTER all
of the rest of the expression has been evaluated</emp>.  That's why it's
called "post", of course!  In this case, the entire expression consists
of simply <var>i</var>, so the result here is to simply increment
<var>i</var>.</li>

<li>Ok, now we're at the end of the basic block.  Since it started with a
<statement>while</statement> statement, we're going to loop back up to
the while and then:</li>

<li>We have arrived back at the start of the <statement>while</statement>
statement.  It seems like such a long time ago we were once here,
doesn't it?  Only this time things seem slightly different...what could
it be?  A new haircut, perhaps?  No!  The variable <var>i</var> is equal
to <tt>1</tt> this time instead of <tt>0</tt>!  So we have to check the
continuation condition again.  Sure enough, <tt>1 &lt; 10</tt> last time I
checked, so we enter the block of code again.</li>

<li>We <func>printf()</func> "<tt>i is now 1!</tt>".</li>

<li>We increment <var>i</var> and it goes to <tt>2</tt>.</li>

<li>We loop back up to the <statement>while</statement> statement and
check to see if the continuation condition is true.</li>

<li>Yadda, yadda, yadda.  I think you can see where this is going.
Let's skip ahead to the <emp>incredible future</emp> where people
commute to work on their AI-controlled rocket scooters, eat anti-gravity
beets, and little spherical robot helicopters freely roam the skies
making <emp>beep-beep-beep-beep</emp> noises.  And where the variable
<var>i</var> has finally been incremented so it's value is <tt>10</tt>.
Meanwhile, while we've slept in cryogenic hybernation, our program has
been dutifully fulfilling its thousand-year mission to print things like
"i is now 4!", "i is now 5!", and finally, "i is now 9!"</li>

<li>So <var>i</var> has finally been incremented to <tt>10</tt>, and we
check the continuation condition.  It <tt>10 &lt; 10</tt>?  Nope, that'll
be false and zero, so the <statement>while</statement> statement is
finally completed and we continue to the next line.</li>

<li>And lastly <func>printf</func> is called, and we get our parting
message: "<tt>All done!</tt>".</li>

</numlist>

<p>That was a lot of tracing, there, wasn't it?  This kind of mentally
running through a program is commonly called <emp>desk-checking</emp>
your code, because historically you do it sitting at your desk.  It's a
powerful debugging technique you have at your disposal, as well.</p>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="dowhilestat">
<title>The <statement>do-while</statement> statement</title>

<p>So now that we've gotten the <statement>while</statement> statement
under control, let's take a look at its closely related cousin,
<statement>do-while</statement>.</p>

<p>They are basically the same, except if the continuation condition is
false on the first pass, <statement>do-while</statement> will execute
once, but <statement>while</statement> won't execute at all.  Let's see
by example:</p>

<code>/* using a while statement: */

i = 10;

// this is not executed because i is not less than 10:
while(i &lt; 10) {
	printf("while: i is %d\n", i);
	i++;
}

/* using a do-while statement: */

i = 10;

// this is executed once, because the continuation condition is
// not checked until after the body of the loop runs:
do {
	printf("do-while: i is %d\n", i);
	i++;
} while (i &lt; 10);

printf("All done!\n");</code>

<p>Notice that in both cases, the continuation condition is false right
away.  So in the <statement>while</statement>, the condition fails, and
the following block of code is never executed.  With the
<statement>do-while</statement>, however, the condition is checked
<emp>after</emp> the block of code executes, so it always executes at
least once.  In this case, it prints the message, increments
<var>i</var>, then fails the condition, and continues to the "All done!"
output.</p>

<p>The moral of the story is this: if you want the loop to execute at
least once, no matter what the continuation condition, use
<statement>do-while</statement>.</p>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="forstat">
<title>The <statement>for</statement> statement</title>

<p>Now you're starting to feel more comfortable with these looping
statements, huh!  Well, listen up!  It's time for something a little
more complicated: the <statement>for</statement> statement.  This is
another looping construct that gives you a cleaner syntax than
<statement>while</statement> in many cases, but does basically the same
thing.  Here are two pieces of equivalent code:</p>

<code>// using a while statement:

// print numbers between 0 and 9, inclusive:
i = 0;
while (i &lt; 10) {
	printf("i is %d\n", i);
	i++;
}

// do the same thing with a for-loop:
for (i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
	printf("i is %d\n", i);
}</code>

<p>That's right, kids&emdash;they do exactly the same thing.  But you
can see how the <statement>for</statement> statement is a little more
compact and easy on the eyes.</p>

<p>It's split into three parts, separated by semicolons.  The first is
the initialization, the second is the continuation condition, and the
third is what should happen at the end of the block if the contination
condition is true.  All three of these parts are optional.  And empty
<statement>for</statement> will run forever:</p>

<code>for(;;) {
	printf("I will print this again and again and again\n" );
	printf("for all eternity until the cold-death of the universe.\n");

}</code>

</sect3>

</sect2> <!-- sect2 id="statements" -->

</sect1> <!-- sect1 id="sve" -->

<sect1 id="bbrevisited">
<title>Building Blocks Revisited</title>

<quote><p><emp>"Is everything all right, sir?"</emp><br/>
<emp>"No.  No, it's not.  Some smegger's filled out this 'Have You Got a
Good Memory' quiz."</emp><br/>
<emp>"Why, that was you, sir.  Don't you remember?"</emp><br/>
--Kryten and Dave Lister, Red Dwarf</p></quote>

<p>Before we start with functions in the next section, we're going to
quickly tie this in with that very important thing to remember back at
the beginning of the guide.  Now what was it...oh, well, I guess I gave
it away with this section title, but let's keep talking as if that
didn't happen.</p>

<p>Yes, it was basic building blocks, and how you take a specification
and turn it into little bite-sized pieces that you can easily translate
into blocks of code.  I told you to take it on faith that I'd tell you
some of the basic pieces, and I'm just reminding you here, in case you
didn't notice, that all those statements back there are little basic
building blocks that you can use in your programs.</p>

<p>Such as, if the specification reads:</p>

<offsettext><p><b>Assignment:</b> Write a program that repeatedly
accepts user input and then prints the numbers between 0 and the entered
number.  If the user enters a number less than or equal to zero, the
program will exit.</p></offsettext>

<p>You now have enough information to figure out all the basic building
blocks to make this program happen.  You'll have to steal
<func>scanf()</func> and <func>printf()</func> usage from previous
examples, but the rest of the parts correspond to various statements
you've seen in the previous section.</p>

<p>Note that off the top of my head, I can think of many many ways to
implement this assignment.  If you come up with one that works, good for
you!  Sure, it might not be the best, but what is "best", anyway?
(Well, it turns out best is defined as what your professor or boss
thinks is best, but let's be happily theoretical for the moment.
Ahhh.)</p>

<p>So!  Do some breakdown of the above assignment, and come up with the
basic structure you'd use.  In fact, go ahead and code it up, and try it
out!</p>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="functions">
<title>Functions</title>

<p>With the previous section on building blocks fresh in your head,
let's imagine a freaky world where a program is so complicated, so
insidiously large, that once you shove it all into your
<func>main()</func>, it becomes rather unwieldy.</p>

<p>What do I mean by that?  The best analogy I can think of is that
programs are best read, modified, and understood by humans when they are
split into convenient pieces, like a book is most conveniently read when
it is split into paragraphs.</p>

<p>Ever try to read a book with no paragraph breaks?  It's tough, man,
believe me.  I once read through <emp>Captain Singleton</emp> by Daniel
Defoe since I was a fan of his, but Lord help me, the man didn't put a
single paragraph break in there.  It was a brutal novel.</p>

<p>But I digress.  What we're going to do to help us along is to put
some of those building blocks in their own functions when they become
too large, or when they do a different thing than the rest of the code.
For instance, the assignment might call for a number to be read, then
the sum of all number between 1 and it calculated and printed.  It would
make sense to put the code for calculating the sum into a separate
function so that the main code a) looks cleaner, and b) the function can
be <emp>reused</emp> elsewhere.</p>

<p>Reuse is one of the main reasons for having a function.  Take the
<func>printf()</func> for instance.  It's pretty complicated down there,
parsing the format string and knowing how to actually output characters
to a device and all that.  Imagine if you have to rewrite all that code
every single time you wanted to output a measly string to the console?
No, no&emdash;far better to put the whole thing in a function and let
you just call it repeatedly, see?</p>

<p>You've already seen a few functions called, and you've even seen one
<emp>defined</emp>, namely the almighty <func>main()</func> (the
definition is where you actually put the code that does the work of the
function.)  But the <func>main()</func> is a little bit incomplete
in terms of how it is defined, and this is allowed for purely historical
reasons.  More on that later.  Here we'll define and call a normal
function called <func>plus_one()</func> that take an integer parameter
and returns the value plus one:</p>

<code>int plus_one(int n) /* THE DEFINITION */
{
	return n + 1;
}

int main(void)
{
	int i = 10, j;
	
	j = plus_one(i); /* THE CALL */

	printf("i + 1 is %d\n", j);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>(Before I forget, notice that I defined the function before I used it.
If hadn't done that, the compiler wouldn't know about it yet when it
compiles <func>main()</func> and it would have given an unknown function
call error.  There is a more proper way to do the above code with
function prototypes, but we'll talk about that later.)</p>

<p>So here we have a function definition for <func>plus_one()</func>.
The first word, <type>int</type>, is the return type of the function.
That is, when we come back to use it in <func>main()</func>, the value
of the expression (in the case of the call, the expression is merely the
call itself) will be of this type.  By wonderful coincidence, you'll
notice that the type of <var>j</var>, the variable that is to hold the
return value of the function, is of the same type, <type>int</type>.
This is completely on purpose.</p>

<p>Then we have the function name, followed by a <emp>parameter
list</emp> in parenthesis.  These correspond to the values in
parenthesis in the call to the function...but <emp>they don't have to
have the same names</emp>.  Notice we call it with <var>i</var>, but the
variable in the function definition is named <var>n</var>.  This is ok,
since the compiler will keep track of it for you.</p>

<p>Inside the <func>plus_one()</func> itself, we're doing a couple
things on one line here.  We have an expression <tt>n + 1</tt> that is
evaluated before the <statement>return</statement> statement.  So if we
pass the value 10 into the function, it will evaluate <tt>10 + 1</tt>,
which, in this universe, comes to 11, and it will return that.</p>

<p>Once returned to the call back in <func>main()</func>, we do the
assignment into <var>j</var>, and it takes on the return value, which
was 11.  Hey look!  <var>j</var> is now <var>i</var> plus one!  Just
like the function was supposed to do!  This calls for a celebration!</p>

<p>[<emp>GENERIC PARTY SOUNDS.</emp>]</p>

<p>Ok, that's enough of that.  Now, a couple paragraphs back, I
mentioned that the names in the parameter list of the function
definition correspond to the <emp>values</emp> passed into the function.
In the case of <func>plus_one()</func>, you can call it any way you
like, as long as you call it with an <type>int</type>-type parameter.
For example, all these calls are valid:</p>

<code>int a = 5, b = 10;

plus_one(a);	 /* the type of a is int */
plus_one(10);	/* the type of 10 is int */
plus_one(1+10);  /* the type of the whole expression is still int */
plus_one(a+10);  /* the type of the whole expression is still int */
plus_one(a+b);   /* the type of the whole expression is still int */
plus_one(plus_one(a));  /* oooo! return value is int, so it's ok!  */</code>
	
<p>If you're having trouble wrapping your head around that last line
there, just take it one expression at a time, starting at the innermost
parentheses (because the innermost parentheses are evaluated first,
rememeber?)  So you start at <var>a</var> and think, that's a valid
<type>int</type> to call the function <func>plus_one()</func> with, so
we call it, and that returns an <type>int</type>, and that's a valid
type to call the next outer <func>plus_one()</func> with, so we're
golden.</p>

<p>Hey!  What about the return value from all of these?  We're not
assigning it into anything!  Where is it going?  Well, on the last line,
the innermost call to <func>plus_one()</func> is being used to call
<func>plus_one()</func> again, but aside from that, you're
right&emdash;they are being discarded completely.  This is legal, but
rather pointless unless you're just writing sample code for
demonstration purposes.</p>

<p>It's like we wrote "5" down on a slip of paper and passed it to the
<func>plus_one()</func> function, and it went through the trouble of
adding one, and writing "6" on a slip of paper and passing it back to
us, and then we merely just throw it in the trash without looking at it.
We're such bastards.</p>

<p>I have said the word "value" a number of times, and there's a good
reason for that.  When we pass parameters to functions, we're doing
something commonly referred to as <emp>passing by value</emp>.  This
warrants its own subsection.</p>

<sect2 id="passvalue">
<title>Passing by Value</title>

<p>When you pass a value to a function, <emp>a copy of that value</emp>
gets made in this magical mystery world known as <emp>the stack</emp>.
(The stack is just a hunk of memory somewhere that the program allocates
memory on.  Some of the stack is used to hold the copies of values that
are passed to functions.)</p>

<p>(Here is where the Pedant Police come and get me and say that the C
specification doesn't say anything about a stack.  It's true.  Your
system might not use a stack deep-down for function calls.  But it's
going to look like it does, and every single C programmer on the planet
will know what you're talking about when you talk about "the stack".  It
would be just mean for me to keep you in the dark.  Plus, the stack
analogy is excellent for describing how recursion works.)</p>

<p>For now, the important part is that <emp>a copy</emp> of the variable
or value is being passed to the function.  The practical upshot of
this is that since the function is operating on a copy of the value, you
can't affect the value back in the calling function directly.  Like if
you wanted to increment a value by one, this would NOT work:</p>

<code>void increment(int a)
{
	a++;
}

int main(void)
{
	int i = 10;

	increment(i);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Wait a minute, wait a minute&emdash;hold it, hold it!  What's this
<type>void</type> return type on this function?  Am I trying to pull a
fast one on you?  Not at all.  This just means that the function doesn't
return any value.  Relax!</p>

<p>So anyway, if I might be allowed to get on with it, you might think
that the value of <var>i</var> after the call would be 11, since that's
what the <operator>++</operator> does, right?  This would be incorrect.
What is really happening here?</p>

<p>Well, when you pass <var>i</var> to the <func>increment()</func>
function, a copy gets made on the stack, right?  It's the copy that
<func>increment()</func> works on, not the original; the original
<var>i</var> is unaffected.  We even gave the copy a name: <var>a</var>,
right?  It's right there in the parameter list of the function
definition.  So we increment <var>a</var>, sure enough, but what
good does that do us?  None!  Ha!</p>

<p>That's why in the previous example with the <func>plus_one()</func>
function, we <statement>return</statement>ed the locally modified value
so that we could see it again in <func>main()</func>.</p>

<p>Seems a little bit restrictive, huh?  Like you can only get one piece
of data back from a function, is what you're thinking.  There is,
however, another way to get data back; people call it <emp>passing by
reference</emp>.  But no fancy-schmancy name will distract you from the
fact that <emp>EVERYTHING</emp> you pass to a function <emp>WITHOUT
EXCEPTION</emp> is copied onto the stack and the function operates on
that local copy, <emp>NO MATTER WHAT</emp>.  Remember that, even when
we're talking about this so-called passing by reference.</p>

<p>But that's a story for another time.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="prototypes">
<title>Function Prototypes</title>

<p>So if you recall back in the ice age a few sections ago, I mentioned
that you had to define the function before you used it, otherwise the
compiler wouldn't know about it ahead of time, and would bomb out with
an error.</p>

<p>This isn't quite strictly true.  You can notify the compiler in
advance that you'll be using a function of a certain type that has a
certain parameter list and that way the function can be defined
anywhere at all, as long as the <emp>function prototype</emp> has been
declared first.</p>

<p>Fortunately, the function prototype is really quite easy.  It's
merely a copy of the first line of the function definition with a
semicolon tacked on the end for good measure.  For example, this code
calls a function that is defined later, because a prototype has been
declared first:</p>

<code>int foo(void); /* this is the prototype! */

int main(void)
{
	int i;
	
	i = foo();

	return 0;
}

int foo(void) /* this is the definition, just like the prototype! */
{
	return 3490;
}</code>

<p>You might notice something about the sample code we've been
using...that is, we've been using the good old <func>printf()</func>
function without defining it or declaring a prototype!  How do we get
away with this lawlessness?  We don't, actually.  There is a prototype;
it's in that header file <file>stdio.h</file> that we included with
<tt>#include</tt>, remember?  So we're still legit, officer!</p>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="vars2">
<title>Variables, The Sequel</title>

<p>Just when you thought it was safe to know everything there was to
know about variables, this section of the guide lunges at you from the
darkness!  What?!  There's more?</p>

<p>Yes, I'm sorry, but I'm afraid there is.  We're going to talk about a
couple things in this section that increase the power you have over
variables <emp>TO THE EXTREME</emp>.  Yes, by now you realize that
melodrama is a well-respected part of this guide, so you probably
weren't even taken off-guard by that one, ironically.</p>

<p>Where was I?  Oh, yes; let's talk about variable <emp>scope</emp> and
<emp>storage classes</emp>.</p>

<sect2 id="varscope">
<title>"Up Scope"</title>

<p>You recall how in some of those functions that we previously defined
there were variables that were visible from some parts of the program
but not from others?  Well, if you can use a variable from a certain
part of a program, it's said to be <emp>in scope</emp> (as opposed to
<emp>out of scope</emp>.)  A variable will be in scope if it is declared
inside the block (that is, enclosed by squirrley braces) that is
currently executing.</p>

<p>Take a look at this example:</p>

<code>int frotz(int a)
{
	int b;

	b = 10; /* in scope (from the local definition) */
	a = 20; /* in scope (from the parameter list) */
	c = 30; /* ERROR, out of scope (declared in another block, in main()) */
}

int main(void)
{
	int c;

	c = 20; /* in scope */
	b = 30; /* ERROR, out of scope (declared above in frotz()) */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>So you can see that you have to have variables declared locally for
them to be in scope.  Also note that the parameter <var>a</var> is also
in scope for the function <func>frotz()</func></p>

<p>What do I mean by <emp>local variables</emp>, anyway?  These are
variable that exist and are visible only in a single basic block of code
(that is, code that is surrounded by squirrley braces) and, basic blocks
of code within them.  For instance:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{  /* start of basic block */
	int a = 5; /* local to main() */

	if (a != 0) {
		int b = 10; /* local to if basic block */
		
		a = b; /* perfectly legal--both a and b are visible here */
	}

	b = 12; /* ERROR -- b is not visible out here--only in the if */

	{ /* notice I started a basic block with no statement--this is legal */
		int c = 12;
		int a; /* Hey!  Wait!  There was already an "a" out in main! */

		/* the a that is local to this block hides the a from main */
		a = c; /* this modified the a local to this block to be 12 */
	}

	/* but this a back in main is still 10 (since we set it in the if): */
	printf("%d\n", a);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>There's a lot of stuff in that example, but all of it is basically a
presentation of a simple rule: when it comes to local variables, you can
only use them in the basic block in which they are declared, or in basic
blocks within that.  Look at the "ERROR" line in the example to see
exactly what <emp>won't</emp> work.</p>

<p>Let's digress for a second and take into account the special case of
parameters passed to functions.  These are in scope for the entire
function and you are free to modify them to your heart's content.  They
are just like local variables to the function, except that they have
copies of the data you passed in, obviously.</p>

<code>void foo(int a)
{
	int b;

	a = b; /* totally legal */
}</code>

<sect3 id="globals">
<title>Global variables</title>

<p>There are other types of variables besides locals.  There are
<emp>global variables</emp>, for instance.  Sounds grand, huh.  Though
they're aren't exactly the chicken's pajamas for a number of reasons,
they're still a powerful piece of the language.  Wield this power with
care, since you can make code that's very hard to maintain if you abuse
it.</p>

<p>A global variable is visible thoughout the entire file that it is
defined in (or declared in&emdash;more on that later).  So it's just
like a local, except you can use it from anyplace.  I guess, then, it's
rather not like a local at all.  But here's an example:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

/* this is a global variable.  We know it's global, because it's */
/* been declared in "global scope", and not in a basic block somewhere */
int g = 10;

void afunc(int x)
{
	g = x; /* this sets the global to whatever x is */
}

int main(void)
{
	g = 10;	/* global g is now 10 */
	afunc(20); /* but this function will set it to 20 */
	printf("%d\n", g); /* so this will print "20" */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Remember how local variables go on the stack?  Well, globals go on
<emp>the heap</emp>, another chunk of memory. And never the twain shall
meet.  You can think of the heap as being more "permanent" than the
stack, in many ways.</p>

<p>(Dang it&emdash;the C Standard doesn't say anything about the heap,
either.  But, like the stack, all C programmers use the terminology
and will know what you're talking about.)</p>

<p>Now, I mentioned that globals can be dangerous. How is that?  Well,
one thing you could imagine is a large-scale project in which there were
a bazillion globals declared by a bazillion different programmers.  What
if they named them the same thing?  What if you thought you were using a
local, but you had forgotten to declare it, so you were using the
global instead?</p>

<p>(Ooo.  That's a good side note: if you declare a local with the same
name as a global, it hides the global and all operations in the scope
will take place on the local variable.)</p>

<p>What else can go wrong?  Sometimes using global variables encourages
people to not structure their code as well as they might have otherwise.
It's a good idea to not use them until there simply is no other
reasonable way to move data around.</p>

<p>Another thing to consider is this: does it actually make sense to
have this data stored globally for all to see?  For example, if you have
a game where you use "the temperature of the world" in a lot of
different places, that might be a good candidate for a global varible.
Why?  Because it's a pain to pass it around, and everyone has the same
need for it.</p>

<p>On the other hand, "the temperature of this guy's little finger"
might not be of so much interest to the rest of the universe.  It'd be
better to store that data in a way that's more associated with the guy
than globally.  We'll talk more later about associating data with things
(nice and vague, huh?) later.</p>


</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="stclasses">
<title>Storage Classes</title>

<p>What is a storage class?  It's a class for storing variables.</p>

<p>You're welcome.</p>

<p>Don't get this confused with any C++ class, either, since it's not at
all the same thing.</p>

<p>So what does a storage class declaration do?  It tells the compiler
where to store the data, such as on the stack or on the heap, or if
variable data storage is already declared elsewhere.</p>

<p>"What?"</p>

<p>Let's just get some examples in there and it'll make more sense.</p>

<sect3 id="static">
<title>Gimme some static!</title>

<p>Ready?  Here's an example: I'm sitting on BART (the Bay Area Rapid
Transit subway) as I type this on my way home from work.  There is a
young couple happily canoodling each other in the seat in front of me,
and it's completely distracting.</p>

<p>...Er, what.  No, an example!  Yes!  Ok, here it is:</p>

<code>void print_plus_one(void)
{
	static int a=0; /* static storage class! */

	printf("%d\n", a);

	a++;  /* increment the static value */
}

int main(void)
{
	print_plus_one(); /* prints "0" */
	print_plus_one(); /* prints "1" */
	print_plus_one(); /* prints "2" */
	print_plus_one(); /* prints "3" */
	print_plus_one(); /* prints "4" */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>What have we here?  How can this magic be?  Isn't that a local
variable in <func>print_plus_one()</func> and doesn't it get allocated
on the stack and doesn't it go away after the function returns?  How can
it possibly remember the value from the last call?</p>

<p>The answer: it uses the modern day magic that is the
<type>static</type> keyword.  This directive (given before the type)
tells the compiler to actually store this data someplace permanent
instead of the stack!  Ooooo!  Well, the value gets initialized once (in
the definition), and it never gets initialized again, so all operations
on it are cumulative.</p>

<p>Also, if you simply define a local variable as static, it'll be
initialized automatically to zero unless you specify otherwise.</p>

<p>You'll probably see more use for this later, but it's common enough
that you should know about it.</p>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="otherstor">
<title>Other Storage Classes</title>

<p>There are other storage classes, yes.  The default is
<type>auto</type>, which you never see in the wild since it's
default.</p>

<p>Another is <type>extern</type> which tells the compiler that the
definition of the variable is in a different file.  This allows you to
reference a global variable from a file, even if its definition is
somewhere else.  It would be illegal to define it twice, and since it's
global it'd be nice to have it available across different source
files.</p>

<p>I know, I know.  It's hard to imagine now, but programs do get big
enough to span multiple files eventually. <smiley/></p>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- Variables, The Sequel -->

<sect1 id="pointers">
<title>Pointers&emdash;Cower In Fear!</title>

<p>Pointers are one of the most feared things in the C language.  In
fact, they are the one thing that makes this language challenging at
all.  But why?</p>

<p>Because they, quite honestly, can cause electric shocks to come up
through the keyboard and physically <emp>weld</emp> your arms permantly
in place, cursing you to a life at the keyboard.</p>

<p>Well, not really.  But they can cause huge headaches if you don't
know what you're doing when you try to mess with them.</p>

<sect2 id="ptmem">
<title>Memory and Variables</title>

<p>Computer memory holds data of all kinds, right?  It'll hold
<type>float</type>s, <type>int</type>s, or whatever you have.  To make
memory easy to cope with, each byte of memory is identified by an
integer.  These integers increase sequentially as you move up through
memory.  You can think of it as a bunch of numbered boxes, where each
box holds a byte of data.  The number that represents each box is called
its <emp>address</emp>.</p>

<p>Now, not all data types use just a byte.  For instance, a
<type>long</type> is often four bytes, but it really depends on the
system.  You can use the <operator>sizeof()</operator> operator to
determine how many bytes of memory a certain type uses.  (I know,
<operator>sizeof()</operator> looks more like a function than an
operator, but there we are.)</p>

<code>printf("a long uses %d bytes of memory\n", sizeof(long));</code>

<p>When you have a data type that uses more than a byte of memory, the
bytes that make up the data are always adjacent to one another in
memory.  Sometimes they're in order, and sometimes they're not, but
that's platform-dependent, and often taken care of for you without you
needing to worry about pesky byte orderings.</p>

<p>So <emp>anyway</emp>, if we can get on with it and get a drum roll
and some forboding music playing for the definition of a pointer, <emp>a
pointer is the address of some data in memory</emp>.  Imagine the
classical score from 2001: A Space Odessey at this point.  Ba bum ba
bum ba bum BAAAAH!</p>

<p>Ok, so maybe a bit overwrought here, yes?  There's not a lot of
mystery about pointers.  They are the address of data.  Just like an
<type>int</type> can be <tt>12</tt>, a pointer can be the address of
data.</p>

<p>Often, we like to make a pointer to some data that we have stored in
a variable, as opposed to any old random data out in memory whereever.
Having a pointer to a variable is often more useful.</p>

<p>So if we have an <type>int</type>, say, and we want a
pointer to it, what we want is some way to get the address of that
<type>int</type>, right?  After all, the pointer is just the
<emp>address of</emp> the data.  What operator do you suppose we'd use
to find the <emp>address of</emp> the <type>int</type>?</p>

<p>Well, by a shocking suprise that must come as something of a shock to
you, gentle reader, we use the <operator>address-of</operator> operator (which
happens to be an ampersand: "<operator>&amp;</operator>") to find the
address of the data.  Ampersand.</p>

<p>So for a quick example, we'll introduce a new <emp>format
specifier</emp> for <func>printf()</func> so you can print a pointer.
You know already how <tt>%d</tt> prints a decimal integer, yes?  Well,
<tt>%p</tt> prints a pointer.  Now, this pointer is going to look like
a garbage number (and it might be printed in hexidecimal instead of
decimal), but it is merely the number of the box the data is stored in.
(Or the number of the box that the first byte of data is stored in, if
the data is multi-byte.)  In virtually all circumstances, including this
one, the actual value of the number printed is unimportant to you, and I
show it here only for demonstration of the <operator>address-of</operator>
operator.</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	int i = 10;

	printf("The value of i is %d, and its address is %p\n", i, &amp;i);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>On my laptop, this prints:</p>

<screen>The value of i is 10, and its address is 0xbffff964</screen>

<p>(I can show off a bit here, and say that from experience the address
to me looks like its on the stack...and it is, since it's a local
variable, and all locals go on the stack.  Am I cool or what.
Don't answer that.)</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="pttypes">
<title>Pointer Types</title>

<p>Well, this is all well and good.  You can now successfully take the
address of a variable and print it on the screen.  There's a little
something for the ol' resume, right?  Here's where you grab me by the
scruff of the neck and ask politely what the frick pointers are good
for.</p>

<p>Excellent question, and we'll get to that right after these messages
from our sponsor.</p>

<offsettext><p><tt>ACME ROBOTIC HOUSING UNIT CLEANING SERVICES.  YOUR
HOMESTEAD WILL BE DRAMATICALLY IMPROVED OR YOU WILL BE TERMINATED.
MESSAGE ENDS.</tt></p></offsettext>

<p>Welcome back to another installment of Beej's Guide to Whatever.
When we met last we were talking about how to make use of pointers.
Well, what we're going to do is store a pointer off in a variable so
that we can use it later.  You can identify the <emp>pointer type</emp>
because there's an asterisk (<type>*</type>) before the variable name
and after its type:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int i;  /* i's type is "int" */
	int *p; /* p's type is "pointer to an int", or "int-pointer" */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Hey, so we have here a variable that is a pointer itself, and it can
point to other <type>int</type>s.  We know it points to
<type>int</type>s, since it's of type <type>int*</type> (read
"int-pointer").</p>

<p>When you do an assignment into a pointer variable, the type of the
right hand side of the assignment has to be the same type as the
pointer variable.  Fortunately for us, when you take the
<operator>address-of</operator> a variable, the resultant type is a
pointer to that variable type, so assignments like the following are
perfect:</p>

<code>int i;
int *p; /* p is a pointer, but is uninitialized and points to garbage */

p = &amp;i; /* p now "points to" i */</code>

<p>Get it?  I know is still doesn't quite make much sense since you
haven't seen an actual use for the pointer variable, but we're taking
small steps here so that no one gets lost.  So now, let's introduce you
to the anti-address-of, operator.  It's kind of like what
<operator>address-of</operator> would be like in Bizarro World.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="defer">
<title>Dereferencing</title>

<p>A pointer, also known as an address, is sometimes also called a
<emp>reference</emp>.  How in the name of all that is holy can there be
so many terms for exactly the same thing?  I don't know the answer to
that one, but these things are all equivalent, and can be used
interchangably.</p>

<p>The only reason I'm telling you this is so that the name of this
operator will make any sense to you whatsoever.  When you have a pointer
to a variable (AKA "a reference to a variable"), you can use the
original variable through the pointer by <emp>dereferencing</emp> the
pointer.  (You can think of this as "de-pointering" the pointer, but no
one ever says "de-pointering".)</p>

<p>What do I mean by "get access to the original variable"?  Well, if you
have a variable called <var>i</var>, and you have a pointer to
<var>i</var> called <var>p</var>, you can use the dereferenced pointer
<var>p</var> <emp>exactly as if it were the original variable
<var>i</var></emp>!</p>

<p>You almost have enough knowledge to handle an example.  The last
tidbit you need to know is actually this: what is the dereference
operator?  It is the asterisk, again: <operator>*</operator>.  Now,
don't get this confused with the asterisk you used in the pointer
declaration, earlier.  They are the same character, but they have
different meanings in different contexts.</p>

<p>Here's a full-blown example:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	int i;
	int *p;  // this is NOT a dereference--this is a type "int*"

	p = &amp;i; // p now points to i

	i = 10;  // i is now 10
	*p = 20; // i (yes i!) is now 20!!

	printf("i is %d\n", i);   // prints "20"
	printf("i is %d\n", *p);  // "20"!  dereference-p is the same as i!

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Remember that <var>p</var> holds the address of <var>i</var>, as you
can see where we did the assignment to <var>p</var>.  What the
dereference operator does is tells the computer to <emp>use the variable
the pointer points to</emp> instead of using the pointer itself.  In
this way, we have turned <var>*p</var> into an alias of sorts for
<var>i</var>.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="ptpass">
<title>Passing Pointers as Parameters</title>

<p>Right about now, you're thinking that you have an awful lot of
knowledge about pointers, but absolutely zero application, right?  I
mean, what use is <var>*p</var> if you could just simply say
<var>i</var> instead?</p>

<p>Well, my feathered friend, the real power of pointers comes into play
when you start passing them to functions.  Why is this a big deal?  You
might recall from before that you could pass all kinds of parameters to
functions and they'd be dutifully copied onto the stack, and then you
could manipulate local copies of those variables from within the
function, and then you could return a single value.</p>

<p>What if you wanted to bring back more than one single piece of data
from the function?  What if I answered that question with another
question, like this:</p>

<p>What happens when you pass a pointer as a parameter to a function?
Does a copy of the pointer get put on the stack?  <emp>You bet your
sweet peas it does.</emp>  Remember how earlier I rambled on and on about
how <emp>EVERY SINGLE PARAMETER</emp> gets copied onto the stack and the
function uses a copy of the parameter?  Well, the same is true here.
The function will get a copy of the pointer.</p>

<p>But, and this is the clever part: we will have set up the pointer in
advance to point at a variable...and then the function can
dereference its copy of the pointer to get back to the original
variable!  The function can't see the variable itself, but it can
certainly dereference a pointer to that variable!  Example!</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

void increment(int *p) /* note that it accepts a pointer to an int */
{
	*p = *p + 1; /* add one to p */
}

int main(void)
{
	int i = 10;

	printf("i is %d\n", i); /* prints "10" */

	increment(&amp;i); /* note the address-of; turns it into a pointer */

	printf("i is %d\n", i); /* prints "11"! */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Ok!  There are a couple things to see here...not the least of which
is that the <func>increment()</func> function takes an <type>int*</type>
as a parameter.  We pass it an <type>int*</type> in the call by changing
the <type>int</type> variable <var>i</var> to an <type>int*</type> using
the <operator>address-of</operator> operator.  (Remember, a pointer is
an address, so we make pointers out of variables by running them through
the <operator>address-of</operator> operator.)</p>

<p>The <func>increment()</func> function gets a copy of the pointer on
the stack.  Both the original pointer <var>&amp;i</var> (in
<func>main()</func>) and the copy of the pointer <var>p</var> (in
<func>increment()</func>) point to the same address.  So dereferencing
either will allow you to modify the original variable <var>i</var>!
The function can modify a variable in another scope!  Rock on!</p>

<p>Pointer enthusiasts will recall from early on in the guide, we used a
function to read from the keyboard, <func>scanf()</func>...and, although
you might not have recognized it at the time, we used the
<operator>address-of</operator> to pass a pointer to a value to
<func>scanf()</func>.  We had to pass a pointer, see, because
<func>scanf()</func> reads from the keyboard and stores the result in a
variable.  The only way it can see that variable that is local to that
calling function is if we pass a pointer to that variable:</p>

<code>int i = 0;

scanf("%d", &amp;i);        /* pretend you typed "12" */
printf("i is %d\n", i); /* prints "i is 12" */</code>

<p>See, <func>scanf()</func> dereferences the pointer we pass it in
order to modify the variable it points to.  And now you know why you
have to put that pesky ampersand in there!</p>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="structs">
<title>Structures and Unions</title>

<p>You've been messing with variables for quite some time now, and
you've made a bunch of them here and there to do stuff, yes?  Usually
you bundle them into the same basic block and let it go at that.</p>

<p>Sometimes, though, it makes more sense to put them together into a
<emp>structure</emp>.  This is a construct that allows you to logically
(or even illogically, if the fancy takes you) group variables into, uh,
groups.  You can then reference the group as a whole.  One place this
comes in really handily is if you want to pass 13 bazillion parameters
to a function, but don't want the function declaration to be that long.
You just put all the variables into a structure (or <type>struct</type>,
as it is normally called), and then pass that structure to the function.
(Actually, people usually pass a pointer to the structure, but we'll get
to that later.)</p>

<p>So how do you use one of these things?  First off, the
<type>struct</type> itself is a new type.  If you make a variable that
is a <type>struct foo</type>, it's type is "<type>struct foo</type>",
just as the number 12 is of type "<type>int</type>".  This is a little
bit spooky because this could be the first time you've created a new
type, and it might be unclear how that works.</p>

<p>Adding to the confusion, it turns out there are multiple ways to
create and use a new <type>struct</type> type, and barely any of them
are particularly intuitive.  We'll have an example of one way to declare
a new <type>struct</type> here:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

/* Here we declare the type so we can use it later: */
struct stuff {
	int val;
	float b;
};

/* Note that we don't actually have any variables of that type, yet. */

int main(void)
{
	/* ok, now let's declare a variable "s" of type "struct stuff" */
	struct stuff s;


	s.val = 3490;  /* assignment into a struct! */
	s.b = 3.14159;

	printf("The val field in s is: %d\n", s.val);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>The compiler allows us to predeclare a <type>struct</type> like in
the example.  We can then use it later, like we do in
<func>main()</func> to assign values into it.  When we say things like
<tt>s.val = 3490</tt>, we are using a special operator to access the
<type>val</type> field, known as the <emp>dot operator</emp>
(<operator>.</operator>).</p>

<sect2 id="structpt">
<title>Pointers to <type>struct</type>s</title>

<p>Now let's talk a bit about how to pass these <type>struct</type>s
around to other functions and stuff.  I mentioned before that you
probably want to pass a pointer to the <type>struct</type> instead of
the <type>struct</type> itself.  Why?</p>

<p>Don't you hate it when the professor asks you a question like that,
but you're too tired in lecture to care to begin to think about it?
"Just tell me and we'll get on with it," is what you're thinking, isn't
it.</p>

<p>Fine!  Be that way!  Well, remember that when you pass parameters to
functions, and I'll clear my throat here in preparation to say again,
<emp>EVERY PARAMETER WITHOUT FAIL GETS COPIED ONTO THE STACK when you
call a function!</emp>  So if you have a huge <type>struct</type> that's
like 80,000 bytes in size, it's going to copy that onto the stack when
you pass it.  That takes time.</p>

<p>Instead, why not pass a pointer to the <type>struct</type>?  I hear
you&emdash;doesn't the pointer have to get copied on the stack then?
Sure does, but a pointer is, these days, only 4 or 8 bytes, so it's much
easier on the machine, and works faster.</p>

<p>And there's even a little bit of <emp>syntactic sugar</emp> to help
access the fields in a pointer to a <type>struct</type>.  For those that
aren't aware, syntactic sugar is a feature of a compiler that simplifies
the code even though there is another way to accomplish the same thing.
For instance, I've already mentioned the <operator>+=</operator> a
number of times...what does it do?  Did I ever tell you?  To be honest,
in all the excitement, I've forgotten myself.  Here is an example that
shows how it works like another two operators, but is a little bit
easier to use.  It is syntactic sugar:</p>

<code>i = i + 12;  /* add 12 to i */
i += 12;     /* &lt;-- does exactly the same thing as "i = i + 12" */</code>

<p>You see?  It's not a necessary operator because there's another way
to do the same thing, but people like the shortcut.</p>

<p>But we are way off course, buster.  I was talking about pointers to
<type>struct</type>s, and here we are talking about how to access them.
Here's an example wherein we have a <type>struct</type> variable, and
another variable that is a pointer to that <type>struct</type> type, and
some usage for both (this will use <type>struct stuff</type> from above):</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

/* Here we declare the type so we can use it later: */
struct antelope {
	int val;
	float something;
};

int main(void)
{
	struct antelope a;
	struct antelope *b; /* this is a pointer to a struct antelope */

	b = &amp;a; /* let's point b at a for laughs and giggles */

	a.val = 3490; /* normal struct usage, as we've already seen */

	/* since b is a pointer, we have to dereference it before we can */
	/* use it:                                                       */

	(*b).val = 3491;

	/* but that looks kinda bad, so let's do the exact same thing  */
	/* except this time we'll use the "arrow operator", which is a */
	/* bit of syntactic sugar:                                     */

	b->val = 3491; /* EXACTLY the same as (*b).val = 3491; */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>So here we've seen a couple things.  For one, we have the manner with
which we dereference a pointer to a <type>struct</type> and then use the
dot operator (<operator>.</operator>) to access it.  This is kind of the
classic way of doing things: we have a pointer, so we dereference it to
get at the variable it points to, then we can treat it as if it
<emp>is</emp> that variable.</p>

<p>But, syntactic sugar to the rescue, we can use the <emp>arrow
operator</emp> (<operator>-&gt;</operator>) instead of the dot operator!
Saves us from looking ugly in the code, doesn't?  The arrow operator has
a build-in deference, so you don't have to mess with that syntax when
you have a pointer to a <type>struct</type>.  So the rule is this: if
you have a <type>struct</type>, use the dot operator; if you have a
<emp>pointer</emp> to a <type>struct</type>, use the arrow operator
(<operator>-&gt;</operator>).</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="ptsfunc">
<title>Passing <type>struct</type> pointers to functions</title>

<p>This is going to be a very short section about passing pointers to
structs to functions.  I mean, you already know how to pass variables as
paramters to functions, and you already know how to make and use
pointers to <type>struct</type>s, so there's really not much to be said
here.  An example should show it straightforwardly enough.
("Straightforwardly"--there's an oxymoronic word if ever I saw one.)</p>

<p>Grrrr.  Why do I always sit on this side of the bus?  I mean, I know
that the sun streams in here, and I can barely read my screen with the
bright light blazing away against it.  You think I'd learn by now.  So
<emp>anyway</emp>...</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

struct mutantfrog {
	int num_legs;
	int num_eyes;
};

void build_beejs_frog(struct mutantfrog *f)
{
	f->num_legs = 10;
	f->num_eyes = 1;
}

int main(void)
{
	struct mutantfrog rudolph;

	build_beejs_frog(&amp;rudolph);  /* passing a pointer to the struct */

	printf("leg count: %d\n", rudolph.num_legs); /* prints "10" */
	printf("eye count: %d\n", rudolph.num_eyes); /* prints "1" */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Another thing to notice here: if we passed the <type>stuct</type>
instead of a pointer to the <type>struct</type>, what would happen in
the function <func>build_beejs_frog()</func> when we changed the values?
That's right: they'd only be changed in the local copy, and not back at
out in <func>main()</func>.  So, in short, pointers to
<type>struct</type>s are the way to go when it comes to passing
<type>struct</type>s to functions.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="unions">
<title>Unions</title>

<p>Now that we've covered <type>struct</type>s to a certain extent, we
can talk about a related entity called a <type>union</type>.
Syntactically, <type>union</type>s are very much the same as
<type>struct</type>s; take the above examples and replace the word
<type>struct</type> with the word <type>union</type> and you're there.
But you need to be aware of the important difference between the two.</p>

<p>And the important difference is this: <type>union</type>s share the
same memory space for all their members.  For example, consider this
<type>union</type>:</p>

<code>union misc_stuff{
	int train_type;
	char *crab_name;
	float cups_of_coffee;
};</code>

<p>If you store something in the <var>train_type</var> field, it's going
to munge what's in the <var>crab_name</var> field and the
<var>cups_of_coffee</var> field.  That's because all three fields are
stored in the same place in memory.</p>

<p>The reason <type>union</type> exists is to all you to save memory in a
<type>struct</type>-like construct when you know you won't be using the
fields at the same time.  A more practical example might be if you
wanted to store data and its type, you could store the type as an
<type>int</type> (or an <type><link dest="enum">enum</link></type>,
talked about later), and then store the data in a <type>union</type>,
below that.</p>

<code><![CDATA[#include <stdio.h>

struct variable {
	// 0 = int, 1 = float, 2 = string
	int type;

	union data {
		int i;
		float f;
		char *s;
	} data;
};

void print_variable(struct variable *v)
{
	switch(v->type) {
	case 0: // int
		printf("%d\n", v->data.i);
		break;
	case 1: // float
		printf("%f\n", v->data.f);
		break;
	case 2: // string
		printf("%s\n", v->data.s);
		break;
	}
}

int main(void)
{
	struct variable v;

	v.type = 1;
	v.data.f = 0.8;

	print_variable(&v);

	return 0;
}]]></code>

</sect2>

<p>Just a quick note here to get you thinking about how you're going to
be breaking stuff down into basic blocks.  You now have a lot of
different tools at your disposal: loops, conditionals,
<type>struct</type>s, and especially functions.  Remember back on how
you learned to break down projects into little pieces and see what you'd
use these individual tools for.</p>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="arrays">
<title>Arrays</title>

<p>What a wide array of information we have for you in this section.
<emp>*BLAM*!</emp>  We're sorry&emdash;that pun has been taken out and
shot.</p>

<p>An array: a linear collection of related data.  Eh?  It's a
continuous chunk of memory that holds a number of identical data types.
Why would we want to do that?  Well, here's an example without
arrays:</p>

<code>int age0;
int age1;
int age2;
int age3;
int age4;

age1 = 10;
printf("age 1 is %d\n", age1);</code>

<p>And here is that same example using the magical power of arrays:</p>

<code>int age[5];

age[1] = 10;
printf("age 1 is %d\n", age[1]);</code>

<p>Ooooo!  See how much prettier that is?  You use the square-brackets
notation (<tt>[]</tt>) to access <emp>elements</emp> in the array by
putting an <type>int</type> variable in there or, like we did in the
example, a constant number.  Since you can <emp>index</emp> the array
using a variable, it means you can do things in loops and stuff.  Here's
a better example:</p>

<code>int i;
int age[5] = {10,20,25,8,2};

for(i = 0; i &lt; 5; i++) {
	printf("age %d is %d\n", i, age[i]);
}</code>

<p>whoa&emdash;we've done a couple new things here.  for one, you'll
notice in the array definition that we've initialized the entire array
at once.  this is allowed <emp>in the definition only</emp>.  once you
get down to the code, it's too late to initialize the array like this,
and it must be done an element at a time.</p>

<p>the other thing to notice is how we've accessed the array element
inside the <statement>for</statement> loop: using <var>age[i]</var>.  so
what happens in this <statement>for</statement> is that <var>i</var>
runs from 0 to 4, and so each <var>age</var> is printed out in turn,
like so:</p>

<screen>age 0 is 10
age 1 is 20
age 2 is 25
age 3 is 8
age 4 is 2</screen>

<p>why does it run from 0 to 4 instead of 1 to 5?  good question.  the
easiest answer is that the array index numbers are <emp>zero-based</emp>
instead of one-based.  that's not really an answer, i know...well, it
turns out that most (if not all) processors use zero-based indexing in
their machine code for doing memory access, so this maps very well to
that.</p>

<p>You can make arrays of any type you desire, including
<type>struct</type>s, and pointers.</p>

<sect2 id="array2fun">
<title>Passing arrays to functions</title>

<p>it's pretty effortless to pass an array to a function, but things get
a little wierd.  the weirdest part is that when you pass the "whole"
array by putting its name in as a parameter to the function, it's
actually a <emp>pointer to the first element of the array</emp> that
gets passed in for you.</p>

<p>now, inside the function, you can still access the array using array
notation (<tt>[]</tt>).  here's an example:</p>

<code>void init_array(int a[], int count)
{
	int i;

	/* for each element, set it equal to its index number times 10: */

	for(i = 0; i &lt; count; i++)
		a[i] = i * 10;
}

int main(void)
{
	int mydata[10];

	init_array(mydata, 10);  /* note lack of [] notation */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>A couple things to note here are that we didn't have to specify the
array <emp>dimension</emp> (that is, how many elements are in the array)
in the declaration for <func>init_array()</func>.  We could have, but we
didn't have to.</p>

<p>Also, since an array in C has no built-in concept of how big it is
(i.e. how many elements it holds), we have to be nice and cooperative
and actually pass in the array size separately into the function.  We
use it later in the <statement>for</statement> to know how many elements
to initialize.</p>

<p>Hey!  We didn't use the address-of operator in the call!  Wouldn't
that make a copy of the array onto the stack?  Isn't that bad?  Well,
no.</p>

<p>When you have an array, leaving off the and square brackets gives you
a <emp>pointer</emp> to the first element of the array.  (You can use
the address-of operator if you want, but it actually results in a
different pointer type, so it might not be what you expect.)  So it is,
in fact, a pointer to the array that's getting copied onto the stack for
the function call, not the entire array.</p>

<p>Right about now, you should be recognizing that you can use arrays to
hold a lot of things, and that could serve you quite well in your
projects which often involve collections of data.  For instance, let's
say:</p>

<offsettext><p>We have a virtual world where we have a number of virtual
creatures that run around doing virtual things.  Each creature has a
real X and Y coordinate.  There are 12 creatures.  Each step of the
simulation, the creatures will process their behavior algorithm and move
to a new position.  The new position should be
displayed.</p></offsettext>

<p>Uh oh!  Time for building blocks!  What do we have?  Ok, we need an
X and Y coordinate for the creatures.  We need 12 creatures.  We need a
construct that repeatedly processes the behavior for each.  And we need
output.</p>

<p>So the coordinates of the creature.  There are a few ways to do this.
You could have two arrays of 12 elements, one to hold the X and one to
hold the Y coordinate.  (These are known as <emp>parallel arrays</emp>.)
But let's instead try to think of a way that we could bundle those data
together.  I mean, they're both related to the same virtual creature, so
wouldn't it be nice to have them somehow logically related?  If only
there were a way...but wait!  That's right!  A <type>struct</type>!</p>

<code>struct creature {
	float x;
	float y;
};</code>

<p>There we go.  Now we need 12 of them; 12 items of type <type>struct
creature</type>.  What's a good way of holding a collection of identical
types?  Yes, yes!  Array!</p>

<code>struct creature guys[12];</code>

<p>So what else&emdash;we need to be able to repeatedly execute the
behavior of these creatures.  Like looping over and over and over...yes,
a loop would be good for that.  But how many times should we loop?  I
mean, the specification didn't tell us that, so it's an excellent
question.  Often we'll loop until some exit condition is true (like the
user presses ESCAPE or something like that), but since the spec writer
didn't say, let's just loop forever.</p>

<code>for(;;) {  /* loop forever */</code>

<p>Now what?  We need to write the behavior of the creatures and put it
in the loop, right?  Since this is a lot of self-contained code we're
about to write, we might as well stick it in a function and call that
function for each of the creatures.  But I'll leave the actual
implementation of that function up to you, the reader. <smiley/></p>

<code>for(i = 0; i &lt; 12; i++) {
			execute_behavior(&amp;(guys[i]));
		}</code>

<p>You notice that we did use the address-of operator there in the call.
In this case, we're not passing the whole array; we're just passing a
pointer to a single element in the array.  It's not always necessary to
do that (you could have it copy the single element in the call), but
since this is a <type>struct</type>, I pass a pointer to keep the memory
overhead low.</p>

<p>The last thing to do was to output the information.  How this is done
should be in the spec, but isn't.  It would be cool to do a
hi-resolution screen with little icons for where the creatures are, but
that is currently beyond the scope of what we're doing here, so we'll
just write a simple thing to print out the creatures.</p>

<p>One final note&emdash;it's always a good idea to initialize the data
before using it, right?  So I'll write a function that initializes the
creatures, too, before we use it.  How it initializes them is also
undefined in the spec, so I'll arbitrarily set them up in a diagonal
line.</p>

<p>Completed (except for the behavior) code:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

struct creature {
	float x;
	float y;
};

void execute_behavior(struct creature *c)
{
	/* does nothing now */
	/* --you'll have to code it if you want them to ever move! */
}

main(int main(void)
{
	int i;
	struct creature guys[12];

	/* initialize them--could be its own function: */

	for(i = 0; i &lt; 12; i++) {
		guys[i].x = (float)i; /* (float) is a "cast"--it changes the type! */
		guys[i].y = (float)i;
	}

	/* main loop */

	for(;;) {   /* loop forever */

		/* have them do their thing: */

		for(i = 0; i &lt; 12; i++) {
			execute_behavior(&amp;(guy[i]));
		}

		/* output the result */
		for(i = 0; i &lt; 12; i++) {
			printf("creature %d: (%.2f, %.2f)\n", i, guys[i].x, guys[i].y);
		}
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>I threw in a <emp>cast</emp> there in the code: <tt>(float)</tt>.
See <var>i</var> is an <type>int</type>, but each of the fields
<var>guys[i].x</var> and <var>guys[i].y</var> is a <type>float</type>.
The cast changes the expression right after it, in this case
"<var>i</var>" to the specified type.  It's always a good idea to have
the same types on both sides of the assignment operator
(<operator>=</operator>).</p>

<p>Another new thing is the "<tt>%.2f</tt>" in the <func>printf()</func>
format string.  A plain "<tt>%f</tt>" means to print a
<type>float</type>, which is what we're passing it.  The addtional
"<tt>.2</tt>" means print it using two decimal places.  You can leave
the "<tt>.2</tt>" off and see what happens. <smiley/></p>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="strings">
<title>Strings</title>

<p>A string is a theoretical construct in modern physics that is used to
help explain the very fabric of the universe itself.</p>

<p>This is <emp>exactly</emp> the same as a C string, except that it is,
in fact, completely different.</p>

<p>A string in C is a sequence of bytes in memory that usually contains
a bunch of letters.  Constant strings in C are surrounded by
double quotes (<tt>"</tt>).  You may have seen strings before in such
programming blockbusters, such as Hello World:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	printf("Hello, World!\n");

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>You've spotted the string <tt>"Hello, World!\n"</tt> in there, haven't
you.</p>

<p>What type is that string, anyway?  Well, it turns out that a constant
string (that is, one in double quotes) is of type <type>char*</type>.
But you can also put a string in a <type>char</type> array, if you so
desire.  The <type>char*</type> points at the first character in the
string.  Examples:</p> 

<code>char *s = "Hello!";

printf("%s\n", s);    /* prints "Hello!" */
printf("%c\n", *s);   /* prints 'H' */
printf("%c\n", s[0]); /* prints 'H' */
printf("%c\n", s[1]); /* prints 'e' */
printf("%c\n", s[4]); /* prints 'o' */</code>

<p>(Note the two new format specifiers for <func>printf()</func> here:
<tt>%c</tt> for printing a single <type>char</type>, and <tt>%s</tt> for
printing a string!  Ain't that exciting!)</p>

<p>And look here, we're accessing this string in a whole variety of
different ways.  We're printing the whole thing, and we're printing
single characters.</p>

<p>You can also initialize <type>char</type> arrays during their
definition, just like other arrays:</p>

<code>char s[20] = "The aliens are coming!";</code>

<p>And you can change the array elements on the fly, too by simply
assigning into it:</p>

<code>char s[20] = "Give me $10!";

printf("%s\n", s);  /* prints "Give me $10!" */

s[9] = '8';
printf("%s\n", s);  /* prints "Give me $80!" */</code>

<p>In this case, note that we've put a constant <type>char</type> on the
right side of the assignment.  Constant <type>char</type>s use the
single quote (<tt>'</tt>).</p>

<p>One more thing to remember is that when you specify an array by name
without the square brackets, it's just like using a pointer to the
beginning of the array.  So you can actually do assignments like
this:</p>

<code>char a[20] = "Cats are better.";
char *p;

p = a;  /* p now points to the first char in array a */</code>

<p>One more thing: strings in C end with a NUL character.  That is, a
zero.  It is most properly written as '\0',  You can truncate a string
to zero length by assigning '\0' to the first byte in the string.  Also,
all the standard string functions assume the string ends with a NUL
character.</p>

<p>Standard string functions, did I say?  Yes, I did.</p>

<p>C provides a whole metric slew of functions that you can use to
modify strings, stick them together, parse them apart, and so on.  Check
out the reference section for all the brilliant <emp>string processing
power</emp> at your disposal.  It is your responsibility as a citizen of
the Planet Earth to wield this ultimate power wisely!  (And pay me
$80.)</p>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="dydydynamic">
<title>Dynamic Memory</title>

<p>Well, aren't you looking dynamic this morning, reader?  Or is it
evening?  I always lose track of these things.</p>

<p>Up until now, we've been talking about memory that pretty much is set
up at the beginning of the program run.  You have constant strings here
and there, arrays of predeclared length, and variables all declared
ahead of time.  But what if you have something like the following?</p>

<offsettext><p><b>Assignment:</b> Implement a program that will read an arbitrary
number of integers from the keyboard.  The first line the user enters
will be the number of <type>int</type>s to read.  The <type>int</type>s
themselves will appear on subsequent lines, one <type>int</type> per
line.</p></offsettext>

<p>Yes, it's that time again: break it up into component parts that you
can implement.  You'll need to read lines of text from the keyboard
(there's a cool little function called <func>fgets()</func> that can help
here), and the first line you'll need to convert to an integer so you
know how many more lines to read.  (You can use <func>atoi()</func>,
read "ascii-to-integer" to do this conversion.)  Then you'll need to
read that many more strings and store them...where?</p>

<p>Here's where dynamic memory can help out&emdash;we need to store a
bunch of <type>int</type>s, but we don't know how many until after the
program has already started running.  What we do is find out how many
<type>int</type>s we need, then we calculate how many bytes we need for
each, multiply those two numbers to get the total number of bytes we
need to store everything, and then ask the OS to allocate that many
bytes for us on the heap for us to use in the manner we choose.  In this
case, we're choosing to store <type>int</type>s in there.</p>

<p>There are three functions we're going to talk about here.  Well, make
that four functions, but one is just a variant of another:
<func>malloc()</func> (allocate some memory for us to use),
<func>free()</func> (release some memory that <func>malloc()</func> gave
us earlier), <func>realloc()</func> (change the size of some previously
allocated memory), and <func>calloc()</func> (just like
<func>malloc()</func>, except clears the memory to zero.)</p>

<p>Using these functions in unison results in a beautifully intricate
dance of data, ebbing and flowing with the strong tidal pull of the
dedicated user's will.</p>

<p>Yeah.  Let's cut the noise and get on with it here.</p>

<sect2 id="mallocg">
<title><func>malloc()</func></title>

<p>This is the big one: he's the guy that gives you memory when you ask
for it.  It returns to you a pointer to a chunk of memory of a specified
number of bytes, or <type>NULL</type> if there is some kind of error
(like you're out of memory).  The return type is actually
<type>void*</type>, so it can turn into a pointer to whatever you
want.</p>

<p>Since <func>malloc()</func> operates in bytes of memory and you often
operate with other data types (e.g. "Allocate for me 12
<type>int</type>s."), people often use the <operator>sizeof()</operator>
operator to determine how many bytes to allocate, for example:</p>

<code>int *p;

p = malloc(sizeof(int) * 12); // allocate for me 12 ints! </code>

<p>Oh, and that was pretty much an example of how to use
<func>malloc()</func>, too.  You can reference the result using pointer
arithmetic or array notation; either is fine since it's a pointer.  But
you should really check the result for errors:</p>

<code>int *p;

p = malloc(sizeof(float) * 3490); // allocate 3490 floats!

if (p == NULL) {
	printf("Horsefeathers!  We're probably out of memory!\n");
	exit(1);
}</code>

<p>More commonly, people pack this onto one line:</p>

<code>if ((p = malloc(100)) == NULL) { // allocate 100 bytes
	printf("Ooooo!  Out of memory error!\n");
	exit(1);
}</code>

<p>Now remember this: you're allocating memory on the heap and there are
only two ways to ever get that memory back: 1) your program can exit, or
2) you can call <func>free()</func> to free a <func>malloc()</func>'d
chunk.  If your program runs for a long time and keeps
<func>malloc()</func>ing and never <func>free()</func>ing when it
should, it's said to "leak" memory.  This often manifests itself in a
way such as, "Hey, Bob.  I started your print job monitor program a week
ago, and now it's using 13 terabytes of RAM.  Why is that?"</p>

<p>Be sure to avoid memory leaks!  <func>free()</func> that memory when
you're done with it!</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="gfree">
<title><func>free()</func></title>

<p>Speaking of how to free memory that you've allocated, you do it with
the implausibly-named <func>free()</func> function.</p>

<p>This function takes as its argument a pointer that you've picked up
using <func>malloc()</func> (or <func>calloc()</func>).  And it releases
the memory associated with that data.  You really should never use
memory after it has been <func>free()</func>'d.  It would be Bad.</p>

<p>So how about an example:</p>

<code>int *p;

p = malloc(sizeof(int) * 37); // 37 ints!

free(p);  // on second thought, never mind! </code>

<p>Of course, between the <func>malloc()</func> and the
<func>free()</func>, you can do anything with the memory your twisted
little heart desires.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="grealloc">
<title><func>realloc()</func></title>

<p><func>realloc()</func> is a fun little function that takes a chunk of
memory you allocated with <func>malloc()</func> (or
<func>calloc()</func>) and changes the size of the memory chunk.  Maybe
you thought you only needed 100 <type>int</type>s at first, but now you
need 200.  You can <func>realloc()</func> the block to give you the
space you need.</p>

<p>This is all well and good, except that <func>realloc()</func> might
have to <emp>move your data</emp> to another place in memory if it
can't, for whatever reason, increase the size of the current block.
It's not omnipotent, after all.</p>

<p>What does this mean for you, the mortal?  Well in short, it means you
should use <func>realloc()</func> sparingly since it could be an
expensive operation.  Usually the procedure is to keep track of how much
room you have in the memory block, and then add another big chunk to it
if you run out.  So first you allocate what you'd guess is enough room
to hold all the data you'd require, and then if you happened to run out,
you'd reallocate the block with the next best guess of what you'd
require in the future.  What makes a good guess depends on the program.
Here's an example that just allocates more "buckets" of space as
needed:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

#define INITIAL_SIZE 10
#define BUCKET_SIZE 5

static int data_count; // how many ints we have stored
static int data_size;  // how many ints we *can* store in this block
static int *data;      // the block of data, itself

int main(void)
{
	void add_data(int new_data); // function prototype
	int i;

	// first, initialize the data area:
	data_count = 0;
	data_size = INITIAL_SIZE;
	data = malloc(data_size * sizeof(int)); // allocate initial area

	// now add a bunch of data
	for(i = 0; i &lt; 23; i++) {
		add_data(i);
	}

	return 0;
}

void add_data(int new_data)
{
	// if data_count == data_size, the area is full and
	// needs to be realloc()'d before we can add another:

	if (data_count == data_size) {
		// we're full up, so add a bucket
		data_size += BUCKET_SIZE;
		data = realloc(data, data_size * sizeof(int));
	}

	// now store the data
	*(data+data_count) = new_data;

	// ^^^ the above line could have used array notation, like so:
	//  data[data_count] = new_data;

	data_count++;
}</code>

<p>In the above code, you can see that a potentially expensive
<func>realloc()</func> is only done after the first 10 <type>int</type>s
have been stored, and then again only after each block of five after
that.  This beats doing a <func>realloc()</func> every time you add a
number, hands down.</p>

<p>(Yes, yes, in that completely contrived example, since I know I'm
adding 23 numbers right off the get-go, it would make much more sense to
set <var>INITIAL_SIZE</var> to 25 or something, but that defeats the
whole purpose of the example, now, doesn't it?)</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="gcalloc">
<title><func>calloc()</func></title>

<p>Since you've already read the section on <func>malloc()</func> (you
have, right?), this part will be easy!  Yay!  Here's the scoop:
<func>calloc()</func> is just like <func>malloc()</func>, except that it
1) clears the memory to zero for you, and 2) it takes two parameters
instead of one.</p>

<p>The two parameters are the number of elements that are to be in the
memory block, and the size of each element.  Yes, this is exactly like
we did in <func>malloc()</func>, except that <func>calloc()</func> is
doing the multiply for you:</p>

<code>// this:
p = malloc(10 * sizeof(int));

// is just like this:
p = calloc(10, sizeof(int));
// (and the memory is cleared to zero when using calloc())</code>

<p>The pointer returned by <func>calloc()</func> can be used with
<func>realloc()</func> and <func>free()</func> just as if you had used
<func>malloc()</func>.</p>

<p>The drawback to using <func>calloc()</func> is that it takes time to
clear memory, and in most cases, you don't need it clear since you'll
just be writing over it anyway.  But if you ever find yourself
<func>malloc()</func>ing a block and then setting the memory to zero
right after, you can use <func>calloc()</func> to do that in one
call.</p>

<p>I wish this section on <func>calloc()</func> were more exciting, with
plot, passion, and violence, like any good Hollywood picture, but...this
is C programming we're talking about.  And that should be exciting in
its own right.  Sorry!</p>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="morestuff">
<title>More Stuff!</title>

<p>This is the section where we flesh out a bunch of the stuff we'd done
before, except in more detail.  We even throw a couple new things in
there for good measure.  You can read these sections in any order you
want and as you feel you need to.</p>

<sect2 id="ptarith">
<title>Pointer Arithmetic</title>

<p>Pointer <emp>what</emp>?  Yeah, that's right: you can perform math on
pointers.  What does it mean to do that, though?  Well, pay attention,
because people use <emp>pointer arithmetic</emp> all the time to
manipulate pointers and move around through memory.</p>

<p>You can add to and subtract from pointers.  If you have a pointer to
a <type>char</type>, incrementing that pointer moves to the next
<type>char</type> in memory (one byte up).  If you have a pointer to an
<type>int</type>, incrementing that pointer moves to the next
<type>int</type> in memory (which might be four bytes up, or some other
number depending on your CPU architecture.)  It's important to know that
the number of bytes of memory it moves differs depending on the type of
pointer, but that's actually all taken care of for you.</p>

<code>/* This code prints: */
/*  50               */
/*  99               */
/*  3490             */

int main(void)
{
	int a[4] = { 50, 99, 3490, 0 };
	int *p;

	p = a;
	while(*p > 0) {
		printf("%i\n", *p);
		p++; /* go to the next int in memory */
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>What have we done!  How does this print out the values in the array?
First of all, we point <var>p</var> at the first element of the array.
Then we're going to loop until what <var>p</var> points at is less than
or equal to zero.  Then, inside the loop, we print what <var>p</var> is
pointing at.  Finally, <emp>and here's the tricky part</emp>, we
<emp>increment the pointer</emp>.  This causes the pointer to move to
the next <type>int</type> in memory so we can print it.</p>

<p>In this case, I've arbitrarily decided (yeah, it's shockingly true: I
just make all this stuff up) to mark the end of the array with a zero
value so I know when to stop printing.  This is known as a <emp>sentinel
value</emp>...that is, something that lets you know when some data ends.
If this sounds familiar, it's because you just saw it in the section on
strings.  Remember&emdash;strings end in a zero character
(<tt>'\0'</tt>) and the string functions use this as a sentinel value to
know where the string ends.</p>

<p>Lots of times, you see a <statement>for</statement> loop used to go
through pointer stuff.  For instance, here's some code that copies a
string:</p>

<code>char *source = "Copy me!";
char dest[20];  /* we'll copy that string into here */

char *sp;  /* source pointer */
char *dp;  /* destination pointer */

for(sp = source, dp = dest; *sp != '\0'; sp++, dp++) {
	*dp = *sp;
}

printf("%s\n", dest); /* prints "Copy me!" */</code>

<p>Looks complicated!  Something new here is the <emp>comma
operator</emp> (<operator>,</operator>).  The comma operator allows you
to stick expressions together.  The total value of the expression is the
rightmost expression after the comma, but all parts of the expression
are evaluated, left to right.</p>

<p>So let's take apart this <statement>for</statement> loop and see
what's up.  In the initialization section, we point <var>sp</var> and
<var>dp</var> to the source string and the destination area we're going
to copy it to.</p>

<p>In the body of the loop, the actual copy takes place.  We copy, using
the assignment operator, the character that the source pointer points
to, to the address that the destination pointer points to.  So in this
way, we're going to copy the string a letter at a time.</p>

<p>The middle part of the <statement>for</statement> loop is the
continuation condition&emdash;we check here to see if the source pointer
points at a NUL character which we know exists at the end of the source
string.  Of course, at first, it's pointing at <tt>'C'</tt> (of the
"Copy me!" string), so we're free to continue.</p>

<p>At the end of the <statement>for</statement> statement we'll
increment both <var>sp</var> and <var>dp</var> to move to the next
character to copy.  Copy, copy, copy!</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="typedef">
<title><statement>typedef</statement></title>

<p>This one isn't too difficult to wrap your head around, but there are
some strange nuances to it that you might see out in the wild.
Basically <statement>typedef</statement> allows you to make up an alias
for a certain type, so you can reference it by that name instead.</p>

<p>Why would you want to do that?  The most common reason is that the
other name is a little bit too unwieldy and you want something more
concise...and this most commonly occurs when you have a
<type>struct</type> that you want to use.</p>

<code>struct a_structure_with_a_large_name {
	int a;
	float b;
};

typedef struct a_structure_with_a_large_name NAMESTRUCT;

int main(void)
{
	/* we can make a variable of the structure like this: */
	struct a_structure_with_a_large_name one_variable;

	/* OR, we can do it like this: */
	NAMESTRUCT another_variable;

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>In the above code, we've defined a type, <type>NAMESTRUCT</type>,
that can be used in place of the other type, <type>struct
a_structure_with_a_large_name</type>.  Note that this is now a
full-blown type; you can use it in function calls, or whereever you'd
use a "normal" type.  (Don't tell <statement>typedef</statement>'d types
they're not normal&emdash;it's impolite.)</p>

<p>You're probably also wondering why the new type name is in all caps.
Historically, <statement>typedef</statement>'d types have been all caps
in C by convention (it's certainly not necessary.)  In C++, this is no
longer the case and people use mixed case more often.  Since this is a C
guide, we'll stick to the old ways.</p>

<p>(One thing you might commonly see is a <type>struct</type> with an
underscore before the <type>struct</type> tag name in the
<statement>typedef</statement>.  Though technically illegal, many
programmers like to use the same name for the <type>struct</type> as
they do for the new type, and putting the underscore there
differentiates the two visaully.  But you shouldn't do it.)</p>

<p>You can also typedef "anonymous" <type>struct</type>s, like this</p>

<code>typedef struct {
	int a;
	float b;
} someData;</code>

<p>So then you can define variables as type <type>someData</type>.  Very
exciting.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="enum">
<title><type>enum</type></title>

<p>Sometimes you have a list of numbers that you want to use to
represent different things, but it's easier for the programmer to
represent those things by name instead of number.  You can use an
<type>enum</type> to make symbolic names for integer numbers
that programmers can use later in their code in place of
<type>int</type>s.</p>

<p>(I should note that C is more relaxed that C++ is here about
interchanging <type>int</type>s and <type>enum</type>s.
We'll be all happy and C-like here, though.)</p>

<p>Note that an <type>enum</type> is a type, too.  You can
<statement>typedef</statement> it, you can pass them into functions, and
so on, again, just like "normal" types.</p>

<p>Here are some enums and their usage.  Remember&emdash;treat them just
like <type>int</type>s, more or less.</p>

<code>enum fishtypes {
	HALIBUT,
	TUBESNOUT,
	SEABASS,
	ROCKFISH
};

int main(void)
{
	enum fishtypes fish1 = SEABASS;
	enum fishtypes fish2;

	if (fish1 == SEABASS) {
		fish2 = TUBESNOUT;
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Nothing to it&emdash;they're just symbolic names for unique numbers.
Basically it's easier for other programmers to read and maintain.</p>

<p>Now, you can print them out using <tt>%d</tt> in
<func>printf()</func>, if you want.  For the most part, though, there's
no reason to know what the actual number is; usually you just want the
symbolic representation.</p>

<p>But, since I know you're dying of curiosity, I might as well tell you
that the <type>enum</type>s start at zero by default, and increase from
there.  So in the above example, <tt>HALIBUT</tt> would be 0,
<tt>TUBESNOUT</tt> would be 1, and <tt>ROCKFISH</tt> would be 3.</p>

<p>If you want, though, you can override any or all of these:</p>

<code>enum frogtypes {
	THREELEGGED=3,
	FOUREYED,
	SIXHEADED=6
};</code>

<p>In the above case, two of the enums are explicitly defined.  For
<tt>FOUREYED</tt> (which isn't defined), it just increments one from the
last defined value, so its value is 4.  You can, if you're curious, have
duplicate values, but why would you want to, sicko?</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="morestruct">
<title>More <type>struct</type> declarations</title>

<p>Remember how, many moons ago, I mentioned that there were a number of
ways to declare <type>struct</type>s and not all of them made a whole
lot of sense.  We've already seen how to declare a <type>struct</type>
globally to use later, as well as one in a
<statement>typedef</statement> situation, <emp>comme ca</emp>:</p>

<code>/* standalone: */

struct antelope {
	int legcount;
	float angryfactor;
};

/* or with typedef: */

typedef struct _goatcheese {
	char victim_name[40];
	float cheesecount;
} GOATCHEESE;</code>

<p>But you can also declare variables along with the <type>struct</type>
declaration by putting them directly afterward:</p>

<code>struct breadtopping {
	enum toppingtype type; /* BUTTER, MARGARINE or MARMITE */
	float amount;
} mytopping;

/* just like if you'd later declared: */

struct breadtopping mytopping;</code>

<p>So there we've kinda stuck the variable defintion on the tail end
of the <type>struct</type> definition.  Pretty sneaky, but you see that
happen from time to time in that so-called <emp>Real Life</emp> thing
that I hear so much about.</p>

<p>And, just when you thought you had it all, you can actually omit the
<statement>struct</statement> name in many cases.  For example:</p>

<code>typedef struct { /* &lt;--Hey!  We left the name off! */
	char name[100];
	int num_movies;
} ACTOR_PRESIDENT;</code>

<p>It's more <emp>right</emp> to name all your <type>struct</type>s,
even if you don't use the proper name and only use the
<statement>typedef</statement>'d name, but you still see those naked
<type>struct</type>s here and there.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="clargs">
<title>Command Line Arguments</title>

<p>I've been lying to you this whole time, I must admit.  I thought I
could hide it from you and not get caught, but you realized that
something was wrong...why doesn't the <func>main()</func> have a return
type or argument list?</p>

<p>Well, back in the depths of time, for some reason, !!!TODO
research!!! it was perfectly acceptable to do that.  And it persists to
this day.  Feel free to do that, in fact,  But that's not telling you
the whole story, and it's time you knew the <emp>whole truth</emp>!</p>

<p>Welcome to the real world:</p>

<code>int main(int argc, char **argv)</code>

<p>Whoa!  What is all that stuff?  Before I tell you, though, you have
to realize that programs, when executed from the command line, accept
arguments from the command line program, and return a result to the
command line program.  Using many Unix shells, you can get the return
value of the program in the shell variable <var>$?</var>.  (This doesn't
even work in the windows command shell&emdash;use !!!TODO look up
windows return variable!!! instead.)  And you specify parameters to the
program on the command line after the program name.  So if you have a
program called "makemoney", you can run it with parameters, and then
check the return value, like this:</p>

<screen>$ makemoney fast alot
$ echo $?
2</screen>

<p>In this case, we've passed two command line arguments, "fast" and
"alot", and gotten a return value back in the variable <var>$?</var>,
which we've printed using the Unix <com>echo</com> command.  How
does the program read those arguments, and return that value?</p>

<p>Let's do the easy part first: the return value.  You've noticed that
the above prototype for <func>main()</func> returns an <type>int</type>.
Swell!  So all you have to do is either <statement>return</statement>
that value from <func>main()</func> somewhere, or, alternatively, you
can call the function <func>exit()</func> with an exit value as the
parameter:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int a = 12;

	if (a == 2) {
		exit(3); /* just like running (from main()) "return 3;" */
	}

	return 2; /* just like calling exit(2); */
}</code>

<p>For historical reasons, an exit status of <tt>0</tt> has meant
success, while nonzero means failure.  Other programs can check your
program's exit status and react accordingly.</p>

<p>Ok that's the return status.  What about those arguments?  Well, that
whole definition of <var>argv</var> looks too intimidating to start
with.  What about this <var>argc</var> instead?  It's just an
<type>int</type>, and an easy one at that.  It contains the total count
of arguments on the command line, <emp>including the name of the program
itself</emp>.  For example:</p>

<screen>$ makemoney fast alot         # &lt;-- argc == 3
$ makemoney                   # &lt;-- argc == 1
$ makemoney 1 2 3 4 5         # &lt;-- argc == 6</screen>

<p>(The dollar sign, above, is a common Unix command shell prompt.  And
that hash mark (<tt>#</tt>) is the command shell comment character in
Unix.  I'm a Unix-dork, so you'll have to deal.  If you have a problem,
talk to those friendly Stormtroopers over there.)</p>

<p>Good, good.  Not much to that <var>argc business</var>, either.  Now
the biggie: <var>argv</var>.  As you might have guessed, this is where
the arguments themselves are stored.  But what about that
<type>char**</type> type?  What do you do with that?  Fortunately, you
can often use array notation in the place of a dereference, since you'll
recall arrays and pointers are related beasties.  In this case, you can
think of <var>argv</var> as an array of pointers to strings, where each
string pointed to is one of the command line arguments:</p>

<screen>$ makemoney   somewhere  somehow
$ # argv[0]    argv[1]   argv[2]   (and argc is 3)</screen>

<p>Each of these array elements, <var>argv[0]</var>, <var>argv[1]</var>,
and so on, is a string.  (Remember a string is just a pointer to a
<type>char</type> or an array of <type>char</type>s, the name of which
is a pointer to the first element of the array.)</p>

<p>I haven't told you much of what you can do with strings yet, but
check out the reference section for more information.  What you do know
is how to <func>printf()</func> a string using the "<tt>%s</tt>" format
specifier, and you do know how to do a loop.  So let's write a program
that simply prints out its command line arguments, and then sets an exit
status value of 4:</p>

<code>/* showargs.c */

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(int argc, char **argv)
{
	int i;

	printf("There are %d things on the command line\n", argc);
	printf("The program name is \"%s\"\n", argv[0];

	printf("The arguments are:\n");
	
	for(i = 1; i &lt; argc; i++) {
		printf("    %s\n", argv[i]);
	}

	return 4; /* exit status of 4 */
}</code>

<p>Note that we started printing arguments at index 1, since we already
printed <var>argv[0]</var> before that.  So sample runs and output
(assuming we compiled this into a program called
<com>showargs</com>):</p>

<screen>$ showargs alpha bravo
There are 3 things on the command line
The program name is "showargs"
The arguments are:
    alpha
	bravo

$ showargs
There are 1 things on the command line
The program name is "showargs"
The arguments are:

$ showargs 12
There are 2 things on the command line
The program name is "showargs"
The arguments are:
    12</screen>

<p>(The actual thing in <var>argv[0]</var> might differ from system to
system.  Sometimes it'll contain some path information or other
stuff.)</p>

<p>So that's the secret for getting stuff into your program from the
command line!</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="multiarray">
<title>Multidimensional Arrays</title>

<p>Welcome to...the <emp>Nth Dimension!</emp>  Bet you never thought
you'd see that.  Well, here we are.  Yup.  The Nth Dimension.</p>

<p>Ok, then.  Well, you've seen how you can arrange sequences of data in
memory using an array.  It looks something like this:</p>

<p>!!!TODO image of 1d array</p>

<p>Now, imagine, if you will, a <emp>grid</emp> of elements instead of
just a single row of them:</p>

<p>This is an example of a <emp>two-dimensional</emp> array, and can be
indexed by giving a row number and a column number as the index, like
this: <tt>a[2][10]</tt>.  You can have as many dimensions in an array
that you want, but I'm not going to draw them because 2D is already past
the limit of my artistic skills.</p>

<p>So check this code out&emdash;it makes up a two-dimensional array,
initializes it in the definition (see how we nest the squirrely braces
there during the init), and then uses a <emp>nested loop</emp> (that is,
a loop inside another loop) to go through all the elements and
pretty-print them to the screen.</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	int a[2][5] = {	{ 10, 20, 30, 40, 55 },  /* [2][5] == [rows][cols] */
					{ 10, 18, 21, 30, 44 } };

	int i, j;

	for(i = 0; i &lt; 2; i++) {     /* for all the rows... */
		for(j = 0; j &lt; 5; j++) { /* print all the columns! */
			printf("%d ", a[i][j]);
		}

		/* at the end of the row, print a newline for the next row */
		printf("\n"); 
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>As you might well imagine, since there really is no surprise ending
for a program so simple as this one, the output will look something like
this:</p>

<screen>10 20 30 40 55
10 18 21 30 44</screen>

<p>Hold on for a second, now, since we're going to take this concept for
a spin and learn a little bit more about how arrays are stored in
memory, and some of tricks you can use to access them.  First of all,
you need to know that in the previous example, even though the array has
two rows and is multidimensional, the data is stored sequentially in
memory in this order: 10, 20, 30, 40, 55, 10, 18, 21, 30, 44.</p>

<p>See how that works?  The compiler just puts one row after the next
and so on.</p>

<p>But hey!  Isn't that just like a one-dimensional array, then?  Yes,
for the most part, it technically is!  A lot of programmers don't even
bother with multidimensional arrays at all, and just use single
dimensional, doing the math by hand to find a particular row and
column.  You can't technically just switch dimensions whenever you feel
like it, Buccaroo Bonzai, because the types are different.  And it'd be
bad form, besides.</p>

<p>For instance...nevermind the "for instance".  Let's do the same
example again using a single dimensional array:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	int a[10] = {	10, 20, 30, 40, 55,  /* 10 elements (2x5) */
					10, 18, 21, 30, 44 };

	int i, j;

	for(i = 0; i &lt; 2; i++) {     /* for all the rows... */
		for(j = 0; j &lt; 5; j++) { /* print all the columns! */
			int index = i*5 + j; /* calc the index */
			printf("%d ", a[index]);
		}

		/* at the end of the row, print a newline for the next row */
		printf("\n"); 
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>So in the middle of the loop we've declared a local variable
<var>index</var> (yes, you can do that&emdash;remember local variables
are local to their block (that is, local to their surrounding squirrley
braces)) and we calculate it using <var>i</var> and <var>j</var>.  Look
at that calculation for a bit to make sure it's correct.  This is
technically what the compiler does behind your back when you accessed
the array using multidimensional notation.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="cast">
<title>Casting and promotion</title>

<p>Sometimes you have a type and you want it to be a different type.
Here's a great example:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int a = 5;
	int b = 10;
	float f;

	f = a / b;  /* calculate 5 divided by 10 */
	printf("%.2f\n", f);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>And this prints:</p>

<code>0</code>

<p>...What?  Five divided by 10 is zero?  Since when?  I'll tell you:
since we entered the world of integer-only division.  When you divide
one <type>int</type> by another <type>int</type>, the result is an
<type>int</type>, and any fractional part is thrown away.  What do we do
if we want the result to become a <type>float</type> somewhere along the
way so that the result is correct?</p>

<p>Turns out, either integer (or both) in the divide can be made into a
<type>float</type>, and then the result of the divide will be also be a
<type>float</type>.  So just change one and everything should work
out.</p>

<p>"Get on with it!  How do you cast?"  Oh yeah&emdash;I guess I should
actually do it.  You might recall the cast from other parts of this
guide, but just in case, we'll show it again:</p>

<code>f = (float)a / b;  /* calculate 5 divided by 10 */</code>

<p>Bam!  There is is!  Putting the new type in parens in front of the
expression to be converted, and it magically becomes that type!</p>

<p>You can cast almost anything to almost anything else, and if you mess
it up somehow, it's entirely your fault since the compiler will blindly
do whatever you ask. <smiley/></p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="incomplete">
<title>Incomplete types</title>

<p>This topic is a little bit more advanced, but bear with it for a bit.
An incomplete type is simply the declaration of the name of a particular
<type>struct</type>, put there so that you can use pointers to the
<type>struct</type> without actually knowing the fields stored therein.
It most often comes up when people don't want to
<statement>#include</statement> another header file, which can happen
for a variety of different reasons.</p>

<p>For example, here we use a pointer to a type without actually having
it defined anywhere in <func>main()</func>.  (It is defined elsewhere,
though.)</p>

<code>struct foo;  /* incomplete type!  Notice it's, well, incomplete. */

int main(void)
{
	struct foo *w;

	w = get_next_wombat(); /* grab a wombat */
	process_wombat(w);     /* use it somewhere */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>I'm telling you this in case you find yourself trying to include a
header that includes another header that includes the same header, or if
your builds are taking forever because you're including too many
headers, or...more likely you'll see an error along the lines of "cannot
reference incomplete type".  This error means you've tried to do too
much with the incomplete type (like you tried to dereference it or use a
field in it), and you need to <statement>#include</statement> the right
header file with the full complete declaration of the
<type>struct</type>.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="voidp">
<title><type>void</type> pointers</title>

<p>Welcome to <emp>THE VOID</emp>!  As Neo Anderson would say,
"...Whoa."  What is this <type>void</type> thing?</p>

<p>Stop!  Before you get confused, a <type>void</type> pointer isn't the
same thing as a <type>void</type> return value from a function or a
<type>void</type> argument list.  I know that can be confusing, but
there it is.  Just wait until we talk about all the ways you can use the
<type>static</type> keyword.</p>

<p>A <type>void</type> pointer is a <emp>pointer to any type</emp>.  It
is automatically cast to whatever type you assign into it, or copy from
it.  Why would you want to ever use such a thing?  I mean, if you're
going to dereference a pointer so that you can get to the original
value, doesn't the compiler need to know what type the pointer is so
that it can use it properly?</p>

<p>Yes.  Yes, it does.  Because of that, you cannot dereference a
<type>void</type> pointer.  It's against the law, and the C Police will
be at your door faster than you can say Jack Robinson.  Before you can
use it, you have to cast it to another pointer type.</p>

<p>How on Valhalla is this going to be of any use then?  Why would you
even want a pointer you didn't know the type of?</p>

<offsettext><p><b>The Specification:</b> Write a function that can append
pointers <emp>of any type</emp> to an array.  Also write a function that
can return a particular pointer for a certain index.</p></offsettext>

<p>So in this case, we're going to write a couple useful little
functions for storing off pointers, and returning them later.  The
function has be to <emp>type-agnostic</emp>, that is, it must be able to
store pointers of any type.  This is something of a fairly common
feature to libraries of code that manipulate data&emdash;lots of them
take <type>void</type> pointers so they can be used with any type of
pointer the programmer might fancy.</p>

<p>Normally, we'd write a linked list or something to hold these, but
that's outside the scope of this book.  So we'll just use an array,
instead, in this superficial example.  Hmmm.  Maybe I should write a
beginning data structures book...</p>

<p>Anyway, the specification calls for two functions, so let's pound
those puppies out right here:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

void *pointer_array[10]; /* we can hold up to 10 void-pointers */
int index=0;

void append_pointer(void *p)
{
	pointer_array[index++] = p;
}

void *get_pointer(int i)
{
	return pointer_array[i];
}</code>

<p>Since we need to store those pointers somewhere, I went ahead and
made a global array of them that can be accessed from within both
functions.  Also, I made a global index variable to remember where to
store the next appended pointer in the array.</p>

<p>So check the code out for <func>append_pointer()</func> there.  How
is all that crammed together into one line?  Well, we need to do two
things when we append: store the data at the current index, and move the
index to the next available spot.  We copy the data using the assignment
operator, and then notice that we use the <emp>post-increment</emp>
operator (<operator>++</operator>) to increment the index.  Remember
what <emp>post</emp>-increment means?  It means the increment is done
<emp>after</emp> the rest of the expression is evaluated, including that
assignment.</p>

<p>The other function, <func>get_pointer</func>, simply returns the
<type>void*</type> at the specified index, <var>i</var>.  What you want
to watch for here is the subtle difference between the return types of
the two functions.  One of them is declared <type>void</type>, which
means it doesn't return anything, and the other one is declared with a
return type of <type>void*</type>, which means it returns a
<type>void</type> pointer.  I know, I know, the duplicate usage is a
little troublesome, but you get used to it in a big hurry.  Or else!</p>

<p>Finally, we have that code all written&emdash;now how can we actually
use it?  Let's write a <func>main()</func> function that will use these
functions:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	char *s = "some data!";  /* s points to a constant string (char*) */
	int a = 10;
	int *b;

	char *s2;  /* when we call get_pointer(), we'll store them back here */
	int *b2;

	b = &amp;a; /* b is a pointer to a */

	/* now let's store them both, even though they're different types */
	append_pointer(s);
	append_pointer(b);

	/* they're stored!  let's get them back! */
	s2 = get_pointer(0); /* this was at index 0 */
	b2 = get_pointer(1); /* this was at index 1 */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>See how the pointer types are interchangable through the
<type>void*</type>?  C will let you convert the <type>void*</type> into
any other pointer with impunity, and it really is up to you to make sure
you're getting them back to the type they were originally.  Yes, you can
make mistakes here that crash the program, you'd better believe it.
Like they say, "C gives you enough rope to hang yourself."</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="nullp">
<title><type>NULL</type> pointers</title>

<p>I think I have just enough time before the plane lands to talk about
<type>NULL</type> when it comes to pointers.</p>

<p><type>NULL</type> simply means a pointer to nothing.  Sometimes it's
useful to know if the pointer is valid, or if it needs to be
initialized, or whatever.  <type>NULL</type> can be used as a sentinel
value for a variety of different things.  Rememeber: it means "this
pointer points to nothing"!  Example:</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	int *p = NULL;

	if (p == NULL) {
		printf("p is uninitialized!\n");
	} else {
		printf("p points to %d\n", *p);
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Note that pointers aren't preinitialized to <type>NULL</type> when
you declare them&emdash;you have to explicitly do it.  (No non-static
local variables are preinitialized, pointers included.)</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="static2">
<title>More Static</title>

<p>Modern technology has landed me safely here at LAX, and I'm free to
continue writing while I wait for my plane to Ireland.  Tell me you're
not jealous at least on some level, and I won't believe you.</p>

<p>But enough about me; let's talk about programming.  (How's that for a
geek pick-up line?  If you use it, do me a favor and don't credit
me.)</p>

<p>You've already seen how you can use the <type>static</type> keyword
to make a local variable persist between calls to its function.  But
there are other exciting completely unrelated uses for
<type>static</type> that probably deserve to have their own keyword, but
don't get one.  You just have to get used to the fact that
<type>static</type> (and a number of other things in C) have different
meanings depending on context.</p>

<p>So what about if you declare something as <type>static</type> in the
global scope, instead of local to a function?  After all, global
variables already persist for the life of the program, so
<type>static</type> can't mean the same thing here.  Instead, at the
global scope, <type>static</type> means that the variable or function
declared <type>static</type> <emp>is only visible in this particular
source file</emp>, and cannot be referenced from other source files.
Again, this definition of <type>static</type> only pertains to the
global scope.  <type>static</type> still means the same old thing in the
local scope of the function.</p>

<p>You'll find that your bigger projects little bite-sized pieces
themselves fit into larger bite-sized pieces (just like that picture of
the little fish getting eaten by the larger fish being eaten by the
fish that's larger, still.)  When you have enough related smaller
bite-sized pieces, it often makes sense to put them in their own source
file.</p>

<p>I'm going to rip the example from the section on <link
dest="voidp"><type>void</type> pointers</link> wherein we have a couple
functions that can be used to store any types of pointers.</p>

<p>One of the many issues with that example program (there are all kinds
of shortcomings and bugs in it)  is that we've declared a global
variable called <var>index</var>.  Now, "index" is a pretty common word,
and it's entirely likely that somewhere else in the project, someone
will make up their own variable and name it the same thing as yours.
This could cause all kinds of problems, not the least of which is they
can modify your value of <var>index</var>, something that is very
important to you.</p>

<p>One solution is to put all your stuff in one source file, and then
declare <var>index</var> to be <type>static</type> global.  That way, no
one from outside your source file is allowed to use it.  You are King!
<type>static</type> is a way of keeping the implementation details of
your portion of the code out of the hands of others.  Believe me, if you
let other people meddle in your code, they will do so with playful
abandon!  Big Hammer Smash!</p>

<p>So here is a quick rewrite of the code to be stuck it its own
file:</p>

<code>/** file parray.c **/

static void *pointer_array[10]; /* now no one can see it except this file! */
static int index=0; /* same for this one! */

/* but these functions are NOT static, */
/* so they can be used from other files: */

void append_pointer(void *p)
{
	pointer_array[index++] = p;
}

void *get_pointer(int i)
{
	return pointer_array[i];
}

/** end of file parray.c **/</code>

<p>What would be proper at this point would be to make a file called
<file>parray.h</file> that has the function prototypes for the two
functions in it.  Then the file that has <func>main()</func> in it can
<statement>#include</statement> <file>parray.h</file> and use the
functions when it is all linked together.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="multifile">
<title>Typical Multifile Projects</title>

<p>Like I'm so fond of saying, projects generally grow too big for a
single file, very similarly to how The Blob grew to be enormous and had
to be defeated by Steve McQueen.  Unfortunately, McQueen has already
made his great escape to Heaven, and isn't here to help you with your
code.  Sorry.</p>

<p>So when you split projects up, you should try to do it in bite-sized
modules that make sense to have in individual files.  For instance, all
the code responsible for calculating Fast Fourier Transforms (a
mathematical construct, for those not in the know), would be a good
candidate for its own source file.  Or maybe all the code that controls
a particular AI bot for a game could be in its own file.  It's more of a
guideline than a rule, but if something's not a least in some way
related to what you have in a particular source file already, maybe it
should go elsewhere.  A perfect illustrative question for this scenario
might be, "What is the 3D rendering code doing in the middle of the
sound driver code?"</p>

<p>When you do move code to its own source file, there is almost always
a header file that you should write to go along with it.  The code in
the new source file (which will be a bunch of functions) will need to
have prototypes and other things made visible to the other files so they
can be used.  The way the other source files use other files is to
<statement>#include</statement> their header files.</p>

<p>So for example, let's make a small set of functions and stick them in
a file called <file>simplemath.c</file>:</p>

<code>/** file simplemath.c **/

int plusone(int a)
{
	return a+1;
}

int minusone(int a)
{
	return a-1;
}

/** end of file simplemath.c **/</code>

<p>A couple simple functions, there.  Nothing too complex, yes?  But by
themselves, they're not much use, and for other people to use them we
need to distribute their prototypes in a header file.  Get ready to
absorbe this...you should recognize the prototypes in there, but I've
added some new stuff:</p>

<code>/** file simplemath.h **/

#ifndef _SIMPLEMATH_H_
#define _SIMPLEMATH_H_

/* here are the prototypes: */

int plusone(int a);
int minusone(int a);

#endif

/** end of file simplemath.h **/</code>

<p>Icky.  What is all that <statement>#ifndef</statement> stuff?  And
the <statement>#define</statement> and the
<statement>#endif</statement>?  They are <emp>boilerplate code</emp>
(that is, code that is more often than not stuck in a file) that
prevents the header file from being included multiple times.</p>

<p>The short version of the logic is this: if the symbol
<var>_SIMPLEMATH_H_</var> isn't defined then define it, and then do all
the normal header stuff.  Else if the symbol <var>_SIMPLEMATH_H_</var>
<emp>is</emp> already defined, do nothing.  In this way, the bulk of the
header file is included only once for the build, no matter how many
other files try to include it.  This is a good idea, since at best it's
a redundant waste of time to re-include it, and at worst, it can cause
compile-time errors.</p>

<p>Well, we have the header and the source files, and now it's time to
write a file with <func>main()</func> in it so that we can actually use
these things:</p>

<code>/** file main.c **/

#include "simplemath.h"

int main(void)
{
	int a = 10, b;

	b = plusone(a);  /* make that processor work! */

	return 0;
}

/** end of file main.c **/</code>

<p>Check it out!  We used double-quotes in the
<statement>#include</statement> instead of angle brackets!  What this
tells the preprocessor to do is, "include this file from the current
directory instead of the standard system directory."  I'm assuming that
you're putting all these files in the same place for the purposes of
this exercise.</p>

<p>Recall that including a file is exactly like bringing it into your
source at that point, so, as such, we bring the prototypes into the
source right there, and then the functions are free to be used in
<func>main()</func>.  Huzzah!</p>

<p>One last question!  How do we actually build this whole thing?  From
the command line:</p>

<screen>$ cc -o main main.c simplemath.c</screen>

<p>You can lump all the sources on the command line, and it'll build
them together, nice and easy.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="cpp">
<title>The Almighty C Preprocessor</title>

<p>Remember back about a million years ago when you first started
reading this guide and I mentioned something about spinach?  That's
right&emdash;you remember how spinach relates to the whole computing
process?</p>

<p>Of course you don't remember.  I just made it up just now; I've never
mentioned spinach in this guide.  I mean, c'mon.  What does spinach have
to do with anything?  Sheesh!</p>

<p>Let me steer you to a less leafy topic: the C preprocessor.  As the
name suggests, this little program will process source code before the C
compiler sees it.  This gives you a little bit more control over what
gets compiled and how it gets compiled.</p>

<p>You've already seen one of the most common preprocessor directives:
<statement>#include</statement>.  Other sections of the guide have
touched upon various other ones, but we'll lay them all out here for
fun.</p>

<sect3 id="cppinclude">
<title><statement>#include</statement></title>

<p>The well-known <statement>#include</statement> directive pulls in
source from another file.  This other file should be a header file in
virtually every single case.</p>

<p>On each system, there are a number of standard include files that you
can use for various tasks.  Most popularly, you've seen
<file>stdio.h</file> used.  How did the system know where to find it?
Well, each compiler has a set of directories it looks in for header
files when you specify the file name in angle brackets.  (On Unix
systems, it commonly searches the <file>/usr/include</file>
directory.)</p>

<p>If you want to include a file from the same directory as the source,
use double quotes around the name of the file.  Some examples:</p>

<code>/* include from the system include directory: */

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;sys/types.h&gt;

/* include from the local directory: */

#include "mutants.h"
#include "fishies/halibut.h"</code>

<p>As you can see from the example, you can also specify a
<emp>relative path</emp> into subdirectories out of the main directory.
(Under Unix, again, there is a file called <file>types.h</file> in the
directory <file>/usr/include/sys</file>.)</p>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="cppdefine">
<title><statement>#define</statement></title>

<p>The <statement>#define</statement> is one of the more powerful C
preprocessor directives.  With it you can declare constants to be
substituted into the source code before the compiler even sees them.
Let's say you have a lot of constants scattered all over your program
and each number is <emp>hard-coded</emp> (that is, the number is written
explicitly in the code, like "2").</p>

<p>Now, you thought it was a constant when you wrote it because the
people you got the specification swore to you up and down on pain of
torture that the number would be "2", and it would never change in 100
million years so strike them blind right now.</p>

<p>Hey&emdash;sounds good.  You even have someone to blame if it did
change, and it probably won't anyway since they seem so sure.</p>

<p><emp>Don't be a fool.</emp></p>

<p>The spec will change, and it will do so right after you have put the
number "2" in approximately three hundred thousand places throughout
your source, they're going to say, "You know what?  Two just isn't going
to cut it&emdash;we need three.  Is that a hard change to make?"</p>

<p>Blame or not, you're going to be the one that has to change it.  A
good programmer will realize that hard-coding numbers like this isn't a
good idea, and one way to get around it is to use a
<statement>#define</statement> directive.  Check out this example:</p>

<code>#define PI 3.14159265358979  /* more pi than you can handle */

int main(void)
{
	float r =10.0;

	printf("pi: %f\n", PI);
	printf("pi/2: %f\n", PI/2);
	printf("area: %f\n", PI*r*r);
	printf("circumference: %f\n", 2*PI*r);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>(Typically <statement>#define</statement>s are all capitals, by
convention.)  So, hey, we just printed that thing out as if it was a
float.  Well, it <emp>is</emp> a float.  Remember&emdash;the C
preprocessor substitutes the value of <var>PI</var> <emp>before the
compiler even sees it</emp>.  It is just as if you had typed it there
yourself.</p>

<p>Now let's say you've used <var>PI</var> all over the place and now
you're just about ready to ship, and the designers come to you and say,
"So, this whole pi thing, um, we're thinking it needs to be four instead
of three-point-one-whatever.  Is that a hard change?"</p>

<p>No problem in this case, no matter how deranged the change request.
All you have to do is change the one <statement>#define</statement> at
the top, and it's therefore automatically changed all over the code
when the C preprocessor runs through it:</p>

<code>#define PI 4.0  /* whatever you say, boss */</code>

<p>Pretty cool, huh.  Well, it's perhaps not as good as to be "cool",
but you have not yet witnessed the destructive power of this fully
operational preprocessor directive!  You can actually use
<statement>#define</statement> to write little <emp>macros</emp> that
are like miniature functions that the preprocessor evaluates, again,
before the C compiler sees the code.  To make a macro like this, you
give an argument list (without types, because the preprocessor knows
nothing about types, and then you list how that is to be used.  For
instance, if we want a macro that evaluates to a number you pass it
times 3490, we could do the following:</p>

<code>#define TIMES3490(x) ((x)*3490)    /* no semicolon, notice! */

void evaluate_fruit(void)
{
	printf("40 * 3490 = %d\n", TIMES3490(40));
}</code>

<p>In that example, the preprocessor will take the macro and
<emp>expand</emp> it so that it looks like this to the compiler:</p>

<code>void evaluate_fruit(void)
{
	printf("40 * 3490 = %d\n", ((40)*3490));
}</code>

<p>(Actually the preprocessor can do basic math, so it'll probably
reduce it directly to "139600".  But this is my example and I'll do as I
please!)</p>

<p>Now here's a question for you: are you taking it on blind faith that
you need all those parenthesis in the macro, like you're some kind of
LISP superhero, or are you wondering, "Why am I wasting precious moments
of my life to enter all these parens?"</p>

<p>Well, you <emp>should</emp> be wondering!  It turns out there are
cases where you can really generate some <emp>evil</emp> code with a
macro without realizing it.  Take a look at this example which builds
without a problem:</p>

<code>#define TIMES3490(x) x*3490

void walrus_discovery_unit(void)
{
	int tuskcount = 7;

	printf("(tuskcount+2) * 3490 = %d\n", TIMES3490(tuskcount + 2));
}</code>

<p>What's wrong here?  We're calculating <tt>tuskcount+2</tt>, and then
passing that through the <func>TIMES3490()</func> macro.  But look at
what it expands to:</p>

<code>printf("(tuskcount+2) * 3490 = %d\n", tuskcount+2*3490);</code>

<p>Instead of calculating <tt>(tuskcount+2)*3490</tt>, we're calculating
<tt>tuskcount+(2*3490)</tt>, because multiplication comes before
addition in the order of operations!  See, adding all those extra parens
to the macro prevents this sort of thing from happening.  So programmers
with good practices will automatically put a set of parens around each
usage of the parameter variable in the macro, as well as a set of
parens around the outside of the macro itself.</p>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="macif">
<title><statement>#if</statement> and
<statement>#ifdef</statement></title>

<p>There are some <emp>conditionals</emp> that the C preprocessor can
use to discard blocks of code so that the compiler never sees them.  The
<statement>#if</statement> directive operates like the C
<statement>if</statement>, and you can pass it an expression to be
evaluated.  It is most common used to block off huge chunks of code like
a comment, when you don't want it to get built:</p>

<code>void set_hamster_speed(int warpfactor)
{
#if 0
	uh this code isn't written yet.  someone should really write it.
#endif
}</code>

<p>You can't nest comments in C, but you can nest
<statement>#if</statement> directives all you want, so it can be very
helpful for that.</p>

<p>The other if-statement, <statement>#ifdef</statement> is true if the
subsequent macro is already defined.  There's a negative version of this
directive called <statement>#ifndef</statement> ("if not defined").
<statement>#ifndef</statement> is very commonly used with header files
to keep them from being included multiple times:</p>

<code>/** file aardvark.h **/

#ifndef _AARDVARK_H_
#define _AARDVARK_H_

int get_nose_length(void);
void set_nose_length(int len);

#endif

/** end of file aardvark.h **/</code>

<p>The first time this file is included, <var>_AARDVARK_H_</var> is not
yet defined, so it goes to the next line, and defines it, and then does
some function prototypes, and you'll see there at the end, the whole
<statement>#if</statement>-type directive is culminated with an
<statement>#endif</statement> statement.  Now if the file is included
again (which can happen when you have a lot of header files are
including other header files <emp>ad
infininininini&emdash;</emp>cough!), the macro <var>_AARDVARK_H_</var>
will already be defined, and so the <statement>#ifndef</statement> will
fail, and the file up to the <statement>#endif</statement> will be
discarded by the preprocessor.</p>

<p>Another extremely useful thing to do here is to have certain code
compile for a certain platform, and have other code compile for a
different platform.  Lots of people like to build software with a macro
defined for the type of platform they're on, such as <var>LINUX</var> or
<var>WIN32</var>.  And you can use this to great effect so that your
code will compile and work on different types of systems:</p>

<code>void run_command_shell(void)
{
#ifdef WIN32
	system("COMMAND.EXE");
#elifdef LINUX
	system("/bin/bash");
#else
#error We don't have no steenkin shells!
#endif
}</code>

<p>A couple new things there, most notable
<statement>#elifdef</statement>.  This is the contraction of "else
ifdef", which must be used in that case.  If you're using
<statement>#if</statement>, then you'd use the corresponding
<statement>#elif</statement>.</p>

<p>Also I threw in an <statement>#error</statement> directive, there.
This will cause the preprocessor to bomb out right at that point with
the given message.</p>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="pt2pt">
<title>Pointers to pointers</title>

<p>You've already seen how you can have a pointer to a variable...and
you've already seen how a pointer <emp>is</emp> a variable, so is it
possible to have a <emp>pointer to a pointer</emp>?</p>

<p>No, it's not.</p>

<p>I'm kidding&emdash;of course it's possible.  Would I have this
section of the guide if it wasn't?</p>

<p>There are a few good reasons why we'd want to have a pointer to a
pointer, and we'll give you the simple one first: you want to pass a
pointer as a parameter to a function, have the function modify it, and
have the results reflected back to the caller.</p>

<p>Note that this is exactly the reason why we use pointers in function
calls in the first place: we want the function to be able to modify the
thing the pointer points to.  In this case, though, the thing we want it
to modify is another pointer.  For example:</p>

<code>void get_string(int a, char **s)
{
	switch(a) {
		case 0:
			*s = "everybody";
			break;

		case 1:
			*s = "was";
			break;

		case 2:
			*s = "kung-foo fighting";
			break;

		default:
			*s = "errrrrrnt!";
	}
}

int main(void)
{
	char *s;

	get_string(2, &amp;s);

	printf("s is \"%s\"\n", s);  /* 's is "kung-foo fighting"' */

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>What we have, above, is some code that will deliver a string (pointer
to a <type>char</type>) back to the caller via pointer to a pointer.
Notice that we pass the <emp>address of</emp> the pointer <var>s</var>
in <func>main()</func>.  This gives the function
<func>get_string()</func> a pointer to <var>s</var>, and so it can
dereference that pointer to change what it is pointing at, namely
<var>s</var> itself.</p>

<p>There's really nothing mysterious here.  You have a pointer to a
thing, so you can dereference the pointer to change the thing.  It's
just like before, except for that fact that we're operating on a pointer
now instead of just a plain base type.</p>

<p>What else can we do with pointers to pointers?  You can dynamically
make a construction similar to a two-dimensional array with them.  The
following example relies on your knowledge that the function call
<func>malloc()</func> returns a chunk of sequential bytes of memory that
you can use as you will.  In this case, we'll use them to create a
number of <type>char*</type>s.  And we'll have a pointer to that, as
well, which is therefore of type <type>char**</type>.</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	char **p;

	p = malloc(sizeof(char*) * 10);  // allocate 10 char*s

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Swell.  Now what can we do with those?  Well, they don't point to
anything yet, but we can call <func>malloc()</func> for each of them in
turn and then we'll have a big block of memory we can store strings
in.</p>

<code>int main(void)
{
	char **p;
	int i;

	p = malloc(sizeof(char*) * 10);  // allocate 10 char*s-worth of bytes

	for(i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
		*(p+i) = malloc(30); // 30 bytes for each pointer

		// alternatively we could have written, above:
		//   p[i] = malloc(30);
		// but we didn't.

		sprintf(*(p+i), "this is string #%d", i);
	}

	for(i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
		printf("%d: %s\n", i, p[i]); // p[i] same as *(p+i)
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>Ok, as you're probably thinking, this is where things get completely
wacko-jacko.  Let's look at that second <func>malloc()</func> line and
dissect it one piece at a time.</p>

<p>You know that <var>p</var> is a pointer to a pointer to a
<type>char</type>, or, put another way, it's a pointer to a
<type>char*</type>.  Keep that in mind.</p>

<p>And we know this <type>char*</type> is the first of a solid block of
10, because we just <func>malloc()</func>'d that many before the for
loop.  With that knowledge, we know that we can use some pointer
arithmetic to hop from one to the next.  We do this by adding the
value of <var>i</var> onto the <type>char**</type> so that when we
dereference it, we are pointing at the next <type>char*</type> in the
block.  In the first iteration of the loop <var>i</var> is zero, so
we're just referring to the first <type>char*</type>.</p>

<p>And what do we do with that <type>char*</type> once we have it?  We
point it at the return value of <func>malloc()</func> which will point
it at a fresh ready-to-use 30 bytes of memory.</p>

<p>And what do we use that memory for (sheesh, this could go on
forever!)--well, we use a variant of <func>printf()</func> called
<func>sprintf()</func> that writes the result into a string instead of
to the console.</p>

<p>And there you have it.  Finally, for fun, we print out the results
using array notation to access the strings instead of pointer
arithmetic.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="ptfunc">
<title>Pointers to Functions</title>

<p>You've completely mastered all that pointer stuff, right?  I mean,
you are the <emp>Pointer Master</emp>!  No, really, I insist!</p>

<p>So, with that in mind, we're going to take the whole pointer and
address idea to the next phase and learn a little bit about the machine
code that the compiler produces.  I know this seems like it has nothing
to do with this section, Pointers to Functions, but it's background that
will only make you stronger.  (Provided, that is, it doesn't kill you
first.  Admittedly, the chances of death from trying to understand this
section are slim, but you might want to read it in a padded room just as
a precautionary measure.)</p>

<p>Long ago I mentioned that the compiler takes your C source code and
produces <emp>machine code</emp> that the processor can execute.  These
machine code instructions are small (taking between one and four bytes
or memory, typically, with optionally up to, say, 32 bytes of arguments
per instruction&emdash;these numbers vary depending on the processor in
question).  This isn't so important as the fact that these instructions
have to be stored somewhere.  Guess where.</p>

<p>You thought that was a rhetorical command, but no, I really do want
you to guess where, generally, the instructions are stored.</p>

<p>You have your guess?  Good.  Is it animal, vegetable, or mineral?
Can you fly in it?  Is it a rocketship?  Yay!</p>

<p>But, cerebral digression aside, yes, you are correct, the
instructions are stored in memory, just like variables are stored in
memory.  Instructions themselves have addresses, and a special variable
in the CPU (generally known as a "register" in CPU-lingo) points to the
address of the currently executing instruction.</p>

<p>Whatwhat?  I said "points to" and "address-of"!  Suddenly we have a
connection back to pointers and all that...familiar ground again.  But
what did I just say?  I said: instructions are held in addresses, and,
therefore, you have have a pointer to a block of instructions.  A block
of instructions in C is held in a function, and, therefore, you can have
a pointer to a function.  <emp>Voila</emp>!</p>

<p>Ok, so if you have a function, how do you get the address of the
function?  Yes, you can use the <operator>&amp;</operator>, but most people
don't.  It's similar to the situation with arrays, where the name of the
array without square brackets is a pointer to the first element in the
array; the name of the function without parens is a pointer to the first
instruction in the function.  That's the easy part.</p>

<p>The hard part is declaring a variable to be of type "pointer to
function".  It's hard because the syntax is funky:</p>

<code>// declare p as a pointer to a function that takes two int
// parameters, and returns a float:

float (*p)(int, int);</code>

<p>Again, note that this is a <emp>declaration of a pointer</emp> to a
function.  It doesn't yet point to anything in particular.  Also notice
that you don't have to put dummy parameter names in the declaration of
the pointer variable.  All right, let's make a function, point to it,
and call it:</p>

<code>int deliver_fruit(char *address, float speed)
{
	printf("Delivering fruit to %s at speed %.2f\n", address, speed);

	return 3490;
}

int main(void)
{
	int (*p)(char*,float);  // declare a function pointer variable

	p = deliver_fruit; // p now points to the deliver_fruit() function

	deliver_fruit("My house", 5280.0); // a normal call

	p("My house", 5280.0); // the same call, but using the pointer

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>What the heck good is this?  The usual reasons are these:</p>

<list>

<li>You want to change what function is called at runtime.</li>

<li>You have a big array of data including pointers to functions.</li>

<li>You don't know the function at compile-time; maybe it's in a shared
library that you load a runtime and query to find a function, and that
query returns a pointer to the function.  I know this is a bit beyond
the scope of the section, but bear with me.</li>

</list>

<p>For example, long ago a friend of mine and I wrote a program that
would simulate a bunch of creatures running around a grid.  The
creatures each had a <type>struct</type> associated with them that held
their position, health, and other information.  The <type>struct</type>
also held a pointer to a function that was their behavior, like
this:</p>

<code>struct creature {
	int xpos;
	int ypos;
	float health;
	int (*behavior)(struct useful_data*);
};</code>

<p>So for each round of the simulation, we'd walk through the list of
creatures and call their behavior function (passing a pointer to a bunch
of useful data so the function could see other creatures, know about
itself, etc.)  In this way, it was easy to code bugs up as having
different behaviors.</p>

<p>Indeed, I wrote a creature called a "brainwasher" that would, when it
got close to another creature, change that creature's behavior pointer to
point to the brainwasher's behavior code!  Of course, it didn't take
long before they were all brainwashers, and then starved and
cannibalized themselves to death.  Let that be a lesson to you.</p>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="varargs">
<title>Variable Argument Lists</title>

<p>Ever wonder, in your spare time, while you lay awake at night
thinking about the C Programming Language, how functions like
<func>printf()</func> and <func>scanf()</func> seem to take an arbitrary
number of arguments and other functions take a specific number?  How do
you even write a function prototype for a function that takes a variable
number of arguments?</p>

<p>(Don't get confused over terminology here&emdash;we're not talking
about variables.  In this case, "variable" retains its usual boring old
meaning of "an arbitrary number of".)</p>

<p>Well, there are some little tricks that have been set up for you in
this case.  Remember how all the arguments are pushed onto the stack
when passed to a function?  Well, some macros have been set up to help
you walk along the stack and pull arguments off one at a time.  In this
way, you don't need to know at compile-time what the argument list will
look like&emdash;you just need to know how to parse it.</p>

<p>For instance, let's write a function that averages an arbitrary
number of positive numbers.  We can pull numbers off the stack one at a
time and average them all, but we need to know when to stop pulling
stuff off the stack.  One way to do this is to have a sentinel value
that you watch for&emdash;when you hit it, you stop.  Another way is to
put some kind of information in the mandatory first argument.  Let's do
option B and put the count of the number of arguments to be averaged in
as the first argument to the function.</p>

<p>Here's the prototype for the function&emdash;this is how we declare a
variable argument list.  The first argument (at least) must be
specified, but that's all:</p>

<code>float average(int count, ...);</code>

<p>It's the magical "<tt>...</tt>" that does it, see?  This lets the
compiler know that there can be more arguments after the first one, but
doesn'r require you to say what they are.  So <emp>this</emp> is how we
are able to pass many or few (but at least one, the first argument)
arguments to the function.</p>

<p>But if we don't have names for the variables specified in the
function header, how do we use them in the function?  Well, aren't we
the demanding ones, actually wanting to <emp>use</emp> our function!
Ok, I'll tell you!</p>

<p>There is a special type declared in the header <file>stdarg.h</file>
called <type>va_list</type>.  It holds data about the stack and about
what arguments have been parsed off so far.  But first you have to tell
it where the stack for this function starts, and fortunately we have a
variable right there at the beginning of our <func>average()</func>
function: <var>a</var>.</p>

<p>We operate on our <type>va_list</type> using a number of preprocessor
macros (which are like mini-functions if you haven't yet read the
section on macros.)  First of all, we use <func>va_start()</func> to tell
our <type>va_list</type> where the stack starts.  Then we use
<func>va_arg()</func> repeatedly to pull arguments off the stack.  And
finally we use <func>va_end()</func> to tell our <type>va_list</type> that
we're done with it.  (The language specification says we <emp>must</emp>
call <func>va_end()</func>, and we must call it in the same function from
which we called <func>va_start()</func>.  This allows the compiler to do
any cleanup that is necessary, and keeps the Vararg Police from knocking
on your door.</p>

<p>So an example!  Let's write that <func>average()</func> function.
Remember: <func>va_start()</func>, <func>va_arg()</func>,
<func>va_arg()</func>, <func>va_arg()</func>, etc., and then
<func>va_end()</func>!</p>

<code>float average(int count, ...)
{
	float ave = 0;
	int i;
	va_list args; // here's our va_list!

	va_start(args, count); // tell it the stack starts with "count"

	// inside the while(), pull int args off the stack:

	for(i = 0; i &lt; count; i++) {
		int val = va_arg(args, int); // get next int argument
		ave += (float)val;  // cast the value to a float and add to total
	}

	va_end(args);  // clean this up

	return ave / count; // calc and return the average
}</code>

<p>So there you have it.  As you see, the <func>va_arg()</func> macro
pulls the next argument off the stack of the given type.  So you have to
know in advance what type the thing is.  We know for our
<func>average()</func> function, all the types are <type>int</type>s, so
that's ok.  But what if they're different types mixed all together?  How
do you tell what type is coming next?</p>

<p>Well, if you'll notice, this is exactly what our old friend
<func>printf()</func> does!  It knows what type to call
<func>va_arg()</func> with, since it says so right in the format
string.</p>

<sect3 id="varargsvp">
<title><func>vprintf()</func> and its ilk</title>

<p>There are a number of functions that helpfully accept a
<type>va_list</type> as an argument that you can pass.  This enables you
to wrap these functions up easily in your own functions that take a
variable number of arguments themselves.  For instance:</p>

<offsettext><p><b>Assignment:</b> Implement a version of
<func>printf()</func> called <func>timestamp_printf()</func> that works
<emp>exactly</emp> like <func>printf()</func> except it prints the time
followed by a newline followed by the data output specified by the
<func>printf()</func>-style format string.</p></offsettext>

<p>Holy cow!  At first glance, it looks like you're going to have to
implement a clone of <func>printf()</func> just to get a timestamp out
in front of it!  And <func>printf()</func> is, as we say in the
industry, "nontrivial"!  See you next year!</p>

<p>Wait, though&emdash;wait, wait...there <emp>must</emp> be a way to do
it easily, or this author is complete insane to give you this
assignment, and that couldn't be.  Fruit!  Where is my cheese!?
Blalalauugh!!</p>

<p>Ahem. I'm all right, really, Your Honor.  I'm looking into my crystal
ball and I'm seeing...a type <type>va_list</type> in your future.  In
fact, if we took our variable argument list, processed it with
<func>va_start()</func> and got our <type>va_list</type> back, we could,
if such a thing existed, just pass it to an already-written version of
<func>printf()</func> that accepted just that thing.</p>

<p>Welcome to the world of <func>vprintf()</func>!  It does exactly
that, by Jove!  Here's a lovely prototype:</p>

<code>int vprintf(const char *format, va_list args);</code>

<p>All righty, so what building blocks do we need for this assignment?
The spec says we need to do something just like <func>printf()</func>,
so our function, like <func>printf()</func> is going to accept a format
string first, followed by a variable number of arguments, something like
this:</p>

<code>int timestamp_printf(char *format, ...);</code>

<p>But before it prints its stuff, it needs to output a timestamp
followed by a newline.  The exact format of the timestamp wasn't
specified in the assignment, so I'm going to assume something in the
form of "weekday month day hh:mm:ss year".  By amazing coincidence, a
function exists called <func>ctime()</func> that returns a string in
exactly that format, given the current system time.</p>

<p>So the plan is to print a timestamp, then take our variable argument
list, run it through <func>va_start</func> to get a <type>va_list</type>
out of it, and pass that <type>va_list</type> into
<func>vprintf()</func> and let it work its already-written
<func>printf()</func> magic.  And...GO!</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdarg.h&gt;
#include &lt;time.h&gt;  // for time() and ctime();

int timestamp_printf(char *format, ...)
{
	va_list args;
	time_t system_time;
	char *timestr;
	int return_value;

	system_time = time(NULL); // system time in seconds since epoch
	timestr = ctime(&amp;system_time); // ready-to-print timestamp

	// print the timestamp:
	printf("%s", timestr); // timestr has a newline on the end already

	// get our va_list:
	va_start(args, format);

	// call vprintf() with our arg list:
	return_value = vprintf(format, args);

	// done with list, so we have to call va_end():
	va_end(args);

	// since we want to be *exactly* like printf(), we have saved its
	// return value, and we'll pass it on right here:
	return return_value;
}

int main(void)
{
	// example call:
	timestamp_printf("Brought to you by the number %d\n", 3490);

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>And there you have it!  Your own little <func>printf()</func>-like
functionality!</p>

<p>Now, not every function has a "v" in front of the name for processing
variable argument lists, but most notably all the variants of
<func>printf()</func> and <func>scanf()</func> do, so feel free to use
them as you see fit!</p>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<p>TODO order of operations, 
arrays of pointers to functions</p>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="stdio">
<title>Standard I/O Library</title>

<p>The most basic of all libraries in the whole of the standard C
library is the standard I/O library.  It's used for reading from and
writing to files.  I can see you're very excited about this.</p>

<p>So I'll continue.  It's also used for reading and writing to the
console, as we've already often seen with the <func>printf()</func>
function.</p>

<p>(A little secret here&emdash;many many things in various operating
systems are secretly files deep down, and the console is no exception.
"<emp>Everything in Unix is a file!</emp>" <smiley/>)</p>

<p>You'll probably want some prototypes of the functions you can use,
right?  To get your grubby little mittens on those, you'll want to
include <file>stdio.h</file>.</p>

<p>Anyway, so we can do all kinds of cool stuff in terms of file I/O.
LIE DETECTED.  Ok, ok.  We can do all kinds of stuff in terms of file
I/O.  Basically, the strategy is this:</p>

<numlist>
<li>Use <func>fopen()</func> to get a pointer to a file structure of
type <type>FILE*</type>.  This pointer is what you'll be passing to many
of the other file I/O calls.</li>

<li>Use some of the other file calls, like <func>fscanf()</func>,
<func>fgets()</func>, <func>fprintf()</func>, or etc. using the
<type>FILE*</type> returned from <func>fopen()</func>.</li>

<li>When done, call <func>fclose()</func> with the <type>FILE*</type>.
This let's the operating system know that you're truly done with the
file, no take-backs.</li>
</numlist>

<p>What's in the <type>FILE*</type>?  Well, as you might guess, it
points to a <type>struct</type> that contains all kinds of information
about the current read and write position in the file, how the file was
opened, and other stuff like that.  But, honestly, who cares.  No one,
that's who.  The <type>FILE</type> structure is <emp>opaque</emp> to you
as a programmer; that is, you don't need to know what's in it, and you
don't even <emp>want</emp> to know what's in it.  You just pass it to
the other standard I/O functions and they know what to do.</p>

<p>This is actually pretty important: try to not muck around in the
<type>FILE</type> structure.  It's not even the same from system to
system, and you'll end up writing some really non-portable code.</p>

<p>One more thing to mention about the standard I/O library: a lot of
the functions that operate on files use an "f" prefix on the function
name.  The same function that is operating on the console will leave the
"f" off.  For instance, if you want to print to the console, you use
<func>printf()</func>, but if you want to print to a file, use
<func>fprintf()</func>, see?</p>

<p>Wait a moment!  If writing to the console is, deep down, just like
writing to a file, since everything in Unix is a file, why are there two
functions?  Answer: it's more convenient.  But, more importantly, is
there a <type>FILE*</type> associated with the console that you can use?
Answer: YES!</p>

<p>There are, in fact, <emp>three</emp> (count 'em!) special
<type>FILE*</type>s you have at your disposal merely for just including
<file>stdio.h</file>.  There is one for input, and two for output.</p>

<p>That hardly seems fair&emdash;why does output get two files, and
input only get one?</p>

<p>That's jumping the gun a bit&emdash;let's just look at them:</p>

<deflist>

<def><deftitle><var>stdin</var></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Input from the console.</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><var>stdout</var></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Output to the console.</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><var>stderr</var></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Output to the console on the error file stream.</p></deftext></def>

</deflist>

<p>So standard input (<var>stdin</var>) is by default just what you type
at the keyboard.  You can use that in <func>fscanf()</func> if you want,
just like this:</p>

<code>/* this line: */
scanf("%d", &amp;x);

/* is just like this line: */
fscanf(stdin, "%d", &amp;x);</code>

<p>And <var>stdout</var> works the same way:</p>

<code>printf("Hello, world!\n");
fprintf(stdout, "Hello, world!\n"); /* same as previous line! */</code>

<p>So what is this <var>stderr</var> thing?  What happens when you
output to that?  Well, generally it goes to the console just like
<var>stdout</var>, but people use it for error messages, specifically.
Why?  On many systems you can redirect the output from the program into
a file from the command line...and sometimes you're interested in
getting just the error output.  So if the program is good and writes all
its errors to <var>stderr</var>, a user can redirect just
<var>stderr</var> into a file, and just see that.  It's just a nice
thing you, as a programmer, can do.</p>

<!-- ================================================================
== fopen
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fopen">
<title><func>fopen()</func></title>
<short><p>Opens a file for reading or writing</p></short>

<prototypes><code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

FILE *fopen(const char *path, const char *mode);</code></prototypes>

<description>
<p>The <func>fopen()</func> opens a file for reading or writing.</p>

<p>Parameter <var>path</var> can be a relative or fully-qualified
path and file name to the file in question.</p>

<p>Paramter <var>mode</var> tells <func>fopen()</func> how to open the
file (reading, writing, or both), and whether or not it's a binary
file.  Possible modes are:</p>

<deflist>

<def><deftitle><tt>r</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Open the file for reading (read-only).</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><tt>w</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Open the file for writing (write-only).  The file is created
if it doesn't exist.</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><tt>r+</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Open the file for reading and writing.  The file has to
already exist.</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><tt>w+</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Open the file for writing and reading.  The file is created
if it doesn't already exist.</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><tt>a</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Open the file for append.  This is just like opening a file
for writing, but it positions the file pointer at the end of the file,
so the next write appends to the end.  The file is created if it doesn't
exist.</p></deftext></def>

<def><deftitle><tt>a+</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Open the file for reading and appending.  The file is
created if it doesn't exist.</p></deftext></def>

</deflist>

<p>Any of the modes can have the letter "<tt>b</tt>" appended to the
end, as is "<tt>wb</tt>" ("write binary"), to signify that the file in question is a
<emp>binary</emp> file.  ("Binary" in this case generally means that the
file contains non-alphanumeric characters that look like garbage to
human eyes.)  Many systems (like Unix) don't differentiate between
binary and non-binary files, so the "<tt>b</tt>" is extraneous.  But if
your data is binary, it doesn't hurt to throw the "<tt>b</tt>" in there,
and it might help someone who is trying to port your code to another
system.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p><func>fopen()</func> returns a <type>FILE*</type> that can be used in
subsequent file-related calls.</p>

<p>If something goes wrong (e.g. you tried to open a file for read that
didn't exist), <func>fopen()</func> will return <type>NULL</type>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>int main(void)
{
	FILE *fp;

	if ((fp = fopen("datafile.dat", "r")) == NULL) {
		printf("Couldn't open datafile.dat for reading\n");
		exit(1);
	}

	// fp is now initialized and can be read from

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fclose"><func>fclose()</func></link><br/>
<link dest="freopen"><func>freopen()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== freopen
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="freopen">
<title><func>freopen()</func></title>
<short><p>Reopen an existing <type>FILE*</type>, associating it with a
new path</p></short>

<prototypes><code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

FILE *freopen(const char *filename, const char *mode, FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Let's say you have an existing <type>FILE*</type> stream that's
already open, but you want it to suddenly use a different file than the
one it's using.  You can use <func>freopen()</func> to "re-open" the
stream with a new file.</p>

<p>Why on Earth would you ever want to do that?  Well, the most common
reason would be if you had a program that normally would read from
<var>stdin</var>, but instead you wanted it to read from a file.
Instead of changing all your <func>scanf()</func>s to
<func>fscanf()</func>s, you could simply reopen <var>stdin</var> on the
file you wanted to read from.</p>

<p>Another usage that is allowed on some systems is that you can pass
<type>NULL</type> for <var>filename</var>, and specify a new
<var>mode</var> for <var>stream</var>.  So you could change a file from
"<tt>r+</tt>" (read and write) to just "<tt>r</tt>" (read), for
instance.  It's implementation dependent which modes can be changed.</p>

<p>When you call <func>freopen()</func>, the old <var>stream</var> is
closed.  Otherwise, the function behaves just like the standard
<func>fopen()</func>.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p><func>freopen()</func> returns <var>stream</var> if all goes
well.</p>

<p>If something goes wrong (e.g. you tried to open a file for read that
didn't exist), <func>freopen()</func> will return <type>NULL</type>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	int i, i2;

	scanf("%d", &amp;i); // read i from stdin

	// now change stdin to refer to a file instead of the keyboard
	freopen("someints.txt", "r", stdin);

	scanf("%d", &amp;i2); // now this reads from the file "someints.txt"

	printf("Hello, world!\n"); // print to the screen

	// change stdout to go to a file instead of the terminal:
	freopen("output.txt", "w", stdout);

	printf("This goes to the file \"output.txt\"\n");

	// this is allowed on some systems--you can change the mode of a file:
	freopen(NULL, "wb", stdout); // change to "wb" instead of "w"

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fclose"><func>fclose()</func></link><br/>
<link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== fclose
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fclose">
<title><func>fclose()</func></title>
<short><p>The opposite of <func>fopen()</func>--closes a file when
you're done with it so that it frees system resources.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int fclose(FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>When you open a file, the system sets aside some resources to
maintain information about that open file.  Usually it can only open so
many files at once.  In any case, the Right Thing to do is to close your
files when you're done using them so that the system resources are
freed.</p>

<p>Also, you might not find that all the information that you've written
to the file has actually been written to disk until the file is closed.
(You can force this with a call to <func>fflush()</func>.)</p>

<p>When your program exits normally, it closes all open files for you.
Lots of times, though, you'll have a long-running program, and it'd be
better to close the files before then.  In any case, not closing a file
you've opened makes you look bad.  So, remember to <func>fclose()</func>
your file when you're done with it!</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>On success, <tt>0</tt> is returned.  Typically no one checks for this.
On error <tt>EOF</tt> is returned.  Typically no one checks for this,
either.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>FILE *fp;

fp = fopen("spoonDB.dat", r"); // (you should error-check this)
sort_spoon_database(fp);
fclose(fp);   // pretty simple, huh. </code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== printf, fprintf
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="printf">
<title><func>printf()</func>, <func>fprintf()</func></title>
<short><p>Print a formatted string to the console or to a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int printf(const char *format, ...);
int fprintf(FILE *stream, const char *format, ...);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>

<p>These functions print formatted strings to a file (that is, a
<type>FILE*</type> you likely got from <func>fopen()</func>), or to the
console (which is usually itself just a special file, right?)</p>

<p>The <func>printf()</func> function is legendary as being one of the
most flexible outputting systems ever devisied.  It can also get a bit
freaky here or there, most notably in the <var>format</var> string.
We'll take it a step at a time here.</p>

<p>The easiest way to look at the format string is that it will print
everything in the string as-is, <emp>unless</emp> a character has a
percent sign (<tt>%</tt>) in front of it.  That's when the magic
happens: the next argument in the <func>printf()</func> argument list is
printed in the way described by the percent code.</p>

<p>Here are the most common percent codes:</p>

<deflist>
<def>
<deftitle><tt>%d</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Print the next argument as a signed decimal number, like
<tt>3490</tt>.  The argument printed this way should be an
<type>int</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%f</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Print the next argument as a signed floating point number, like
<tt>3.14159</tt>.  The argument printed this way should be a
<type>float</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%c</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Print the next argument as a character, like
<tt>'B'</tt>.  The argument printed this way should be a
<type>char</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%s</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Print the next argument as a string, like
<tt>"Did you remember your mittens?"</tt>.  The argument printed this
way should be a <type>char*</type> or <type>char[]</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%%</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>No arguments are converted, and a plain old run-of-the-mill
percent sign is printed.  This is how you print a '%' using
<func>printf)()</func>.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>So those are the basics.  I'll give you some more of the percent
codes in a bit, but let's get some more breadth before then.  There's
actually a lot more that you can specify in there after the percent
sign.</p>

<p>For one thing, you can put a field width in there&emdash;this is a
number that tells <func>printf()</func> how many spaces to put on one
side or the other of the value you're printing.  That helps you line
things up in nice columns.  If the number is negative, the result
becomes left-justified instead of right-justified.  Example:</p>

<code>printf("%10d", x);  /* prints X on the right side of the 10-space field */
printf("%-10d", x); /* prints X on the left side of the 10-space field */</code>

<p>If you don't know the field width in advance, you can use a little
kung-foo to get it from the argument list just before the argument
itself.  Do this by placing your seat and tray tables in the fully
upright position.  The seatbelt is fastened by placing
the&emdash;<emp>*cough*</emp>.  I seem to have been doing way too much
flying lately.  Ignoring that useless fact completely, you can specify a
dynamic field width by putting a <tt>*</tt> in for the width.  If you
are not willing or able to perform this task, please notify a flight
attendant and we will reseat you.</p>

<code>int width = 12;
int value = 3490;

printf("%*d\n", width, value);</code>

<p>You can also put a "0" in front of the number if you want it to be
padded with zeros:</p>

<code>int x = 17;
printf("%05d", x);  /* "00017" */</code>

<p>When it comes to floating point, you can also specify how many
decimal places to print by making a field width of the form
"<tt>x.y</tt>" where <tt>x</tt> is the field width (you can leave this
off if you want it to be just wide enough) and <tt>y</tt> is the number
of digits past the decimal point to print:</p>

<code>float f = 3.1415926535;

printf("%.2f", f);  /* "3.14" */
printf("%7.3f", f); /* "  3.141" &lt;-- 7 spaces across */</code>

<p>Ok, those above are definitely the most common uses of
<func>printf()</func>, but there are still more modifiers you can put in
after the percent and before the field width:</p>

<deflist>
<def>
<deftitle><tt>0</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>This was already mentioned above.  It pads the spaces before a
number with zeros, e.g. <tt>"%05d"</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>-</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>This was also already mentioned above.  It causes the value to
be left-justified in the field, e.g. <tt>"%-5d"</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>' '</tt> (space)</deftitle>
<deftext><p>This prints a blank space before a positive number, so that
it will line up in a column along with negative numbers (which have a
negative sign in front of them).  <tt>"% d"</tt>.</p></deftext> </def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>+</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Always puts a <tt>+</tt> sign in front of a number that you
print so that it will line up in a column along with negative numbers
(which have a negative sign in front of them).
<tt>"%+d"</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>#</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>This causes the output to be printed in a different form than
normal.  The results vary based on the specifier used, but
generally, hexidecimal output (<tt>"%x"</tt>) gets a <tt>"0x"</tt>
prepended to the output, and octal output (<tt>"%o"</tt>) gets a
<tt>"0"</tt> prepended to it.  These are, if you'll notice, how such
numbers are represented in C source.  Additionally, floating point
numbers, when printed with this <tt>#</tt> modified, will print a
trailing decimal point even if the number has no fractional part.
Example: <tt>"%#x"</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>Now, I know earlier I promised the rest of the format specifiers...so
ok, here they are:</p>

<deflist>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%i</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Just like <tt>%d</tt>, above.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%o</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Prints the integer number out in octal format.  Octal is a
base-eight number representation scheme invented on the planet Krylon
where all the inhabitants have only eight fingers.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%u</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Just like <tt>%d</tt>, but works on <type>unsigned
int</type>s, instead of <type>int</type>s.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%x</tt> or <tt>%X</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Prints the <type>unsigned int</type> argument in hexidecimal
(base-16) format.  This is for people with 16 fingers, or people who
are simply addicted hex, like you should be.  Just try it!
<tt>"%x"</tt> prints the hex digits in lowercase, while <tt>"%X"</tt>
prints them in uppercase.</p>
</deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%F</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Just like "%f", except any string-based results (which can
happen for numbers like infinity) are printed in
uppercase.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%e</tt> or <tt>%E</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Prints the <type>float</type> argument in exponential
(scientific) notation.  This is your classic form similar to "three
times 10 to the 8th power", except printed in text form: "<tt>3e8</tt>".
(You see, the "<tt>e</tt>" is read "times 10 to the".)  If you use the
<tt>"%E"</tt> specifier, the the exponent "e" is written in uppercase, a
la "<tt>3E8</tt>".</p>
</deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%g</tt> or <tt>%G</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Another way of printing <type>double</type>s.  In this case
the precision you specific tells it how many significant figures to
print.</p>
</deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%p</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Prints a pointer type out in hex representation.  In other
words, the address that the pointer is pointing to is printed.  (Not the
value in the address, but the address number itself.)</p>
</deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%n</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>This specifier is cool and different, and rarely needed.  It
doesn't actually print anything, but stores the number of characters
printed so far in the next pointer argument in the list.</p>
<code>int numChars;
float a = 3.14159;
int b = 3490;

printf("%f %d%n\n", a, b, &amp;numChars);
printf("The above line contains %d characters.\n", numChars);</code>

<p>The above example will print out the values of <var>a</var> and
<var>b</var>, and then store the number of characters printed so far
into the variable <var>numChars</var>.  The next call to
<func>printf()</func> prints out that result.</p>

</deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>So let's recap what we have here.  We have a format string in the
form:</p>

<screen>"%[modifier][fieldwidth][.precision][lengthmodifier][formatspecifier]"</screen>

<p>Modifier is like the <tt>"-"</tt> for left justification, the field
width is how wide a space to print the result in, the precision is, for
<type>float</type>s, how many decimal places to print, and the format
specifier is like <tt>%d</tt>.</p>

<p>That wraps it up, except what's this "lengthmodifier" I put up
there?!  Yes, just when you thought things were under control, I had to
add something else on there.  Basically, it's to tell
<func>printf()</func> in more detail what size the arguments are.  For
instance, <type>char</type>, <type>short</type>, <type>int</type>,
and <type>long</type> are all integer types, but they all use a
different number of bytes of memory, so you can't use plain old
"<tt>%d</tt>" for <emp>all</emp> of them, right?  How can
<func>printf()</func> tell the difference?</p>

<p>The answer is that you tell it explicitly using another optional
letter (the length modifier, this) before the type specifier.  If you
omit it, then the basic types are assumed (like <tt>%d</tt> is for
<type>int</type>, and <tt>%f</tt> is for <type>float</type>).</p>

<p>Here are the format specifiers:</p>

<deflist>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>h</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Integer referred to is a <type>short</type> integer, e.g.
"<tt>%hd</tt>" is a <type>short</type> and "<tt>%hu</tt>" is an
<type>unsigned short</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>l</tt> ("ell")</deftitle>
<deftext><p>Integer referred to is a <type>long</type> integer, e.g.
"<tt>%ld</tt>" is a <type>long</type> and "<tt>%lu</tt>" is an
<type>unsigned long</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>hh</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Integer referred to is a <type>char</type> integer, e.g.
"<tt>%hhd</tt>" is a <type>char</type> and "<tt>%hhu</tt>" is an
<type>unsigned char</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>ll</tt> ("ell ell")</deftitle>
<deftext><p>Integer referred to is a <type>long long</type> integer, e.g.
"<tt>%lld</tt>" is a <type>long long</type> and "<tt>%llu</tt>" is an
<type>unsigned long long</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>I know it's hard to believe, but there might be <emp>still more</emp>
format and length specifiers on your system.  Check your manual for more
information.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>int a = 100;
	float b = 2.717;
	char *c = "beej!";
	char d = 'X';
	int e = 5;

	printf("%d", a); /* "100"      */
	printf("%f", b); /* "2.717000" */
	printf("%s", c); /* "beej!"    */
	printf("%c", d); /* "X"        */
	printf("110%%"); /* "110%"     */

	printf("%10d\n", a);   /* "       100" */
	printf("%-10d\n", a);  /* "100       " */
	printf("%*d\n", e, a); /* "  100"      */
	printf("%.2f\n", b);   /* "2.71"       */

	printf("%hhd\n", c); /* "88" &lt;-- ASCII code for 'X' */
	
	printf("%5d %5.2f %c\n", a, b, d); /* "  100  2.71 X" */</code>

</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="sprintf"><func>sprintf()</func></link>,
<link dest="vprintf"><func>vprintf()</func></link>,
<link dest="vfprintf"><func>vfprintf()</func></link>,
<link dest="vsprintf"><func>vsprintf()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== scanf, fscanf
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="scanf">
<title><func>scanf()</func>, <func>fscanf()</func></title>
<short><p>Read formatted string, character, or numeric data from the
console or from a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int scanf(const char *format, ...);
int fscanf(FILE *stream, const char *format, ...);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>The <func>scanf()</func> family of functions reads data from the
console or from a <type>FILE</type> stream, parses it, and stores the
results away in variables you provide in the argument list.</p>

<p>The format string is very similar to that in <func>printf()</func> in
that you can tell it to read a <tt>"%d"</tt>, for instance for an
<type>int</type>.  But it also has additional capabilities, most notably
that it can eat up other characters in the input that you specify in the
format string.</p>

<p>But let's start simple, and look at the most basic usage first before
plunging into the depths of the function.  We'll start by reading an
<type>int</type> from the keyboard:</p>

<code>int a;

scanf("%d", &amp;a);</code>

<p><func>scanf()</func> obviously needs a pointer to the variable if it
is going to change the variable itself, so we use the address-of
operator to get the pointer.</p>

<p>In this case, <func>scanf()</func> walks down the format string,
finds a "<tt>%d</tt>", and then knows it needs to read an integer and
store it in the next variable in the argument list, <var>a</var>.</p>

<p>Here are some of the other percent-codes you can put in the format
string:</p>

<deflist>
<def>
<deftitle><tt>%d</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads an integer to be stored in an <type>int</type>.  This
integer can be signed.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%f</tt> (<tt>%e</tt>, <tt>%E</tt>, and <tt>%g</tt> are
equivalent)</deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads a floating point number, to be stored in a
<type>float</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%s</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads a string.  This will stop on the first whitespace
character reached, or at the specified field width (e.g. "%10s"),
whichever comes first.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>And here are some more codes, except these don't tend to be used as
often.  You, of course, may use them as often as you wish!</p>

<deflist>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%u</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads an unsigned integer to be stored in an
<type>unsigned int</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%x</tt> (<tt>%X</tt> is equivalent)</deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads an unsigned hexidecimal integer to be stored in an
<type>unsigned int</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%o</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads an unsigned octal integer to be stored in an
<type>unsigned int</type>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%i</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Like <tt>%d</tt>, except you can preface the input with "0x"
if it's a hex number, or "0" if it's an octal number.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%c</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads in a character to be stored in a <type>char</type>.
If you specify a field width (e.g. "<tt>%12c</tt>", it will read that
many characters, so make sure you have an array that large to hold
them.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%p</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads in a pointer to be stored in a <type>void*</type>.
The format of this pointer should be the same as that which is outputted
with <func>printf()</func> and the "<tt>%p</tt>" format
specifier.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%n</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Reads nothing, but will store the number of characters
processed so far into the next <type>int</type> parameter in the
argument list.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%%</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Matches a literal percent sign.  No conversion of parameters
is done.  This is simply how you get a standalone percent sign in your
string without <func>scanf()</func> trying to do something with
it.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>%[</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>This is about the weirdest format specifier there is.  It
allows you to specify a set of characters to be stored away (likely in
an array of <type>char</type>s).  Conversion stops when a character that
is not in the set is matched.</p>

<p>For example, <tt>%[0-9]</tt> means "match all numbers zero through
nine."  And <tt>%[AD-G34]</tt> means "match A, D through G, 3, or
4".</p>

<p>Now, to convolute matters, you can tell <func>scanf()</func> to match
characters that are <emp>not</emp> in the set by putting a caret
(<tt>^</tt>) directly after the <tt>%[</tt> and following it with the
set, like this: <tt>%[^A-C]</tt>, which means "match all characters that
are <emp>not</emp> A through C."</p>

<p>To match a close square bracket, make it the first character in the
set, like this: <tt>%[]A-C]</tt> or <tt>%[^]A-C]</tt>.  (I added the
"<tt>A-C</tt>" just so it was clear that the "<tt>]</tt>" was first in
the set.)</p>

<p>To match a hyphen, make it the last character in the set:
<tt>%[A-C-]</tt>.</p>

<p>So if we wanted to match all letters <emp>except</emp> "%", "^", "]",
"B", "C", "D", "E", and "-", we could use this format string:
<tt>%[^]%^B-E-]</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>So those are the basics!  Phew!  There's a lot of stuff to know, but,
like I said, a few of these format specifiers are common, and the others
are pretty rare.</p>

<p>Got it?  Now we can go onto the next&emdash;no wait!  There's more!
Yes, still more to know about <func>scanf()</func>.  Does it never end?
Try to imagine how I feel writing about it!</p>

<p>So you know that "<tt>%d</tt>" stores into an <type>int</type>.  But
how do you store into a <type>long</type>, <type>short</type>, or
<type>double</type>?</p>

<p>Well, like in <func>printf()</func>, you can add a modifier before
the type specifier to tell <func>scanf()</func> that you have a
longer or shorter type.  The following is a table of the possible
modifiers:</p>

<deflist>
<def>
<deftitle><tt>h</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>The value to be parsed is a <type>short int</type> or
<type>short unsigned</type>.  Example: <tt>%hd</tt> or
<tt>%hu</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>l</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>The value to be parsed is a <type>long int</type> or
<type>long unsigned</type>, or <type>double</type> (for <tt>%f</tt>
conversions.)  Example: <tt>%ld</tt>,
<tt>%lu</tt>, or <tt>%lf</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>L</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>The value to be parsed is a <type>long long</type> for
integer types or <type>long double</type> for <type>float</type> types.
Example: <tt>%Ld</tt>, <tt>%Lu</tt>, or <tt>%Lf</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>*</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p>Tells <func>scanf()</func> do to the conversion specified,
but not store it anywhere.  It simply discards the data as it reads it.
This is what you use if you want <func>scanf()</func> to eat some data
but you don't want to store it anywhere; you don't give
<func>scanf()</func> an argument for this conversion.  Example:
<tt>%*d</tt>.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p><func>scanf()</func> returns the number of items assigned into
variables.  Since assignment into variables stops when given invalid
input for a certain format specifier, this can tell you if you've input
all your data correctly.</p>

<p>Also, <func>scanf()</func> returns <tt>EOF</tt> on end-of-file.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>int a;
long int b;
unsigned int c;
float d;
double e;
long double f;
char s[100];

scanf("%d", &amp;a);  // store an int
scanf(" %d", &amp;a); // eat any whitespace, then store an int
scanf("%s", s); // store a string
scanf("%Lf", &amp;f); // store a long double

// store an unsigned, read all whitespace, then store a long int:
scanf("%u %ld", &amp;c, &amp;b);

// store an int, read whitespace, read "blendo", read whitespace,
// and store a float:
scanf("%d blendo %f", &amp;a, &amp;d);

// read all whitespace, then store all characters up to a newline
scanf(" %[^\n]", s);

// store a float, read (and ignore) an int, then store a double:
scanf("%f %*d %lf", &amp;d, &amp;e);

// store 10 characters:
scanf("%10c", s);</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="sscanf"><func>sscanf()</func></link>,
<link dest="vscanf"><func>vscanf()</func></link>,
<link dest="vsscanf"><func>vsscanf()</func></link>,
<link dest="vfscanf"><func>vfscanf()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== gets, fgets
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="gets">
<title><func>gets()</func>, <func>fgets()</func></title>
<short><p>Read a string from console or file</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

char *fgets(char *s, int size, FILE *stream);
char *gets(char *s);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>

<p>These are functions that will retrieve a newline-terminated string from
the console or a file.  In other normal words, it reads a line of text.
The behavior is slightly different, and, as such, so is the usage.  For
instance, here is the usage of <func>gets()</func>:</p>

<p>Don't use <func>gets()</func>.</p>

<p>Admittedly, rationale would be useful, yes?  For one thing,
<func>gets()</func> doesn't allow you to specify the length of the
buffer to store the string in.  This would allow people to keep entering
data past the end of your buffer, and believe me, this would be Bad
News.</p>

<p>I was going to add another reason, but that's basically the primary
and only reason not to use <func>gets()</func>.  As you might suspect,
<func>fgets()</func> allows you to specify a maximum string length.</p>

<p>One difference here between the two functions: <func>gets()</func>
will devour and throw away the newline at the end of the line, while
<func>fgets()</func> will store it at the end of your string (space
permitting).</p>

<p>Here's an example of using <func>fgets()</func> from the console,
making it behave more like <func>gets()</func>:</p>

<code>char s[100];
gets(s);  // don't use this--read a line (from stdin)
fgets(s, sizeof(s), stdin); // read a line from stdin</code>

<p>In this case, the <operator>sizeof()</operator> operator gives us the
total size of the array in bytes, and since a <type>char</type> is a
byte, it conveniently gives us the total size of the array.</p>

<p>Of course, like I keep saying, the string returned from
<func>fgets()</func> probably has a newline at the end that you might
not want.  You can write a short function to chop the newline off, like
so:</p>

<code>char *remove_newline(char *s)
{
	int len = strlen(s);

	if (len &gt; 0 &amp;&amp; s[len-1] == '\n')  // if there's a newline
		s[len-1] = '\0';          // truncate the string

	return s;
}</code>

<p>So, in summary, use <func>fgets()</func> to read a line of text from
the keyboard or a file, and don't use <func>gets()</func>.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Both <func>fgets()</func> and <func>fgets()</func> return a pointer to
the string passed.</p>

<p>On error or end-of-file, the functions return <type>NULL</type>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char s[100];

gets(s); // read from standard input (don't use this--use fgets()!)

fgets(s, sizeof(s), stdin); // read 100 bytes from standard input

fp = fopen("datafile.dat", "r"); // (you should error-check this)
fgets(s, 100, fp); // read 100 bytes from the file datafile.dat
fclose(fp);

fgets(s, 20, stdin); // read a maximum of 20 bytes from stdin</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="getc"><func>getc()</func></link>,
<link dest="getc"><func>fgetc()</func></link>,
<link dest="getc"><func>getchar()</func></link>,
<link dest="puts"><func>puts()</func></link>,
<link dest="puts"><func>fputs()</func></link>,
<link dest="ungetc"><func>ungetc()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== getc, fgetc, getchar
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="getc">
<title><func>getc()</func>, <func>fgetc()</func>, <func>getchar()</func></title>
<short><p>Get a single character from the console or from a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int getc(FILE *stream);
int fgetc(FILE *stream);
int getchar(void);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>All of these functions in one way or another, read a single character
from the console or from a <type>FILE</type>.  The differences are
fairly minor, and here are the descriptions:</p>

<p><func>getc()</func> returns a character from the specified
<type>FILE</type>.  From a usage standpoint, it's equivalent to the same
<func>fgetc()</func> call, and <func>fgetc()</func> is a little more
common to see.  Only the implementation of the two functions
differs.</p>

<p><func>fgetc()</func> returns a character from the specified
<type>FILE</type>.  From a usage standpoint, it's equivalent to the same
<func>getc()</func> call, except that <func>fgetc()</func> is a little
more common to see.  Only the implementation of the two functions
differs.</p>

<p>Yes, I cheated and used cut-n-paste to do that last paragraph.</p>

<p><func>getchar()</func> returns a character from <var>stdin</var>.  In
fact, it's the same as calling <tt>getc(stdin)</tt>.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>All three functions return the <type>unsigned char</type> that they
read, except it's cast to an <type>int</type>.</p>

<p>If end-of-file or an error is encountered, all three functions return
<tt>EOF</tt>.</p>

</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// read all characters from a file, outputting only the letter 'b's
// it finds in the file

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	FILE *fp;
	int c;

	fp = fopen("datafile.txt", "r"); // error check this!

	// this while-statement assigns into c, and then checks against EOF:

	while((c = fgetc(fp)) != EOF) {
		if (c == 'b') {
			putchar(c);
		}
	}

	fclose(fp);

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== puts, fputs
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="puts">
<title><func>puts()</func>, <func>fputs()</func></title>
<short><p>Write a string to the console or to a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int puts(const char *s);
int fputs(const char *s, FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Both these functions output a NUL-terminated string.
<func>puts()</func> outputs to the console, while <func>fputs()</func>
allows you to specify the file for output.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Both functions return non-negative on success, or <tt>EOF</tt> on
error.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// read strings from the console and save them in a file

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	FILE *fp;
	char s[100];

	fp = fopen("datafile.txt", "w"); // error check this!

	while(fgets(s, sizeof(s), stdin) != NULL) { // read a string
		fputs(s, fp);  // write it to the file we opened
	}

	fclose(fp);

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== putc, fputc, putchar
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="putc">
<title><func>putc()</func>, <func>fputc()</func>, <func>putchar()</func></title>
<short><p>Write a single character to the console or to a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int putc(int c, FILE *stream);
int fputc(int c, FILE *stream);
int putchar(int c);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>All three functions output a single character, either to the console
or to a <type>FILE</type>.</p>

<p><func>putc()</func> takes a character argument, and outputs it to the
specified <type>FILE</type>.  <func>fputc()</func> does exactly the same
thing, and differs from <func>putc()</func> in implementation only.
Most people use <func>fputc()</func>.</p>

<p><func>putchar()</func> writes the character to the console, and is
the same as calling <tt>putc(c, stdout)</tt>.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>All three functions return the character written on success, or
<tt>EOF</tt> on error.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// print the alphabet

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	char i;

	for(i = 'A'; i &lt;= 'Z'; i++)
		putchar(i);

	putchar('\n'); // put a newline at the end to make it pretty

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== fseek
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fseek">
<title><func>fseek()</func>, <func>rewind()</func></title>
<short><p>Position the file pointer in anticipition of the next read or
write.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int fseek(FILE *stream, long offset, int whence);
void rewind(FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>When doing reads and writes to a file, the OS keeps track of where you
are in the file using a counter generically known as the file pointer.
You can reposition the file pointer to a different point in the file
using the <func>fseek()</func> call.  Think of it as a way to randomly
access you file.</p>

<p>The first argument is the file in question, obviously.
<var>offset</var> argument is the position that you want to seek to, and
<var>whence</var> is what that offset is relative to.</p>

<p>Of course, you probably like to think of the offset as being from the
beginning of the file.  I mean, "Seek to position 3490, that should be
3490 bytes from the beginning of the file."  Well, it <emp>can</emp> be,
but it doesn't have to be.  Imagine the power you're wielding here.  Try
to command your enthusiasm.</p>

<p>You can set the value of <var>whence</var> to one of three
things:</p>

<deflist>
<def>
<deftitle><tt>SEEK_SET</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p><var>offset</var> is relative to the beginning of the file.
This is probably what you had in mind anyway, and is the most commonly
used value for <var>whence</var>.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>SEEK_CUR</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p><var>offset</var> is relative to the current file pointer
position.  So, in effect, you can say, "Move to my current position plus
30 bytes," or, "move to my current position minus 20
bytes."</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>SEEK_END</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p><var>offset</var> is relative to the end of the file.  Just
like <tt>SEEK_SET</tt> except from the other end of the file.  Be sure
to use negative values for <var>offset</var> if you want to back up from
the end of the file, instead of going past the end into
oblivion.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>Speaking of seeking off the end of the file, can you do it?  Sure
thing.  In fact, you can seek way off the end and then write a
character; the file will be expanded to a size big enough to hold a
bunch of zeros way out to that character.</p>

<p>Now that the complicated function is out of the way, what's this
<func>rewind()</func> that I briefly mentioned?  It repositions the file
pointer at the beginning of the file:</p>

<code>fseek(fp, 0, SEEK_SET); // same as rewind()
rewind(fp);             // same as fseek(fp, 0, SEEK_SET)</code>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>For <func>fseek()</func>, on success zero is returned; <tt>-1</tt> is
returned on failure.</p>

<p>The call to <func>rewind()</func> never fails.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>fseek(fp, 100, SEEK_SET); // seek to the 100th byte of the file
fseek(fp, -30, SEEK_CUR); // seek backward 30 bytes from the current pos
fseek(fp, -10, SEEK_END); // seek to the 10th byte before the end of file

fseek(fp, 0, SEEK_SET);   // seek to the beginning of the file
rewind(fp);               // seek to the beginning of the file</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="ftell"><func>ftell()</func></link>,
<link dest="fgetpos"><func>fgetpos()</func></link>,
<link dest="fgetpos"><func>fsetpos()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== ftell
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="ftell">
<title><func>ftell()</func></title>
<short><p>Tells you where a particular file is about to read from or
write to.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

long ftell(FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>This function is the opposite of <link
dest="fseek"><func>fseek()</func></link>.  It tells you where in the
file the next file operation will occur relative to the beginning of the
file.</p>

<p>It's useful if you want to remember where you are in the file,
<func>fseek()</func> somewhere else, and then come back later.  You can
take the return value from <func>ftell()</func> and feed it back into
<func>fseek()</func> (with <var>whence</var> parameter set to
<tt>SEEK_SET</tt>) when you want to return to your previous position.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the current offset in the file, or <tt>-1</tt> on error.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>long pos;

// store the current position in variable "pos":
pos = ftell(fp);

// seek ahead 10 bytes:
fseek(fp, 10, SEEK_CUR);

// do some mysterious writes to the file
do_mysterious_writes_to_file(fp);

// and return to the starting position, stored in "pos":
fseek(fp, pos, SEEK_SET);</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fseek"><func>fseek()</func></link>,
<link dest="fseek"><func>rewind()</func></link>,
<link dest="fgetpos"><func>fgetpos()</func></link>,
<link dest="fgetpos"><func>fsetpos()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== fgetpos, fsetpos
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fgetpos">
<title><func>fgetpos()</func>, <func>fsetpos()</func></title>
<short><p>Get the current position in a file, or set the current position
in a file.  Just like <func>ftell()</func> and <func>fseek()</func> for
most systems.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int fgetpos(FILE *stream, fpos_t *pos);
int fsetpos(FILE *stream, fpos_t *pos);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>These functions are just like <func>ftell()</func> and
<func>fseek()</func>, except instead of counting in bytes, they use an
<emp>opaque</emp> data structure to hold positional information about
the file.  (Opaque, in this case, means you're not supposed to know what
the data type is made up of.)</p>

<p>On virtually every system (and certainly every system that I know
of), people don't use these functions, using <func>ftell()</func> and
<func>fseek()</func> instead.  These functions exist just in case your
system can't remember file positions as a simple byte offset.</p>

<p>Since the <var>pos</var> variable is opaque, you have to assign to it
using the <func>fgetpos()</func> call itself.  Then you save the value
for later and use it to reset the position using
<func>fsetpos()</func>.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Both functions return zero on success, and <tt>-1</tt> on error.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char s[100];
fpos_t pos;

fgets(s, sizeof(s), fp); // read a line from the file

fgetpos(fp, &amp;pos);   // save the position

fgets(s, sizeof(s), fp); // read another line from the file

fsetpos(fp, &amp;pos);   // now restore the position to where we saved</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fseek"><func>fseek()</func></link>,
<link dest="ftell"><func>ftell()</func></link>,
<link dest="fseek"><func>rewind()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== ungetc
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="ungetc">
<title><func>ungetc()</func></title>
<short><p>Pushes a character back into the input stream.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int ungetc(int c, FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>You know how <func>getc()</func> reads the next character from a file
stream?  Well, this is the opposite of that&emdash;it pushes a character
back into the file stream so that it will show up again on the very next
read from the stream, as if you'd never gotten it from
<func>getc()</func> in the first place.</p>

<p>Why, in the name of all that is holy would you want to do that?
Perhaps you have a stream of data that you're reading a character at a
time, and you won't know to stop reading until you get a certain
character, but you want to be able to read that character again later.
You can read the character, see that it's what you're supposed to stop
on, and then <func>ungetc()</func> it so it'll show up on the next
read.</p>

<p>Yeah, that doesn't happen very often, but there we are.</p>

<p>Here's the catch: the standard only guarantees that you'll be able to
push back <emp>one character</emp>.  Some implementations might allow
you to push back more, but there's really no way to tell and still be
portable.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>On success, <func>ungetc()</func> returns the character you passed to
it.  On failure, it returns <tt>EOF</tt>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// read a piece of punctuation, then everything after it up to the next
// piece of punctuation.  return the punctuation, and store the rest
// in a string
//
// sample input: !foo#bar*baz
// output:  return value: '!', s is "foo"
//          return value: '#', s is "bar"
//          return value: '*', s is "baz"
//

char read_punctstring(FILE *fp, char *s)
{
	char origpunct, c;
	
	origpunct = fgetc(fp);

	if (origpunct == EOF) // return EOF on end-of-file
		return EOF;

	while(c = fgetc(fp), !ispunct(c) &amp;&amp; c != EOF) {
		*s++ = c; // save it in the string
	}
	*s = '\0'; // nul-terminate the string!

	// if we read punctuation last, ungetc it so we can fgetc it next
	// time:
	if (ispunct(c))
		ungetc(c, fp);
	}

	return origpunct;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="getc"><func>fgetc()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== manpage header
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fread">
<title><func>fread()</func></title>
<short><p>Read binary data from a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

size_t fread(void *p, size_t size, size_t nmemb, FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>You might remember that you can call <link
dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link> with the "<tt>b</tt>" flag in
the open mode string to open the file in "binary" mode.  Files open in
not-binary (ASCII or text mode) can be read using standard
character-oriented calls like <link
dest="getc"><func>fgetc()</func></link> or <link
dest="gets"><func>fgets()</func></link>.  Files open in binary mode are
typically read using the <func>fread()</func> function.</p>

<p>All this function does is says, "Hey, read this many things where
each thing is a certain number of bytes, and store the whole mess of
them in memory starting at this pointer."</p>

<p>This can be very useful, believe me, when you want to do something
like store 20 <type>int</type>s in a file.</p>

<p>But wait&emdash;can't you use <link
dest="printf"><func>fprintf()</func></link> with the "<tt>%d</tt>"
format specifier to save the <type>int</type>s to a text file and store
them that way?  Yes, sure.  That has the advantage that a human can open
the file and read the numbers.  It has the disadvantage that it's slower
to convert the numbers from <type>int</type>s to text and that the
numbers are likely to take more space in the file.  (Remember, an
<type>int</type> is likely 4 bytes, but the string "12345678" is 8
bytes.)</p>

<p>So storing the binary data can certainly be more compact and faster
to read.</p>

<p>(As for the prototype, what is this <type>size_t</type> you see
floating around?  It's short for "size type" which is a data type
defined to hold the size of something.  Great&emdash;would I stop
beating around the bush already and give you the straight story?!  Ok,
<type>size_t</type> is probably an <type>int</type>.)</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>This function returns the number of items successfully read.  If all
requested items are read, the return value will be equal to that of the
parameter <var>nmemb</var>.  If EOF occurs, the return value will be
zero.</p>

<p>To make you confused, it will also return zero if there's an error.
You can use the functions <link dest="feof"><func>feof()</func></link>
or <link dest="feof"><func>ferror()</func></link> to tell which one
really happened.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// read 10 numbers from a file and store them in an array

int main(void)
{
	int i;
	int n[10]
	FILE *fp;

	fp = fopen("binarynumbers.dat", "rb");
	fread(n, sizeof(int), 10, fp);  // read 10 ints
	fclose(fp);

	// print them out:
	for(i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++)
		printf("n[%d] == %d\n", i, n[i]);

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link>,
<link dest="fwrite"><func>fwrite()</func></link>,
<link dest="feof"><func>feof()</func></link>,
<link dest="feof"><func>ferror()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== manpage header
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fwrite">
<title><func>fwrite()</func></title>
<short><p>Write binary data to a file.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

size_t fwrite(const void *p, size_t size, size_t nmemb, FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>This is the counterpart to the <link
dest="fread"><func>fread()</func></link> function.  It writes blocks of
binary data to disk.  For a description of what this means, see the
entry for <link dest="fread"><func>fread()</func></link>.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p><func>fwrite()</func> returns the number of items successfully
written, which should hopefully be <var>nmemb</var> that you passed in.
It'll return zero on error.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// save 10 random numbers to a file

int main(void)
{
	int i;
	int r[10];
	FILE *fp;

	// populate the array with random numbers:
	for(i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
		r[i] = rand();
	}

	// save the random numbers (10 ints) to the file
	fp = fopen("binaryfile.dat", "wb");
	fwrite(r, sizeof(int), 10, fp); // write 10 ints
	fclose(fp);

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link>,
<link dest="fread"><func>fread()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== manpage header
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="feof">
<title><func>feof()</func>, <func>ferror()</func>,
<func>clearerr()</func></title>
<short><p>Determine if a file has reached end-of-file or if an error has
occurred.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int feof(FILE *stream);
int ferror(FILE *stream);
void clearerr(FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Each <type>FILE*</type> that you use to read and write data from and
to a file contains flags that the system sets when certain events occur.
If you get an error, it sets the error flag; if you reach the end of the
file during a read, it sets the EOF flag.  Pretty simple really.</p>

<p>The functions <func>feof()</func> and <func>ferror()</func> give you
a simple way to test these flags: they'll return non-zero (true) if
they're set.</p>

<p>Once the flags are set for a particular stream, they stay that way
until you call <func>clearerr()</func> to clear them.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p><func>feof()</func> and <func>ferror()</func> return non-zero (true) if
the file has reached EOF or there has been an error, respectively.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// read binary data, checking for eof or error
int main(void)
{
	int a;
	FILE *fp;

	fp = fopen("binaryints.dat", "rb");

	// read single ints at a time, stopping on EOF or error:

	while(fread(&amp;a, sizeof(int), 1, fp), !feof(fp) &amp;&amp; !ferror(fp)) {
		printf("I read %d\n", a);
	}

	if (feof(fp))
		printf("End of file was reached.\n");

	if (ferror(fp))
		printf("An error occurred.\n");

	fclose(fp);

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link>,
<link dest="fread"><func>fread()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== perror
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="perror">
<title><func>perror()</func></title>
<short><p>Print the last error message to <var>stderr</var></p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;errno.h&gt;  // only if you want to directly use the "errno" var

void perror(const char *s);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Many functions, when they encounter an error condition for whatever
reason, will set a global variable called <var>errno</var> for you.
<var>errno</var> is just an interger representing a unique error.</p>

<p>But to you, the user, some number isn't generally very useful.  For
this reason, you can call <func>perror()</func> after an error occurs to
print what error has actually happened in a nice human-readable
string.</p>

<p>And to help you along, you can pass a parameter, <var>s</var>, that
will be prepended to the error string for you.</p>

<p>One more clever trick you can do is check the value of the
<var>errno</var> (you have to include <file>errno.h</file> to see it)
for specific errors and have your code do different things.  Perhaps you
want to ignore certain errors but not others, for instance.</p>

<p>The catch is that different systems define different values for
<var>errno</var>, so it's not very portable.  The standard only defines
a few math-related values, and not others.  You'll have to check your
local man-pages for what works on your system.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns nothing at all!  Sorry!</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<p><link dest="fseek"><func>fseek()</func></link> returns <tt>-1</tt> on error, and
sets <var>errno</var>, so let's use it.  Seeking on <var>stdin</var>
makes no sense, so it should generate an error:</p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;errno.h&gt; // must include this to see "errno" in this example

int main(void)
{
	if (fseek(stdin, 10L, SEEK_SET) &lt; 0)
		perror("fseek");

	fclose(stdin); // stop using this stream

	if (fseek(stdin, 20L, SEEK_CUR) &lt; 0) {

		// specifically check errno to see what kind of
		// error happened...this works on Linux, but your
		// mileage may vary on other systems!

		if (errno == EBADF) {
			perror("fseek again, EBADF");
		} else {
			perror("fseek again");
		}
	}

	return 0;
}</code>

<p>And the output is:</p>

<screen>fseek: Illegal seek
fseek again, EBADF: Bad file descriptor</screen>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="feof"><func>feof()</func></link>,
<link dest="feof"><func>ferror()</func></link>,
<link dest="feof"><func>clearerr()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== remove
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="remove">
<title><func>remove()</func></title>
<short><p>Delete a file</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int remove(const char *filename);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Removes the specified file from the filesystem.  It just deletes it.
Nothing magical.  Simply call this function and sacrifice a small
chicken and the requested file will be deleted.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns zero on success, and <tt>-1</tt> on error, setting
<var>errno</var>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char *filename = "/home/beej/evidence.txt";

remove(filename);
remove("/disks/d/Windows/system.ini");</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="rename"><func>rename()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== rename
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="rename">
<title><func>rename()</func></title>
<short><p>Renames a file and optionally moves it to a new location</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int rename(const char *old, const char *new);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Renames the file <var>old</var> to name <var>new</var>.  Use this
function if you're tired of the old name of the file, and you are ready
for a change.  Sometimes simply renaming your files makes them feel new
again, and could save you money over just getting all new files!</p>

<p>One other cool thing you can do with this function is actually move a
file from one directory to another by specifying a different path for
the new name.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns zero on success, and <tt>-1</tt> on error, setting
<var>errno</var>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>rename("foo", "bar"); // changes the name of the file "foo" to "bar"

// the following moves the file "evidence.txt" from "/tmp" to
// "/home/beej", and also renames it to "nothing.txt":
rename("/tmp/evidence.txt", "/home/beej/nothing.txt");</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="remove"><func>remove()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== tmpfile
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="tmpfile">
<title><func>tmpfile()</func></title>
<short><p>Create a temporary file</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

FILE *tmpfile(void);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>This is a nifty little function that will create and open a temporary
file for you, and will return a <type>FILE*</type> to it that you can
use.  The file is opened with mode "<tt>r+b</tt>", so it's suitable for
reading, writing, and binary data.</p>

<p>By using a little magic, the temp file is automatically deleted when
it is <func>close()</func>'d or when your program exits.  (Specifically,
<func>tmpfile()</func> unlinks the file right after it opens it.  If you
don't know what that means, it won't affect your <func>tmpfile()</func>
skill, but hey, be curious!  It's for your own good!)</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>This function returns an open <type>FILE*</type> on success, or
<type>NULL</type> on failure.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
	FILE *temp;
	char s[128];

	temp = tmpfile();

	fprintf(temp, "What is the frequency, Alexander?\n");

	rewind(temp); // back to the beginning

	fscanf(temp, "%s", s); // read it back out

	fclose(temp); // close (and magically delete)

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link><br/>
<link dest="fclose"><func>fclose()</func></link><br/>
<link dest="tmpnam"><func>tmpnam()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== tmpnam
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="tmpnam">
<title><func>tmpnam()</func></title>
<short><p>Generate a unique name for a temporary file</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

char *tmpnam(char *s);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>This function takes a good hard look at the existing files on your
system, and comes up with a unique name for a new file that is suitable
for temporary file usage.</p>

<p>Let's say you have a program that needs to store off some data for a
short time so you create a temporary file for the data, to be deleted
when the program is done running.  Now imagine that you called this file
<file>foo.txt</file>.  This is all well and good, except what if a user
already has a file called <file>foo.txt</file> in the directory that you
ran your program from?  You'd overwrite their file, and they'd be
unhappy and stalk you forever.  And you wouldn't want that, now would
you?</p>

<p>Ok, so you get wise, and you decide to put the file in
<file>/tmp</file> so that it won't overwrite any important content.  But
wait!  What if some other user is running your program at the same time
and they both want to use that filename?  Or what if some other program
has already created that file?</p>

<p>See, all of these scary problems can be completely avoided if you
just use <func>tmpnam()</func> to get a safe-ready-to-use filename.</p>

<p>So how do you use it?  There are two amazing ways.  One, you can
declare an array (or <func>malloc()</func> it&emdash;whatever) that is
big enough to hold the temporary file name.  How big is that?
Fortunately there has been a macro defined for you, <tt>L_tmpnam</tt>,
which is how big the array must be.</p>

<p>And the second way: just pass <type>NULL</type> for the filename.
<func>tmpnam()</func> will store the temporary name in a static array
and return a pointer to that.  Subsequent calls with a <type>NULL</type>
argument will overwrite the static array, so be sure you're done using
it before you call <func>tmpnam()</func> again.</p>

<p>Again, this function just makes a file name for you.  It's up to you
to later <func>fopen()</func> the file and use it.</p>

<p>One more note: some compilers warn against using
<func>tmpnam()</func> since some systems have better functions (like the
Unix function <func>mkstemp()</func>.)  You might want to check your
local documentation to see if there's a better option.  Linux
documentation goes so far as to say, "Never use this function. Use
<func>mkstemp()</func> instead."</p>

<p>I, however, am going to be a jerk and not talk about
<func>mkstemp()</func> because it's not in the standard I'm writing
about.  Nyaah.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns a pointer to the temporary file name.  This is either a
pointer to the string you passed in, or a pointer to internal static
storage if you passed in <type>NULL</type>.  On error (like it can't
find any temporary name that is unique), <func>tmpnam()</func> returns
<type>NULL</type>.</p>

</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char filename[L_tmpnam];
char *another_filename;

if (tmpnam(filename) != NULL)
	printf("We got a temp file named: \"%s\"\n", filename);
else
	printf("Something went wrong, and we got nothing!\n");

another_filename = tmpnam(NULL);
printf("We got another temp file named: \"%s\"\n", another_filename);
printf("And we didn't error check it because we're too lazy!\n");</code>

<p>On my Linux system, this generates the following output:</p>

<screen>We got a temp file named: "/tmp/filew9PMuZ"
We got another temp file named: "/tmp/fileOwrgPO"
And we didn't error check it because we're too lazy!</screen>
	
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fopen"><func>fopen()</func></link><br/>
<link dest="tmpfile"><func>tmpfile()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== setvbuf
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="setvbuf">
<title><func>setbuf()</func>, <func>setvbuf()</func></title>
<short><p>Configure buffering for standard I/O operations</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

void setbuf(FILE *stream, char *buf);
int setvbuf(FILE *stream, char *buf, int mode, size_t size);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Now brace yourself because this might come as a bit of a surprise to
you: when you <func>printf()</func> or <func>fprintf()</func> or use any
I/O functions like that, <emp>it does not normally work
immediately</emp>.  For the sake of efficiency, and to irritate you, the
I/O on a <type>FILE*</type> stream is buffered away safely until certain
conditions are met, and only then is the actual I/O performed.  The
functions <func>setbuf()</func> and <func>setvbuf()</func> allow you to
change those conditions and the buffering behavior.</p>

<p>So what are the different buffering behaviors?  The biggest is called
"full buffering", wherein all I/O is stored in a big buffer until it is
full, and then it is dumped out to disk (or whatever the file is).  The
next biggest is called "line buffering"; with line buffering, I/O is
stored up a line at a time (until a newline (<tt>'\n'</tt>) character is
encountered) and then that line is processed.  Finally, we have
"unbuffered", which means I/O is processed immediately with every
standard I/O call.</p>

<p>You might have seen and wondered why you could call
<func>putchar()</func> time and time again and not see any output until
you called <tt>putchar('\n')</tt>; that's right&emdash;<var>stdout</var>
is line-buffered!</p>

<p>Since <func>setbuf()</func> is just a simplified version of
<func>setvbuf()</func>, we'll talk about <func>setvbuf()</func>
first.</p>

<p>The <var>stream</var> is the <type>FILE*</type> you wish to modify.  The
standard says you <emp>must</emp> make your call to
<func>setvbuf()</func> <emp>before</emp> any I/O operation is performed
on the stream, or else by then it might be too late.</p>

<p>The next argument, <var>buf</var> allows you to make your own buffer
space (using <link dest="malloc"><func>malloc()</func></link> or just a
<type>char</type> array) to use for buffering.  If you don't care to do
this, just set <var>buf</var> to <type>NULL</type>.</p>

<p>
Now we get to the real meat of the function: <var>mode</var> allows you
to choose what kind of buffering you want to use on this
<var>stream</var>.  Set it to one of the following:</p>

<deflist>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>_IOFBF</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p><var>stream</var> will be fully buffered.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>_IOLBF</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p><var>stream</var> will be line buffered.</p></deftext>
</def>

<def>
<deftitle><tt>_IONBF</tt></deftitle>
<deftext><p><var>stream</var> will be unbuffered.</p></deftext>
</def>

</deflist>

<p>Finally, the <var>size</var> argument is the size of the array you
passed in for <var>buf</var>...unless you passed <type>NULL</type> for
<var>buf</var>, in which case it will resize the existing buffer to the
size you specify.</p>

<p>Now what about this lesser function <func>setbuf()</func>?  It's just
like calling <func>setvbuf()</func> with some specific parameters,
except <func>setbuf()</func> doesn't return a value.  The following
example shows the equivalency:</p>

<code>// these are the same:
setbuf(stream, buf);
setvbuf(stream, buf, _IOFBF, BUFSIZ); // fully buffered

// and these are the same:
setbuf(stream, NULL);
setvbuf(stream, NULL, _IONBF, BUFSIZ); // unbuffered</code>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p><func>setvbuf()</func> returns zero on success, and nonzero on failure.
<func>setbuf()</func> has no return value.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>FILE *fp;
char lineBuf[1024];

fp = fopen("somefile.txt", "r");
setvbuf(fp, lineBuf, _IOLBF, 1024);  // set to line buffering
// ...
fclose(fp);

fp = fopen("another.dat", "rb");
setbuf(fp, NULL); // set to unbuffered
// ...
fclose(fp);</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="fflush"><func>fflush()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== fflush
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="fflush">
<title><func>fflush()</func></title>
<short><p>Process all buffered I/O for a stream right now</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int fflush(FILE *stream);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>When you do standard I/O, as mentioned in the section on the <link
dest="setvbuf"><func>setvbuf()</func></link> function, it is usually
stored in a buffer until a line has been entered or the buffer is full
or the file is closed.  Sometimes, though, you really want the output to
happen <emp>right this second</emp>, and not wait around in the buffer.
You can force this to happen by calling <func>fflush()</func>.</p>

<p>
The advantage to buffering is that the OS doesn't need to hit the disk
every time you call <func>fprintf()</func>.  The disadvantage is that if
you look at the file on the disk after the <func>fprintf()</func> call,
it might not have actually been written to yet.  ("I called
<func>fputs()</func>, but the file is still zero bytes long!  Why?!")
In virtually all circumstances, the advantages of buffering outweigh the
disadvantages; for those other circumstances, however, use
<func>fflush()</func>.</p>

<p>Note that <func>fflush()</func> is only designed to work on output
streams according to the spec.  What will happen if you try it on an
input stream?  Use your spooky voice: <emp>who knooooows!</emp></p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>On success, <func>fflush()</func> returns zero.  If there's an error,
it returns <type>EOF</type> and sets the error condition for the stream
(see <link dest="feof"><func>ferror()</func></link>.)</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<p>In this example, we're going to use the carriage return, which is
<tt>'\r'</tt>.  This is like newline (<tt>'\n'</tt>), except that it
doesn't move to the next line.  It just returns to the front of the
current line.</p>

<p>What we're going to do is a little text-based status bar like so many
command line programs implement.  It'll do a countdown from 10 to 0
printing over itself on the same line.</p>

<p>What is the catch and what does this have to do with
<func>fflush()</func>?  The catch is that the terminal is most likely
"line buffered" (see the section on <link
dest="setvbuf"><func>setvbuf()</func></link> for more info), meaning
that it won't actually display anything until it prints a newline.  But
we're not printing newlines; we're just printing carriage returns, so we
need a way to force the output to occur even though we're on the same
line.  Yes, it's <func>fflush()!</func></p>

<code>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;unistd.h&gt; // for prototype for sleep()

int main(void)
{
	int count;

	for(count = 10; count &gt;= 0; count--) {
		printf("\rSeconds until launch: ");  // lead with a CR
		if (count &gt; 0)
			printf("%2d", count);
		else
			printf("blastoff!\n");

		// force output now!!
		fflush(stdout);

		// the sleep() function is non-standard, but virtually every
		// system implements it--it simply delays for the specificed
		// number of seconds:
		sleep(1);
	}

	return 0;
}</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="setvbuf"><func>setbuf()</func></link>,
<link dest="setvbuf"><func>setvbuf()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="stringref">
<title>String Manipulation</title>

<p>As has been mentioned earlier in the guide, a string in C is a
sequence of bytes in memory, terminated by a NUL character
('<tt>\0</tt>').  The NUL at the end is important, since it lets all
these string functions (and <func>printf()</func> and
<func>puts()</func> and everything else that deals with a string) know
where the end of the string actually is.</p>

<!-- TODO string image -->

<p>Fortunately, when you operate on a string using one of these many
functions available to you, they add the NUL terminator on for you, so
you actually rarely have to keep track of it yourself.  (Sometimes you
do, especially if you're building a string from scratch a character at a
time or something.)</p>

<p>In this section you'll find functions for pulling substrings out of
strings, concatenating strings together, getting the length of a string,
and so forth and so on.</p>

<!-- ================================================================
== strlen
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strlen">
<title><func>strlen()</func></title>
<short><p>Returns the length of a string.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

size_t strlen(const char *s);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>This function returns the length of the passed null-terminated string
(not counting the NUL character at the end).  It does this by walking
down the string and counting the bytes until the NUL character, so it's
a little time consuming.  If you have to get the length of the same
string repeatedly, save it off in a variable somewhere.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the number of characters in the string.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char *s = "Hello, world!"; // 13 characters

// prints "The string is 13 characters long.":

printf("The string is %d characters long.\n", strlen(s));</code>
</example>

<seealso>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== strcmp
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strcmp">
<title><func>strcmp()</func>, <func>strncmp()</func></title>
<short><p>Compare two strings and return a difference.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

int strcmp(const char *s1, const char *s2);
int strncmp(const char *s1, const char *s2, size_t n);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Both these functions compare two strings.  <func>strcmp()</func>
compares the entire string down to the end, while <func>strncmp()</func>
only compares the first <var>n</var> characters of the strings.</p>

<p>It's a little funky what they return.  Basically it's a difference of
the strings, so if the strings are the same, it'll return zero (since
the difference is zero).  It'll return non-zero if the strings
differ; basically it will find the first mismatched character and return
less-than zero if that character in <var>s1</var> is less than the
corresponding character in <var>s2</var>.  It'll return greater-than
zero if that character in <var>s1</var> is greater than that in
<var>s2</var>.</p>

<p>For the most part, people just check to see if the return value is
zero or not, because, more often than not, people are only curious if
strings are the same.</p>

<p>These functions can be used as comparison functions for <link
dest="qsort"><func>qsort()</func></link> if you have an array of
<type>char*</type>s you want to sort.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns zero if the strings are the same, less-than zero if the first
different character in <var>s1</var> is less than that in <var>s2</var>,
or greater-than zero if the first difference character in <var>s1</var>
is greater than than in <var>s2</var>.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char *s1 = "Muffin";
char *s2 = "Muffin Sandwich";
char *s3 = "Muffin";

strcmp("Biscuits", "Kittens"); // returns &lt; 0 since 'B' &lt; 'K'
strcmp("Kittens", "Biscuits"); // returns &gt; 0 since 'K' &gt; 'B'

if (strcmp(s1, s2) == 0)
	printf("This won't get printed because the strings differ");

if (strcmp(s1, s3) == 0)
	printf("This will print because s1 and s3 are the same");

// this is a little weird...but if the strings are the same, it'll
// return zero, which can also be thought of as "false".  Not-false
// is "true", so (!strcmp()) will be true if the strings are the
// same.  yes, it's odd, but you see this all the time in the wild
// so you might as well get used to it:

if (!strcmp(s1, s3))
	printf("The strings are the same!")

if (!strncmp(s1, s2, 6))
	printf("The first 6 characters of s1 and s2 are the same");</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="memcmp"><func>memcmp()</func></link>,
<link dest="qsort"><func>qsort()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== strcat, strncat
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strcat">
<title><func>strcat()</func>, <func>strncat()</func></title>
<short><p>Concatenate two strings into a single string.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

int strcat(const char *dest, const char *src);
int strncat(const char *dest, const char *src, size_t n);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>"Concatenate", for those not in the know, means to "stick together".
These functions take two strings, and stick them together, storing the
result in the first string.</p>

<p>These functions don't take the size of the first string into account
when it does the concatenation.  What this means in practical terms is
that you can try to stick a 2 megabyte string into a 10 byte space.
This will lead to unintended consequences, unless you intended to lead
to unintended consequences, in which case it will lead to intended
unintended consequences.</p>

<p>Technical banter aside, your boss and/or professor will be irate.</p>

<p>If you want to make sure you don't overrun the first string, be sure
to check the lengths of the strings first and use some highly technical
subtraction to make sure things fit.</p>

<p>You can actually only concatenate the first <var>n</var> characters
of the second string by using <func>strncat()</func> and specifying the
maximum number of characters to copy.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Both functions return a pointer to the destination string, like most
of the string-oriented functions.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char dest[20] = "Hello";
char *src = ", World!";
char numbers[] = "12345678";

printf("dest before strcat: \"%s\"\n", dest); // "Hello"

strcat(dest, src);
printf("dest after strcat:  \"%s\"\n", dest); // "Hello, world!"

strncat(dest, numbers, 3); // strcat first 3 chars of numbers
printf("dest after strncat: \"%s\"\n", dest); // "Hello, world!123"</code>

<p>Notice I mixed and matched pointer and array notation there with
<var>src</var> and <var>numbers</var>; this is just fine with
string functions.</p>

</example>
<seealso>
<p><link dest="strlen"><func>strlen()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== strchr, strrchr
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strchr">
<title><func>strchr()</func>, <func>strrchr()</func></title>
<short><p>Find a character in a string.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

char *strchr(char *str, int c);
char *strrchr(char *str, int c);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>The functions <func>strchr()</func> and <func>strrchr</func> find the
first or last occurance of a letter in a string, respectively.  (The
extra "r" in <func>strrchr()</func> stands for "reverse"--it looks
starting at the end of the string and working backward.)  Each function
returns a pointer to the char in question, or <type>NULL</type> if the
letter isn't found in the string.</p>

<p>Quite straightforward.</p>

<p>One thing you can do if you want to find the next occurance of the
letter after finding the first, is call the function again with the
previous return value plus one.  (Remember pointer arithmetic?)  Or
minus one if you're looking in reverse.  Don't accidentally go off the
end of the string!</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns a pointer to the occurance of the letter in the string, or
<type>NULL</type> if the letter is not found.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// "Hello, world!"
//       ^  ^   
//       A  B

char *str = "Hello, world!";
char *p;

p = strchr(str, ','); // p now points at position A
p = strrchr(str, 'o'); // p now points at position B</code>

<code>// repeatedly find all occurances of the letter 'B'
char *str = "A BIG BROWN BAT BIT BEEJ";
char *p;

for(p = strchr(str, 'B'); p != NULL; p = strchr(p + 1, 'B')) {
	printf("Found a 'B' here: %s\n", p);
}

// output is:
//
// Found a 'B' here: BIG BROWN BAT BIT BEEJ
// Found a 'B' here: BROWN BAT BIT BEEJ
// Found a 'B' here: BAT BIT BEEJ
// Found a 'B' here: BIT BEEJ
// Found a 'B' here: BEEJ</code>
</example>

<seealso>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== strcpy, strncpy
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strcpy">
<title><func>strcpy()</func>, <func>strncpy()</func></title>
<short><p>Copy a string</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

char *strcpy(char *dest, char *src);
char *strncpy(char *dest, char *src, size_t n);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>These functions copy a string from one address to another, stopping
at the NUL terminator on the <var>src</var>string.</p>

<p><func>strncpy()</func> is just like <func>strcpy()</func>, except
only the first <var>n</var> characters are actually copied.  Beware that
if you hit the limit, <var>n</var> before you get a NUL terminator on
the <var>src</var> string, your <var>dest</var> string won't be
NUL-terminated.  Beware!  BEWARE!</p>

<p>(If the <var>src</var> string has fewer than <var>n</var> characters,
it works just like <func>strcpy()</func>.)</p>

<p>You can terminate the string yourself by sticking the <tt>'\0'</tt>
in there yourself:</p>

<code>char s[10];
char foo = "My hovercraft is full of eels."; // more than 10 chars

strncpy(s, foo, 9); // only copy 9 chars into positions 0-8
s[9] = '\0';        // position 9 gets the terminator</code>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Both functions return <var>dest</var> for your convenience, at no
extra charge.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char *src = "hockey hockey hockey hockey hockey hockey hockey hockey";
char dest[20];

int len;

strcpy(dest, "I like "); // dest is now "I like "

len = strlen(dest);

// tricky, but let's use some pointer arithmetic and math to append
// as much of src as possible onto the end of dest, -1 on the length to
// leave room for the terminator:
strncpy(dest+len, src, sizeof(dest)-len-1);

// remember that sizeof() returns the size of the array in bytes
// and a char is a byte:
dest[sizeof(dest)-1] = '\0'; // terminate

// dest is now:       v null terminator
// I like hockey hocke 
// 01234567890123456789012345</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="memcpy"><func>memcpy()</func></link>,
<link dest="strcat"><func>strcat()</func></link>,
<link dest="strcat"><func>strncat()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== strspn, strcspn
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strspn">
<title><func>strspn()</func>, <func>strcspn()</func></title>
<short><p>Return the length of a string consisting entirely of a set of
characters, or of not a set of characters.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

size_t strspn(char *str, const char *accept);
size_t strcspn(char *str, const char *reject);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p><func>strspn()</func> will tell you the length of a string consisting
entirely of the set of characters in <var>accept</var>.  That is, it
starts walking down <var>str</var> until it finds a character that is
<emp>not</emp> in the set (that is, a character that is not to be
accepted), and returns the length of the string so far.</p>

<p><func>strcspn()</func> works much the same way, except that it walks
down <var>str</var> until it finds a character in the <var>reject</var>
set (that is, a character that is to be rejected.)  It then returns the
length of the string so far.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>The lenght of the string consisting of all characters in
<var>accept</var> (for <func>strspn()</func>), or the length of the
string consisting of all characters except <var>reject</var> (for
<func>strcspn()</func></p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char str1[] = "a banana";
char str2[] = "the bolivian navy on manuvers in the south pacific";

// how many letters in str1 until we reach something that's not a vowel?
n = strspn(str1, "aeiou");  // n == 1, just "a"

// how many letters in str1 until we reach something that's not a, b,
// or space?
n = strspn(str1, "ab "); // n == 4, "a ba"

// how many letters in str2 before we get a "y"?
n = strcspn(str2, "y"); // n = 16, "the bolivian nav"</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="strchr"><func>strchr()</func></link>,
<link dest="strchr"><func>strrchr()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== strstr
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strstr">
<title><func>strstr()</func></title>
<short><p>Find a string in another string.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

char *strstr(const char *str, const char *substr);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Let's say you have a big long string, and you want to find a word, or
whatever substring strikes your fancy, inside the first string.  Then
<func>strstr()</func> is for you!  It'll return a pointer to the
<var>substr</var> within the <var>str</var>!</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>You get back a pointer to the occurance of the <var>substr</var>
inside the <var>str</var>, or <var>NULL</var> if the substring can't be
found.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>char *str = "The quick brown fox jumped over the lazy dogs.";
char *p;

p = strstr(str, "lazy");
printf("%s\n", p); // "lazy dogs."

// p is NULL after this, since the string "wombat" isn't in str:
p = strstr(str, "wombat");</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="strchr"><func>strchr()</func></link>,
<link dest="strchr"><func>strrchr()</func></link>,
<link dest="strspn"><func>strspn()</func></link>,
<link dest="strspn"><func>strcspn()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== manpage header
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="strtok">
<title><func>strtok()</func></title>
<short><p>Tokenize a string.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;string.h&gt;

char *strtok(char *str, const char *delim);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>If you have a string that has a bunch of separators in it, and you
want to break that string up into individual pieces, this function can
do it for you.</p>

<p>The usage is a little bit weird, but at least whenever you see the
function in the wild, it's consistently weird.</p>

<p>Basically, the first time you call it, you pass the string,
<var>str</var> that you want to break up in as the first argument.  For
each subsequent call to get more tokens out of the string, you pass
<var>NULL</var>.  This is a little weird, but <func>strtok()</func>
remembers the string you originally passed in, and continues to strip
tokens off for you.</p>

<p>Note that it does this by actually putting a NUL terminator after the
token, and then returning a pointer to the start of the token.  So the
original string you pass in is destroyed, as it were.  If you need to
preserve the string, be sure to pass a copy of it to
<func>strtok()</func> so the original isn't destroyed.</p>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>A pointer to the next token.  If you're out of tokens,
<var>NULL</var> is returned.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// break up the string into a series of space or
// punctuation-separated words
char *str = "Where is my bacon, dude?";
char *token;

// Note that the following if-do-while construct is very very
// very very very common to see when using strtok().

// grab the first token (making sure there is a first token!)
if ((token = strtok(str, ".,?! ")) != NULL) {
	do {
		printf("Word: \"%s\"\n", token);

		// now, the while continuation condition grabs the
		// next token (by passing NULL as the first param)
		// and continues if the token's not NULL:
	} while ((token = strtok(NULL, ".,?! ")) != NULL);
}

// output is:
//
// Word: "Where"
// Word: "is"
// Word: "my"
// Word: "bacon"
// Word: "dude"
//</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="strchr"><func>strchr()</func></link>,
<link dest="strchr"><func>strrchr()</func></link>,
<link dest="strspn"><func>strspn()</func></link>,
<link dest="strspn"><func>strcspn()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="math">
<title>Mathematics</title>

<p>It's your favorite subject: Mathematics!  Hello, I'm Doctor Math, and
I'll be making math FUN and EASY!</p>

<p><emp>[vomiting sounds]</emp></p>

<p>Ok, I know math isn't the grandest thing for some of you out there,
but these are merely functions that quickly and easily do math you
either know, want, or just don't care about.  That pretty much covers
it.</p>

<p>For you trig fans out there, we've got all manner of things,
including
<link dest="sin">sine</link>,
<link dest="cos">cosine</link>,
<link dest="tan">tangent</link>, and, conversely, 
<link dest="asin">arc sine</link>,
<link dest="acos">arc cosine</link>, and
<link dest="atan">arc tangent</link>.  That's very exciting.</p>

<p>And for normal people, there is a slurry of your run-of-the-mill
functions that will serve your general purpose mathematical needs,
including
<link dest="abs">absolute value</link>,
<link dest="hypot">hypotenuse length</link>,
<link dest="sqrt">square root</link>,
<link dest="cbrt">cube root</link>, and
<link dest="pow">power</link>.</p>

<p>In short, you're a fricking MATHEMATICAL GOD!</p>

<p>Oh wait, before then, I should tell you that the trig functions have
three variants with different suffixes.  The "f" suffix (e.g.
<func>sinf()</func>) returns a <type>float</type>, while the "l" suffix
(e.g. <func>sinl()</func>) returns a massive and nicely accurate
<type>long double</type>.  Normal <func>sin()</func> just returns a
<type>double</type>.  These are extensions to ANSI C, but they should be
supported by modern compilers.</p>

<p>Also, there are several values that are defined in the
<file>math.h</file> header file.</p>

<deflist>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_E</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>e</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_LOG2E</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>log_2 e</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_LOG10E</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>log_10 e</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_LN2</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>log_e 2</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_LN10</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>log_e 10</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_PI</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>pi</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_PI_2</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>pi/2</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_PI_4</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>pi/4</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_1_PI</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>1/pi</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_2_PI</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>2/pi</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_2_SQRTPI</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>2/sqrt(pi)</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_SQRT2</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>sqrt(2)</p></deftext></def>
<def><deftitle><tt>M_SQRT1_2</tt></deftitle><deftext><p>1/sqrt(2)</p></deftext></def>
</deflist>

<!-- ================================================================
== sine
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="sin">
<title><func>sin()</func>, <func>sinf()</func>, <func>sinl()</func></title>
<short><p>Calculate the sine of a number.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double sin(double x);
float sinf(float x);
long double sinl(long double x);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Calculates the sine of the value <var>x</var>, where <var>x</var> is
in radians.</p>

<p>For those of you who don't remember, radians are another way of
measuring an angle, just like degrees.  To convert from degrees to
radians or the other way around, use the following code:</p>

<code>degrees = radians * 180.0f / M_PI;
radians = degrees * M_PI / 180;</code>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the sine of <var>x</var>.  The variants return different
types.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>double sinx;
long double ldsinx;

sinx = sin(3490.0); // round and round we go!
ldsinx = sinl((long double)3.490);</code>

</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="cos"><func>cos()</func></link>,
<link dest="tan"><func>tan()</func></link>,
<link dest="asin"><func>asin()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== cos
================================================================= -->

<manpage id="cos">
<title><func>cos()</func>, <func>cosf()</func>, <func>cosl()</func></title>
<short><p>Calculate the cosine of a number.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double cos(double x)
float cosf(float x)
long double cosl(long double x)</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Calculates the cosine of the value <var>x</var>, where <var>x</var> is
in radians.</p>

<p>For those of you who don't remember, radians are another way of
measuring an angle, just like degrees.  To convert from degrees to
radians or the other way around, use the following code:</p>

<code>degrees = radians * 180.0f / M_PI;
radians = degrees * M_PI / 180;</code>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the cosine of <var>x</var>.  The variants return different
types.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>double sinx;
long double ldsinx;

sinx = sin(3490.0); // round and round we go!
ldsinx = sinl((long double)3.490);</code>

</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="sin"><func>sin()</func></link>,
<link dest="tan"><func>tan()</func></link>,
<link dest="acos"><func>acos()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== tan
================================================================= -->

<manpage id="tan">
<title><func>tan()</func>, <func>tanf()</func>, <func>tanl()</func></title>
<short><p>Calculate the tangent of a number.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double tan(double x)
float tanf(float x)
long double tanl(long double x)</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Calculates the tangent of the value <var>x</var>, where <var>x</var> is
in radians.</p>

<p>For those of you who don't remember, radians are another way of
measuring an angle, just like degrees.  To convert from degrees to
radians or the other way around, use the following code:</p>

<code>degrees = radians * 180.0f / M_PI;
radians = degrees * M_PI / 180;</code>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the tangent of <var>x</var>.  The variants return different
types.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>double tanx;
long double ldtanx;

tanx = tan(3490.0); // round and round we go!
ldtanx = tanl((long double)3.490);</code>

</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="sin"><func>sin()</func></link>,
<link dest="cos"><func>cos()</func></link>,
<link dest="atan"><func>atan()</func></link>,
<link dest="atan"><func>atan2()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== asin
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="asin">
<title><func>asin()</func>, <func>asinf()</func>, <func>asinl()</func></title>
<short><p>Calculate the arc sine of a number.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double asin(double x);
float asinf(float x);
long double asinl(long double x);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Calculates the arc sine of a number in radians.  (That is, the value
whose sine is <var>x</var>.)  The number must be in the range -1.0 to
1.0.</p>

<p>For those of you who don't remember, radians are another way of
measuring an angle, just like degrees.  To convert from degrees to
radians or the other way around, use the following code:</p>

<code>degrees = radians * 180.0f / M_PI;
radians = degrees * M_PI / 180;</code>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the arc sine of <var>x</var>, unless <var>x</var> is out of
range.  In that case, <var>errno</var> will be set to EDOM and the
return value will be NaN.  The variants return different types.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>double asinx;
long double ldasinx;

asinx = asin(0.2);
ldasinx = asinl((long double)0.3);</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="acos"><func>acos()</func></link>,
<link dest="atan"><func>atan()</func></link>,
<link dest="atan"><func>atan2()</func></link>,
<link dest="sin"><func>sin()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== acos
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="acos">
<title><func>acos()</func>, <func>acosf()</func>, <func>acosl()</func></title>
<short><p>Calculate the arc cosine of a number.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double acos(double x);
float acosf(float x);
long double acosl(long double x);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Calculates the arc cosine of a number in radians.  (That is, the value
whose cosine is <var>x</var>.)  The number must be in the range -1.0 to
1.0.</p>

<p>For those of you who don't remember, radians are another way of
measuring an angle, just like degrees.  To convert from degrees to
radians or the other way around, use the following code:</p>

<code>degrees = radians * 180.0f / M_PI;
radians = degrees * M_PI / 180;</code>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns the arc cosine of <var>x</var>, unless <var>x</var> is out of
range.  In that case, <var>errno</var> will be set to EDOM and the
return value will be NaN.  The variants return different types.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>double acosx;
long double ldacosx;

acosx = acos(0.2);
ldacosx = acosl((long double)0.3);</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="asin"><func>asin()</func></link>,
<link dest="atan"><func>atan()</func></link>,
<link dest="atan"><func>atan2()</func></link>,
<link dest="cos"><func>cos()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== atan
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="atan">
<title><func>atan()</func>, <func>atanf()</func>, <func>atanl()</func>,
<func>atan2()</func>, <func>atan2f()</func>, <func>atan2l()</func></title>

<short><p>Calculate the arc tangent of a number.</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double atan(double x);
float atanf(float x);
long double atanl(long double x);

double atan2(double y, double x);
float atan2f(float y, float x);
long double atan2l(long double y, long double x);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Calculates the arc tangent of a number in radians.  (That is, the value
whose tangent is <var>x</var>.)</p>

<p>The <func>atan2()</func> variants are pretty much the same as using
<func>atan()</func> with <var>y</var>/<var>x</var> as the
argument...except that <func>atan2()</func> will use those values to
determine the correct quadrant of the result.</p>

<p>For those of you who don't remember, radians are another way of
measuring an angle, just like degrees.  To convert from degrees to
radians or the other way around, use the following code:</p>

<code>degrees = radians * 180.0f / M_PI;
radians = degrees * M_PI / 180;</code>
</description>

<rvalue>
<p>The <func>atan()</func> functions return the arc tangent of
<var>x</var>, which will be between PI/2 and -PI/2.  The
<func>atan2()</func> functions return an angle between PI and -PI.</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>double atanx;
long double ldatanx;

atanx = atan(0.2);
ldatanx = atanl((long double)0.3);

atanx = atan2(0.2);
ldatanx = atan2l((long double)0.3);</code>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="tan"><func>tan()</func></link>,
<link dest="asin"><func>asin()</func></link>,
<link dest="acos"><func>atan()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

<!-- ================================================================
== sqrt
================================================================= -->
<manpage id="sqrt">
<title><func>sqrt()</func></title>
<short><p>Calculate the square root of a number</p></short>

<prototypes>
<code>#include &lt;math.h&gt;

double sqrt(double x);
float sqrtf(float x);
long double sqrtl(long double x);</code>
</prototypes>

<description>
<p>Computes the square root of a number.  To those of you who don't know
what a square root is, I'm not going to explain.  Suffice it to say, the
square root of a number delivers a value that when squared (multiplied
by itself) results in the original number.</p>

<p>Ok, fine&emdash;I did explain it after all, but only because I wanted
to show off.  It's not like I'm giving you examples or anything, such as
the square root of nine is three, because when you multiply three by
three you get nine, or anything like that.  No examples.  I hate
examples!</p>

<p>And I suppose you wanted some actual practical information here as
well.  You can see the usual trio of functions here&emdash;they all
compute square root, but they take different types as arguments.  Pretty
straightforward, really.</p>

</description>

<rvalue>
<p>Returns (and I know this must be something of a surprise to you) the
square root of <var>x</var>.  If you try to be smart and pass a negative
number in for <var>x</var>, the global variable <var>errno</var> will be
set to <tt>EDOM</tt> (which stands for DOMain Error, not some kind of
cheese.)</p>
</rvalue>

<example>
<code>// example usage of sqrt()

float something = 10;

double x1 = 8.2, y1 = -5.4;
double x2 = 3.8, y2 = 34.9;
double dx, dy;

printf("square root of 10 is %.2f\n", sqrtf(something));

dx = x2 - x1;
dy = y2 - y1;
printf("distance between points (x1, y1) and (x2, y2): %.2f\n",
	sqrt(dx*dx + dy*dy));</code>

<p>And the output is:</p>

<screen>square root of 10 is 3.16
distance between points (x1, y1) and (x2, y2): 40.54</screen>
</example>

<seealso>
<p><link dest="tan"><func>hypot()</func></link></p>
</seealso>

</manpage>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="complexno">
<title>Complex Numbers</title>
<!-- man cabs, complex -->
</sect1>

<sect1 id="time">
<title>Time Library</title>
</sect1>

<!-- ================================================================
== manpage header
================================================================= -->
<!-- <manpage id="">
<title><func></func></title>
<short><p></p></short>

<prototypes>
</prototypes>

<description>
</description>

<rvalue>
</rvalue>

<example>
</example>

<seealso>
</seealso>

</manpage> -->

</guide>

